[Music]
materials we'll be using a glue scissors
and cart and I've explained all about
these in the introduction to this series
of tutorials so there are three basic
types of parallel folds this is the
parallelogram that we looked at in
parallel folds part one and when when
the page is flat the parallelogram goes
flat the other two types they stay in
dimension when the page is flat so first
kind this is the basic parallel fold
equal the lengths on each side of the
pop-up are both the same and the
distance out from the central gully of
the base they're both the same so on the
Left you've got a short length in a long
one and on the right you've got a short
length and a long one
we'll be dealing with that today and the
other one is the asymmetric parallel
fold so here's the asymmetric parallel
fold all four lengths are different
you've got a short length on on the base
and a long one and a long length on the
pop-up and the short one on the left
you've got a short base long piece on
the pop-up on the right you've got a
long piece on the base and a short piece
on the pop-up and the base plus the plus
the pop-up on each side paid balance so
as you close it the pop-up closes so
we're going to be dealing with these two
now I say you have to make one of these
basic parallel columns you take a base
sheet fold it in half crease the base
really thoroughly and then we take a
piece to build with let's have pink bit
okay I'm going to actually show you
three different variations of this so
we'll just cut off three pieces so
there's no importance to the dimensions
of these they're just as you know
whatever whatever you want for your
design basically so this is the first
time I'll make so take the piece of card
fold this in half it's symmetrical so
it's folded in half creased really
thoroughly and then with it folded in
half fold gluing tabs onto the outer
edges fold these thoroughly open it up
and fold fold the creases individually
and the same on the other end from there
night I always just trim off the corners
right and this it's depending on what
you want in your design it can be it can
be glued down really close to the spine
so you've got a tall thin shape or you
can go flatter and flatter further and
further you can even stick it out so
it's flat then it'll still work I'll
show you one of those in a book in a
minute so we'll just glue this on so
we've got the two lengths on the pop-up
they're both the same so we need the two
lengths on the base to be the same as
well so put just put glue just on one
end so use the glue on one end smear it
to the crease and glue it down I'm going
about two centimeters out actually I
want it a bit higher up the page so I'm
gonna put two more on the same page so
there's that soundly glued put the put
the pop-up into it's close position put
glue on the other end
smear it up close the base so it finds
its natural sticking position there it
is the basic symmetric parallel fold the
two loads on the pop-up are the same and
the two lengths on the base of the same
so here's the second variation so this
is it it's very similar to the first
except it's got a flat plain on the top
so I'll turn this around so you can see
see how it works better so again we take
this the strip of card we fold it in the
middle we fold it well though in this
case it's not quite as important we we
fold a tab onto each end again we want
it all symmetrical so we fold the gluing
tabs with the whole piece folded in half
so here are the gluing tabs fold them
fold them well fold them individually
fold them backwards
but with though is I'll just trim off
the corners right and in this case to
get the flat piece on the top you just
put a bit of put a bit of glue into the
into the top of the top of the pop-up so
there's some glue though and close it
down and this one because I'm making it
with such a short piece you can't go
really wide so we're going to have it
much closer closer to the spine the tabs
can either be sticking out like this or
you can fold them away underneath I
think actually in this case is quite
interesting having them on the outside
so I'm going to glue them put the glue
on the outside and glue one side first
so in order to get the symmetry we'll
glue one side first and glue it into
place so here we are
and then we close the close the pop-up
piece down put glue on the other other
tab smear it to the edges and close the
base so it finds its natural sticking
positions so there's the second
variation the third one is even more
simple the third one fold it in half and
this time there are no gluing terms this
time we're making a curved shape these
are quite unusually pop-up so this time
we just put a little bit of glue on the
outside edges of the the pop-up we can
do both at the same time but so just
smear the glue onto the onto the bottom
of the outside edges of the popper
and then set it into there this is
actually slightly fat so I'm just going
to take a srimad piece off so I'm fit
within your page right put that into the
flush into the gully close the base open
it up and we're getting a curve shape so
these are three three variations on the
symmetric parallel fold or give you
different different potential when
you're doing your pop-up designs oh I'll
show you something of a book now so this
is this is robots by yumping Caskey if
we look at the final spreads this this
is their parallel folds this is an
equilateral parallel for both their both
sides are the same it actually the
lengths on the pop-up are the same as on
the on the base so when the base is flat
the whole pop-up post flow so that
that's an equilateral parallel fold
there if we look to the other end of the
book and there's just a very small
example here this the head I think she's
a robot the head of the robot is
parallel folds and her head scarf is so
these are the same type of paranoia
folds as we made the first one right
here we turn it round we can see it more
clearly here's the head of the robot
we've got two you've got the head is one
parallel fold and the head scarf is
another as as you close it you can see
it and then this one the lengths on the
pop-up are bigger than the notes on the
base that's why it stands up in 3d and
there's a final one I've got here that
roaring lion tales by ron van der Meer
and this this is a parallel fold it's a
massive parallel fold
it's got added added creases which are
what sculpt the shape so if you pull it
out pull out these folds you can see
that what we've got here
it's just one big big parallel fold as
you as you close it the whole thing the
whole thing goes flat and by adding
these extra creases he's done a
beautiful sculptural effect on this
pop-up so he's created a real 3d shape
out of the parallel fold by adding
adding extra creases
he's also cut a hole in one side so he's
really gone to turn you can look inside
and and see inside the structure the
palm trees they're coming up through
slots the slots are another another
tutorial later in this series that's the
end of the symmetric parallel fault now
I'll show you the asymmetric parallel
fold this is an example all four lengths
are different the shot to a short in a
long length on the base and I shortened
a long length on the on the pop-up and
it's important to have the lower length
on the pop up above the short length on
the base and vice versa the short length
on the pop-up above the long length I
can actually do a really quick diagram
of how this how this works mathematic
knees basically you have the here's your
here's your book and you've got the
pop-up is something like this so you
could call it if this was one this
length was four this was three this was
two so from one side from here to here
well weigh as 1 plus 4 and the other way
3 plus 2 let me just show you it's got
to balance on each side so on the left
on the base you got 3 on the pop-up
you've got 2 on the other side and the
base you've got 1 on the pop up you've
got 4 so you've got 5 the sum is 5 on
each side the other thing to make it
stand up the pop-up has to be bigger
than the base so on the base you've got
3 plus 1 on the pop-up you've got
four plus two so the base length is
total total for the pop up length for
total is six so now we'll just make one
of those baseships bonded in power and
this film this one is similar to the
ones we just made there are actually two
variations so take a piece of card to
make them reads and this will do so just
I'll just cut a narrow strip off on one
side so we folder tab onto each end and
then fold them really thoroughly as
usual cut off the corners so you don't
snag against anything and then fold fold
1/3 D and the third parallel fold you
know somewhere well off center so there
it is so we've got a short length and a
long length now in this type you again
simulated a parallelogram
you actually line up the central fold of
the pop-up with the gully of the base
mark the mark the short sides you only
need a little mark here because you're
not going to be sticking to that mark
you just need to know how long the short
side is and now the crucial bit you flip
it over so you're going to be sticking
the long side somewhere somewhere in
that region so put some glue on that
long tab
and the important thing is don't stick
it don't stick it to the mark if you
stick it to the mark what you'll get is
a parallelogram so in this case you
stick it closer to the spine than the
mark so just I'll just stick it about
halfway and according to where you stick
it it will give you different shapes so
stick it about half way fold the whole
piece into its closed position
put glue on the other tab here we are
smear it right up to the crease and then
folder fold the base shut so this one is
actually gonna stick out how it's
slightly this is this is just classic
when you're doing a rough you'll
regularly get the bits that stick out so
there it is this is the asymmetric
parallel for both the asymmetric
parallel fold and the symmetric parallel
fold they're both really useful for
other mechanisms for more complicated
method mechanisms there the analyzed
structure for floating planes and you
can raise planes above the base using
these two and then building
parallelograms onto them and we will
deal with that in another tutorial
on floating planes so I'll just I was
just going to show you how to add
another asymmetric bendy shape so in
that case yeah you take the take your
card and in this case you actually fold
it in the middle so you make a crease
right in the middle followed that pretty
well and then you put you put glue on
one one end you putting it on the
outside you you just glued quite a short
amount of the card on the other end
again on the outside you glue a longer
piece of the card so you know just smear
it well over the the surface and then
you you put that put the end flash into
the gully glue it down
and then close the piece and and shut
the base and so what you get with this
is a an asymmetric curving shape these
aren't these these pop-ups with straight
edges these are rigid shapes that you
can build on easily this type is a it's
not a it's not a rigid shape it bounces
around so these aren't good for
structure they're good for decoration or
you can stick small pieces onto them
that all just up at interesting angles
but they're not they're not structures
for for extending like like the like the
rigid shapes so yeah you know you can
have pieces like this that are just out
you can have pieces like like this sort
of jutting out that come up at the
interesting angles so you can play
around with them like that but you
cannot build you cannot build rigid
structures under them so that's
asymmetric parallel form so I'll just
show you a couple of examples oh this is
yeah this is another another more
extreme example of that one we just made
and then this was one I made this is
some this is an asymmetric parallel form
so it's got a big window cut in it
there's another asymmetric parallel form
underneath it and then this is another
asymmetric parallel forms built into
this gully here so if you actually look
at it and on you you can see how this is
both the the inner brown one and the
bigger green one they're both built into
the gully created by the car so this is
this is the asymmetric parallel fold in
action and then I've got a very small
one I can show you in this book bow-wow
by Chuck Murphy and in this case it's
underneath the circle and you open it at
the top this is just this is a v-fold
the cyclist but the dog the structure
the dog is a
loading plain this is a dog floating
parallel with with the base sheet but if
you look at it end on you'll see that
there's an asymmetric parallel folds
used to raise a parallelogram and the
dog is stuck to the top of the
parallelogram so that's an example of
using asymmetric parallel files to raise
a floating plane so that's it for this
this tutorial and everything I've said
is explained in this book pop-up design
and paper mechanics it's explained in
greater detail
[Music]
[Applause]