[Music]
materials we'll be using a glue scissors
and cart and details about all these
materials is explained more fully in the
introductory tutorial so extra creases
this is a basic default with added
creases that create two more planes
which can be built extended and a gully
which can be built into this one is a
parallel fold again we've got extra
creases which create another gully that
you can build into also creates extra
planes that can be extended this one
again this is a basic V fold and in this
case the the extra creases rather than
being used to create the gully like in
this one they've been trimmed down to
create two tabs and that's lifting at
another whole pair of planes which again
creates another gully that you can you
can build on so let's just start by
building one of these
[Music]
so we take a base sheet fold it in half
no need to measure no need to score with
this type of card this is 160 GSM
photocopy card so it's really easy to
fold just crease it really really
thoroughly fold it back on itself a few
times crimp it again and again that's
your base sheet now we'll take a another
piece of card to make the pop-up so we
just take about a third of the card just
just by eye just roughly 2/3 of the card
fold it in half crease it really
thoroughly and then the v-fold you want
to crease is coming up as an angle so we
start this is the folded line start
about half an inch above the base fold
this up as an angle crease it really
well and fold it back on itself you can
cut cut that corner out cut this to make
a couple of tabs trim off those corners
just for neatness and so here we have
the basic basic v-fold pop-up shape the
creases all make it downward pointing
arrow now you've got a choice we're
going to add two more creases basically
they they roughly follow the the line of
that one you can make it absolutely
parallel or you can make it a bit coming
down a bit more steeply this is the
original fold so we fold it over crease
it well fold it back on itself
open it up and now this will fold back
down so then we stick this onto the page
this is what we're going to get and
again as we know very faulty can play
with the play with the angle of the
piece on the page as you as you make it
tighter than the gully that you've
created the extra gully folds points
back down law or as you go wider the
gully lifts up so you can play with the
angles on these folds and it it affects
the overall shape so we'll start by just
gluing this down I'll just cut these a
bit more a little sharper so they don't
overlap on the spine and so we've got
symmetry on the pop-up the angles
between the central crease and the
creases on the viewing tabs they're both
the same each side and now we want
symmetry on on the base and being a
v-fold this will fold down in the
direction at the vias pointing so this
will fold down like this so to get the
symmetry we just just glue one side
up near the up near the top of the page
make sure the central central crease on
the pop-up is aligned with the gulley
glue it down so that's one side glued
down firmly moving nicely they can fold
the whole piece into its closed position
and put glue on the other tab smear the
glue to the the up to the crease and
then fold the page shut so here here we
have this this V fold now has an extra
gully created on top which you can build
into or you can add on you may just
choose to take some odd piece of card
like this and you can just stick it on
like this or like this or you know if I
can fold it and you can glue that glue
that into the gulley anywhere you like
and you're starting to actually sculpt
with this shape so I'll just glue that
one in
so I put it in and as you build with as
you build with pop-ups every time you
add a piece close the base and press it
firmly so as you go step by step you're
sure that the whole structure is sound
to this but it's working that it fits in
that the folds work that the gluing is
working and this in this case we might
as well just add another another little
them parallel fold on top of that so you
can cutter cuts another piece of card
fold it in half add a couple of tabs
trim them this is going to fit into that
gully that we've just created so she's
going to fit in like this so just put a
bit of glue on on one tab smear it to
the edges a little bit this is a
parallel fold so it's got everything's
got to be parallel with the crease in
the gully stick it into place put glue
on the other tab smear the glue fold the
whole piece shut so it finds its natural
natural sticking position
so here it is it's a basic very fold
with added creases which is then lifting
up to more planes which has then got a
parallel fold stuck into the top of it
so you can you can look at this either
with a the pop up the base sheet is a
base with the pop up rising from it or
you can look at it like this so this is
the base sheet as a background did the
pop up coming forward from it or we've
made here is an abstract shape it's just
playing playing with the sculpture and
again now you've actually from the
original v-fold that was two planes
you've now actually got six planes and
so any of these can be expended you can
come up off the blue one you can come up
off the second gully where you can come
up come off the of the parallel fold
it's all just abstract at this point and
it's just yeah use your imagination see
where you want to go the other way you
can play with this is that rather than
creating two more planes with a Guddi
you can create flaps so I just make one
of those to show you how that works so
take a piece of card fold it in half
crease it really well
really crimp the creases fold them back
on themselves crimp them again and again
so this this is your base sheet now
we'll build onto that it's a piece of
card here we'll just take the piece of
cards no measuring just cut it by eye
you know whatever size you want fold it
in half crease it really well fold it
back on itself crimp it and again and
then we're making a basic V fold so this
is the fold line starting about half an
inch up you fold it up at an angle away
from the away from the central fold fold
it back on itself and you open this up
you've got the basic V fold design
you've got the all the creases
make a downward pointing arrow so now
we'll just trim that to make gluing tabs
for the v-fold trim that a bit more
sharp so it won't overlap and spine so
this is your basic V fold piece now
let's make a fold at the top so come in
like this this up this time I've got
more or less parallel with the with the
original ones you can come in more or
less at any angle whatever angle you
come in at it'll affect the shape that
you make but there's no right there's no
wrong in this case I want the top to be
slightly narrower so I'm going to trim
this down coming from the corner I'm
going to cut in like that and then I'm
going to trim these into two more tabs
so now we've got a v-fold with tabs at
the top so we fold fold fold down in the
direction they're pointing so we want
this to be up near the top of your page
we've got symmetry so the two angles on
each side of the central fold are both
the same on this pop-up piece now we
want symmetry on the page so take the
glue just put glue on one tab to start
off with
right then work out whether you want a
really sharp shape or a wider one from
going up roughly 45 degrees but again it
doesn't matter it just depends depends
what shape you want to create
now put glue on the other tab and close
it down so here we've got a v-fold with
a pair of tabs on the top and you can
build into this so you take another
piece fold it in half
I might actually prefer it long way so
no I fold it in half crease it well and
this piece where as in this one we made
before because you're working working
with a gully you can only make these
pieces jut out that the angles created
by the gully in this case because you've
got tabs you can actually see saris
around so you may choose to have it
coming up really steep well you may
choose to have it it can even be
pointing down this way and the tabs will
stick onto it there so you can just see
sorry to round and decide what shape you
want and then in this case you don't
glue one tab and then the other you put
put glue on both tabs at the same time
so put the glue on both the tabs smear
it to the edges
and decide what angle you want it um
really I'm gonna go more or less
horizontal and you just fold the whole
piece down so there we have it and again
you can you can use this either as a
bass coming up looking at it like that
you might prefer to look at it like that
you might even prefer to look at it like
that or like that it's up to you and
again you know you have actually got
another gully it's not a very um it's
not a very deep one but you can build
into this or again you can just stop you
know sticking extra pieces on that just
out just ass all around it and make an
interesting shade and so that that's all
I'm going to show you in terms of making
things there's quite a nice one here
this is the same idea but this is a this
is a v-fold the red v-fold lifting up
the Bluebirds so that's just like the
piece we just made I'll now show you
some some examples of extra creases in
books
so this one is championed Kowski
dinnertime here's the FIR this is just
an elementary pop-up this is a v-fold
with added creases so here you can see
it's just a v-fold the whole thing will
just close and then with the added
creases you get two more two more planes
created the same with the gorilla again
it's a v-fold closes down the added
creases make it you can pop it up and
you get two more planes and a more
interesting sculptural shape same again
here same again here the other book I'd
like to show you this is some monster
Islands Monster Island Ron Vandermeer
and here's a spread this is a basic
right angle v-folds but at the top we've
got added creases creating this
dimension up here this is just you can
fold it down you can fold it down flat
but by adding these extra creases
he's created a more interesting
sculptural shape at the top of the
pop-up and then this one is this roaring
lion tails but Ron Vandermeer and this
is a this is a parallel fold with extra
creases so if we pull this straight so
you can see this is just a very brand
parallel fold the whole school just as
fold flat and by adding these extra
creases he's he sculpted the whole shape
and made it into a really solid 3d shape
rather than just a sort of hollow tent
and then lastly I'd like to show you
this is robots by yen pien Kowski and
the last spread in the book is this
rocket rising from the clouds the cloud
is a basic parallel fold and the rocket
this is a belt onto a v-fold
so here's a v-fold it's got added
creases that create this gully and the
the rocket is a parallel fold built into
the gully and the nose of rocket that's
a mod modification that I'll show you in
another another tutorial
and so everything I've talked about in
this tutorial is is covered in this my
book pop-up design and paper mechanics
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]