[Music]
the same as in 1 & 2 we need cart
this is photocopy cards 160 GSM scissors
need no explanation and glue the same
same glue as was explained in part 1 so
there are five kinds of v-fold the first
is the the right angle default this is
explained in part 1 the second is the
acute angle v-fold these also explained
in part 1 the third is the point of view
fault this is V Falls part two and the
two single V fold is also V Falls part
two and the fifth and final type of V
fold this is the asymmetric V fault
this is too tall it's all about the
asymmetric v-fold most v-folds most pop
up mechanisms are centered on the on the
spine fold and they're completely
symmetric so the asymmetric V fold is
useful it takes the takes the design off
center and is why it just makes the
whole thing much more interesting those
are it's very varied so I've got a whole
array of them here everyone different it
all depends on the angles on the pop-up
and the angles on the page and in each
case all four angles are different
scientists show enough an array of these
[Applause]
they're very hard to actually work out
what the what shape you're going to make
so you either need to know it's good to
make just make trial and error make a
whole series alternatively I'll explain
in a minute in my book there's a
reference set that you can look at so so
here they are as you can see they the
angles just moved all over the place and
have an enormous amount of potential
right take a face sheet and fold it well
so here's a base sheet thoroughly
creased as always counts can't stress
that enough fold it back on itself and
again and again so opens and closes nice
and smoothly we'll take a sheet of cards
cut it in half fold it in half there
most nice pop-ups when you want the two
angles on each side in the pop-up piece
to be symmetric so most pop-ups most
v-folds having folded it in half you
then fold the tabs on to it in this case
all four angles are different the two
angles on the pop-up and the two angles
on the base they're all different so in
this case having folded it in half just
cast a little wedge wedge acid the
bottom corner this is your folded sides
so we just just cut a wedge out and now
we now we fold the gluing tabs on to it
so start with one side fold it maybe you
make quite a quite a large angle and
maybe trim those chill nose corners down
a bit more
so there we are and then the other one
let's make it much more acute so we'll
come right up like this so we've got the
two angles on your pop-up piece are
completely different and again you know
just cut that into the gluing time now
you put this on the put this on the page
this is the very fold always falls in
the direction that the V is pointing
it's going to be on your page something
like this
so it's going to fold down forward so
you need to position it up near the top
of the page
line up the central crease with the
gulley on the base so the central crease
of the pop-up is lined up with the the
crease of the base now mark the small
angle so you on your pop-up you've got a
big angle and a small angle but this
small angle so here's the line now this
is a crucial bit you flip the whole
thing over so now you've got the big the
big angle on the pop-up above the small
angle on the page so if you were to glue
it down following that line you could
glue it down like this in which case the
whole pop-up would lie flat when the
when the page is flat but in this case
you want it to be in dimension you want
it 3d so you move this move this piece
in slightly and it's just got to be
glued down somewhere between the line
you've marked and the central central
gully of the the page and according to
where you can learn it that would affect
though the shape that you end up with so
I'll just glue that
the really crucial thing with this is to
make sure you flip it over so you get
the large the large angle on the pop-up
sticking over the small angle on the
page so here we are they make sure that
you're gluing tab isn't going over there
over the central gully if it does just
trim it back a bit so that's that one
glued down now put the whole thing into
its closed position
but glue on the other tab smear it right
up to the crease bit more glue and then
fold it shut
so here we have an asymmetric free fold
[Music]
all four angles are different the two
angles on the pop-up a difference and
the two angles on the on the base are
different so now I'll just do a little
little diagram to explain how that how
that works so if we take this is the
this is the base sheet with the with the
crease down the middle and I'll just
copy this one we've got the angle that
it's glued down to is here this is where
the one side is glued we'll call that
angle a on the other side we've got a
much much wider angle we'll call that
angle B on the pop-up piece is the is
the dotted line we've got a big angle so
that's here with the with the tab and
we've got a small angle here with the
tab and this is the rest of the cards
so we call these C this is angle C and
this is angle D right the crucial thing
is the angles on each sides the angles
on the pop-up plus the base must be the
same on the left and on the right so in
this case a plus C must equal B plus D
and the other factor is the angles on
the pop-up must be bigger than the
angles on the on the base so C plus D
must be bigger then a plus B I'll just
turn that around so you can so you can
see it clearly so a and B are the angles
on the base C and D are the angles on
the pop-up
so a plus C must equal B plus D so that
you have balance and so that the whole
thing stands up and doesn't lie flat on
the page the angles on the on the pop-up
must be bigger than the angles on the
page so C plus D must be bigger than a
plus B I've got a few books that
demonstrate the asymmetric v-fold first
dinah topia so here it is the pop-up
that the dinosaur is rising from the
dinosaur is rising from an asymmetric
v-fold so you'll see that the angle here
on the pop-up is bigger than the angle
on the page and the angle here on the
pop-up is smaller than the angle on the
page so that's the first one the the
angle on the pop-up the two angles on
the pop-up are the same as the two
angles on the page so when the page is
flat the pop-up is flat the second book
is B where de storybook wolves
beware the storybook wolves and in this
one this is by a paper engineering by
Corrine Fletcher I think she's a really
great paper engineer so here it is this
fairy falling out of the page you can
see the central the central gully on
that on the ferry is really off-center
so this is an asymmetric v-fold you can
see it's asymmetric the central crease
of the of the default is not lined up
with the spine it's coming up with an
angle so this is the asymmetric V fold V
folds fold down in the direction the
direction that the V is pointing so
there is as you close the page the V
fold folds up into it normally pop-ups
are always built further up the page so
everything remains within there within the frame of the book
the frame of the book the way their head
is lifted up that's just a small
parallel fold built into the gulley
whether the v-fold attaches to the page
you can see that if I turn it round
slightly you can see that's a parallel
fold raising her head and the last one
I'd like to show you is the little fish
who cried shark and this has got a
massive messy shark at the end these
both the head and the tail they're both
asymmetric v-folds you can see the
central crease on both these pop-ups
lean lean away from the central gully of
the of the book and the tail this is a
this is a counter fold so and again it's
actually an asymmetric one so you can
see that's giving you an extra pair of
extra pair of planes so that's a
symmetric V folds and all of that is
explained in even more detail in in this
my book pop-up design and paper
mechanics and there's a whole list of
all these ones that I've showed you at
the beginning and all the angles on them
are explained in this book
[Music]
[Applause]