[Music]
blue scissors and card and the details
of these are all explained in the
introductory tutorial so there are three
kinds of parallel fault the first and
possibly the most important is the
parallelogram the parallelogram is a
funny one when you open the base flat
the parallelogram goes flat it's only in
dimension when the bases it's on is is
not flat the other two are the symmetric
parallel fold so the length on each side
of the pop-up are exactly the same and
the asymmetric parallel folds where the
two lengths on the pop-up are different
so these last two we'll be doing in part
two parallel folds this this tutorial is
completely devoted to the parallelogram
parallelograms can be used quite nicely
in combination so here's an example you
can use them this way with the base as a
base card as a base and a background in
which case this has created a whole
series of planes and you can stick
bigger pieces of card onto any of those
either vertical or horizontal so you can
play with it that way
you can also play in it this way so yeah
lots of potential there so first I just
like to show some examples of the
so this is Yankee and Cassidy's haunted
house on the first page we have this
staircase this is actually two
parallelograms this is the first one
built into the gulley created by the
book this is the second one built into
the gulley created by the first
parallelogram and when the page goes
flat the whole pop up goes flat the
second one this is a symmetric parallel
fold so this fridge here the two sides
on each side they're both the same so
when the page is flat the pop-up stands
up this is the third one this is one of
the other uses of the parallelogram is
it it creates that you can use it to to
make moving arms move and we'll be
looking at that later in this tutorial
the next page well this is a this is a
curved shape that we look at in a much
later tutorial but down here at the bath
that is a that is a parallelogram you
can look at it straight on as the page
goes flat the bath goes flat so that's
haunted house the other one I'd like to
show you is sergeant charge
this is sergeant charge illustrated by
Bill Bolton and if we look at this one
this is a parallelogram being used to
turn over these figures so these are all
slotted on but the basic strip that
they're all attached to that is a
parallelogram when the page is flat the
parallelogram is flat but it gives a
really nice action to all those soldier
ants or whatever they are so now I'll
show you how to make a parallelogram
[Music]
usually parallelograms are used values
like this so we get a base sheet fold it
in half fold it really funny take a
piece of card to build with we'll use
pink so here's a pink piece just cut off
a strip from one end doesn't matter how
wide and then we need to actually make
it slightly shorter so maybe cut off an
inch or something and in this case
folder a gluing tab onto each end so
gluing tabs should be roughly 1
centimeter wide or half an inch unless
you want them to be showing in which
case you can make them much bigger so
here it is and then you follow the
crease noting the middle that would be
that would give you a symmetric parallel
fold in this case because it's a
parallelogram just make the make the
crease say a third of the way along or
1/4 of the way and of so you've got two
different lengths so this time put the
central crease on to your on to your
central put the crease on the pop-up on
to your central guarding of the base
mark where the where the crease lies
either end it doesn't matter flip it
round this is the important thing with
these you flip it round so that the long
side is over the short piece on the base
and the short side is over the long one
and then you can because the
parallelogram lies flat when the whole
whole base is flat you can actually glue
both ends at the same time we just put a
bit of glue on there
and the tabs can actually point in or
out it that it really doesn't matter if
you want them
it's where the crease lies that's
important you have the tab in it's
hidden from view when you open it or you
can have it out as part of the design so
there it is as the as the page closes
the parallelogram closes it's good good
idea to really give it a good squash
afterwards just in case you're you're
measuring or gluing is a bit off so here
it is and you can use it this way or you
can use it this way or you can use it
this way so I'll just show you a couple
of examples where books are made using
parallelograms with the base as a base
and the background so the first one I'd
like to show you is cabassa
puss-in-boots and the last spread is
this fantastic fairytale coach made
completely out of parallelograms if you
turn it turn it and look at it end on
you'll see it's all parallelograms as
you close it so the parallelograms
closed down the other one I'd like to
show you is this one don't go out
tonight by Babbitt Cole and in this one
every spread in this book is the same
the same type of design as you pull down
the base so the pop-up appears and if
you look at these from end on or
sideways on you'll see that the whole
the whole thing is a series of
parallelograms as you open and close it
the parallelograms becomes 3d
okay no I'd like to show you how to
build with parallelograms onto a v-fold
so here's a v-fold made in one of the
v-fold tutorials and we're going to
build a parallelogram
there's gullies to build into there's a
gully here and on both sides whether
we're the v-fold is attached to the page
there's also a gunny in the middle in
the middle of the v-fold but again you
can see the gully closes as the v-fold
closes so we'll just take a couple of
pieces of the fridge discards take a
couple of slices off it so you take the
strip of cards start by making a fold on
each end crease the fold thoroughly and
the these two files 1h and these are the
two glowing tabs and the folds are both
parallel and then you make another fold
roughly 1/3 of the way in it really
doesn't matter it depends what type of
what type of shape you wanting to create
but I'll go for roughly a third of the
way along so that's a third parallel
crease crease it really well and then
I'll just trim off these corners it's
not not mechanically necessary but it
think it stops them stops the jagged
bits snagging on things it seems to just
glue slightly better and so now you have
a choice you can either put the parallel
can parallelogram can either be built
onto the pop-up like this and a long
long and low parallelogram or it can be
built onto it like this so it's a tall
parallelogram by luck I've got it more
or less the same height as a as the
v-fold
so we're going to build a tall
parallelogram so we start by putting the
the crease of the central crease of the
parallelogram into the gully
mark weather where the crease lies it's
always the crease that you measure to on
pop-ups so we mark where the crease lies
and then the crucial bit we flip it over
so you're going to glue the long sides
to the mark you've measured the short
side and you actually glue the long side
so we put glue on that tab smear it
right to the right to the crease and
then glue the crease to the mark now you
put the whole parallelogram into its
closed position
so the parallelograms in its closed
position but glue on the other tab and
then you can just close the base and it
finds its natural speaking position so
there we go we've got parallelogram
rising from the page though we've build
another one into this this gully here so
I'll take another piece of card might as
well just straighten this up slightly
and maybe make it slightly shorter okay
we put a tab on each chain just like the
other one another one somewhere not in
the middle again maybe a third of the
way
cut off the tabs as the quarters as
usual we get on of glue that into this
this is going into this gully so put the
done it again on just by luck I've just
got it to the right length therefore any
longer and it wouldn't work so I put
this crease into the central gully I
mark where the fold lives so there's the
fold the crease line and now again the
crucial bit you flip it around so I've
measured the short lengths flip it round
I'm going to stick the long length on to
that mark so I put glue on the glue on
that tab on the long side and glue it to
the glue it to the mark there you go and
this this could be high up on the v-fold
or low down on the v-fold doesn't matter
and now you fold the whole piece into
its close position put glue on the other
tab smear it to the crease
then you shut the hole
shut the whole base and the tab will
find its natural sticking position
okay I'd just like to explain the the
lengths involved in this so every pop-up
spans a gully so in this case this this
parallelogram is spanning this gully and
so every pop-up must be balanced on each
side of the gully so in this case it's
this length this length from the gully
on the base to where the long side
sticks down this length is the same as
this length and on the on the long side
this length the height between where the
top up the parallelogram is stuck to the
v-fold this height is the same as this
height and so that's what's giving you
that's what's giving you balance when
the whole thing is closed you see from
the gully on the v-fold you've got the
height of the v-fold plus a short bit of
the parallelogram and then you've got a
short bit of base and the longer to the
parallelogram and if you look at this
other one it's the same this this short
distance on the v-fold is the same as
this short distance on the parallelogram
and this long distance on the v-fold is
the same as the long distance on the
parallelogram so that's how you get
balanced with these parallelogram shapes
and I can actually show you this as well
on the on the earlier parallelogram
model I've just pointed out this this
short side on the parallelogram is the
same as this short side on the base and
the long side on the parallelogram is
the same as the long side on the base so
on the left-hand side you've got a short
length plus a long one on the right-hand
side you've got a long length plus a
short and so the two sides balance okay
I'll just show you the v-fold in
conjunction with the parallelogram this
book is jungle days by Helen bomber and
she's done a very imaginative use of the
v-fold here
this v-fold rather than it rising up
from the base this is coming forward
from the base so the surface of the
water is made with a v-fold in this case
all the other creatures the ducks the
kids the dog they're all based on
parallelograms lifted by the v-fold
so if we look at it end on here you can
see this there's parallelograms raised
raised by the v-fold raised by the
gulley here where the v-fold joins the
page and it's the same on the other side
you hear we got the dog and the and the
kids
these are parallelograms attached to the
v-fold so as the base closes as the
parrot as the v-fold goes down so the
parallelogram to close down the other
use of the parallelogram is for moving
arms so I'll just show you a quick way
of doing that in actual fact moving arms
is a highly complex aspect of pop up and
there will be a whole tutorial on moving
arms alone but it's an important use of
the parallelogram so I've just shown you
a quick basic way of doing it so here's
here's the base sheet and then we need a
piece to pop up from it so here's a
piece we just cut a chunk off the ends
we'll just make that slightly shorter
put tab on each ends these are parallel
folds with tab on each end and then trim
up the corners and in in this case
there'll be a third fold but this this
third fold keep it keep it quite near
the end so maybe you know one inch two
centimeters something like that
so make that third parallel fold fold it
really really well and now you take this
you fold it shut so this is this is font
closed and you just fold down the top
corner so you're folding this top edge
you close to close the parallelogram you
fold down this top edge to come down
against the the crease so you've got
that that little corner folded over and
this is actually a counter fold so you
can push that in and close it down so
there you are you've got the you've got
the counter fold now you put that this
is going to glue onto the bottom of your
page so put the line up this this middle
crease of the of the pop-up piece mark
where they crease it the the short end
lies on the page so you you just mark
where that crease nice now crucial with
parallelograms you flip it over so
you're not going to stick though you're
gonna stick the long ends to that mark
make sure that make sure this double
triangle is up because it's a
parallelogram it goes flat when the base
is flat so you can put glue on both ends
at the same time smear the glue up to
the crease
and you can glue that glue that down so
you you measure the short distance but
you're gluing the long side too to the
mark and you can glue the other end at
the same time with the whole piece flat
so here it is the whole piece is flat as
you as you close the page just make sure
it all all works nicely and now you you
can push that that counter fold in and
fold it shut right now you can attack
I've made this ever so slightly rough
actually now you can take a piece to use
as a moving of the cut this slightly
slightly narrower this is going to stick
on to the small the triangle on the
small side so we just cut that corner
off and stick this on to that on to that
triangle so this sticks down there and
as the as the base closes I'm not sure
yeah that's fine
as the base closes the the arm moves
down and you can actually enhance the
visual effect if you if you put a elbow
in the arm so if we stick an extra piece
on there you'll get an impression of
even more movement so glue that on there
and now you've dropped the you've got
the moving on and there's a very good
example in the haunted house that I
showed you
oh yeah here's the haunted house and it
was on the third page here is it's the
parallelogram opening and
guerilla moves and it's actually really
interesting if you look at these moving
arms you've got the the triangle that's
on the short side of the parallelogram
and you've got the triangle on the long
side this arm attached to the short side
as the page closes it rotates against
the page this arm attached to the long
side of the parallelogram as the page
closes it flips over so this is this is
quite important about moving arms moving
arms a very sophisticated mechanism
there's a lot more to it you need to
watch the moving arm tutorial which
comes later it's all in my book pop-up
design from paper mechanics and it
explains parallelograms and moving arms
in great detail
[Music]
[Applause]