this tutorial is about V vaults one of
the most important mechanisms in pop-up
design and so I'll just start by talking
about the materials that we're going to
be using in this tutorial so most
important is the card this is 160 GSM
photocopy card and you can use heavier
cards or you can even use heavy
cartridge paper in this case is 160 GSM
the other materials is glue very
important the best glue is solvent based
adhesive water-based will work and the
problem with water based is it goes up
more slowly so it's harder to work with
and it also tends to buckle the card so
you don't get so such pleasing results
you can also use stick glue and stick
glue is very clean very quick very easy
and for making rough dummies it's
absolutely fine but if you make a pop-up
that you want to last that's important
to you stick glue tends to dry out crack
and then your pop ups will fall apart
the other thing you need is a pair of
scissors any scissors will do card glue
scissors that's all you need in this
tutorial and most of the others so all
pop ups need a base and so we start by
just folding a sheet of card in half
crease it really thoroughly I can't
overemphasize how important it is to to
crease the card so fold it fold it back
on itself
crease it again this is your base
there is there are three principles in
popper the first principle is that every
pop-up must span a gully and the first
gully is the spine fold down the middle
of the base the second principle is that
every pop-up must span a gully so it
must be stuck down on each side and it
must be balanced on each side of the
gully so here's the gully in this case
with v-folds which is what we're talking
about in this tutorial it's the angles
that balance so on the pop-up the angles
on each side are the same and on the
base the angles on each side are the
same the third principle is that every
pop-up creates gullies so here we have a
pop-up this is a gully created in the
middle and here's a parallelogram stuck
into it so it's the pop-up rising the
gully the basic gully opening raises the
pop-up and then the pop-up Scully
opening raises the pop-up within it and
here's another example this is again
it's another v-fold but in this case the
the base opening opens the gully raises
the pop-up the pink bit and that these
two parallelograms are stuck into the
gullies created by the father so the
three principles every pop-up mass
Panigale every pop-up must be balanced
on each side of the gully every pop-up
creates gullies which more power works
can be stuck into so those are the three
principles so now we move on to the
actual v-fold
there are five kinds of v-folds this is
the first one this is the right angle
v-fold so the angles on the pop-up are
both 90 degrees so that's the first one
this is the second one this is the acute
angle v-fold so the angles on each side
of the gully both less than 90 degrees
that's the the second type of v-fold the
third this is the pointy v-fold so it's
a variation on the acute angle v-fold
really but the the top rather than
standing proud it comes down to to hit
the page that's the third type of v-fold
again the angles on each side of the
central crease are the same the fourth
type of v-fold
this is the obtuse angle default so in
this one the angles on the pop up on
each side of the central crease they're
both more than 90 degrees that's the two
things Greek default and finally we have
the asymmetric v-fold
so is the asymmetric v-fold in this one
all four angles are different the two
angles on the pop-up are different the
two angles on the base are different but
still the angles on the left on the
pop-up plus the base equals the angles
on the right on the pop-up and the base
so again we've got we've got balance so
those are the five types of v-fold
in this tutorial we're just working with
these two the right angle v-folds and
the acute angle v-fold so i put these
other ones away they come up in a later
tutorial
so we start by making one we'll make a
right-angle v-folds so we take a base
sheet folded thoroughly creased and then
we'll take another sheet of cards to
make the actual pop-up let's try a pink
piece here just just cut it in half by
eye doesn't really doesn't really matter
fold it in half crease it thoroughly
fold it back on it so I can't
overemphasize how important it is to
thoroughly crease all the folds on pop
ups and then we want the angles on each
side this is this is going to be your
pop-up standing up like this on your
page and so we need the angles on each
side to be equal so in this case we fold
it shut and fold some creases onto the
bottom and again crease them well and
then you have to cut out the the corner
so from that point where the the creases
converge you just cut out that angle and
and cut off that bit so you've got these
gluing tabs this shape and now now
you've cut that piece out you can fold
these back individually and crease them
really thoroughly so that's that one and
this one okay so we've got our pop-up
piece and the angles each side that are
matching so we know we've got balance
there now we need to stick it to the
page the way part these V folds fold
down they fold down in the direction at
the V is pointing so this one is going
to fold down this way so it needs to be
near the front of your front of your
page and then the angle that you stick
it to the to the base it can be anything
you like you can have a shape like this
where it's really tight close together
or you can open it up wide and wider you
can go as wide as you like it mustn't be
at 90 degrees to the spine if it's 90
degrees to the
buying the whole thing can just fall
down so it's got to be less than 90
between the central gully and where it's
gluing to the page and the way you glue
these just start by gluing one tab so we
put put a bit of glue on it
smear it right to the right to the to
the fault I use my little finger so it's
not to get glue glue on my other hand
other fingers so I can still use all the
other fingers too to make things line up
the central gully of the pop-up with the
central gully of the base stick that bit
down and just make it make it fun now
you put glue on the other tab smear this
up to the crease the edges aren't really
important in pop up this always
decreases you need to smear the glue
right up to the crease any measuring you
do always to the crease fold it shut and
here is the right angle V fold this type
of V fold the right angle V fold is
really good for architectural subjects
so here's one this is one I've made this
is a this is a right angle V fold
raising a garden it's raising
parallelograms so this is the first
parallelogram it's glued into this gully
of the V fold and then this is the
second parallelogram glued into this
gully
so as the page closes the whole
configuration lifts up and falls away
this book fantastic fairytales by Ron
van der Meer
is all made of this type of right angle
V fold so if we just skim through it is
the first one this is the V fold raising
this parallelogram house to the next
page this is the V fold in this case
it's more open
than the previous one and again you've
got a parallelogram here and you've got
parallelograms here glued into this
gully where the v-fold glues to the page
this is the third one again this is a
right angle V fold and this little table
here this is a right angle V fold
raising a parallelogram here as the page
closes you can see the main one this is
folding down in the direction that the
that the V is pointing and the table
that's folding down in the direction of
these pointing so they both fold away
from each other and this is the final
one
this is a big big right angle V fold
with an array of parallelograms this is
the first one glued into this gulley
this is the second one built into this
gulley this is the third one built into
this gulley as the page closes the whole
whole slew folds away when you look at
the pop-up it's not absolutely flat it
tends to be at a slight angle so when
you look into this right angle V fold
that way the fact that the page isn't
completely flat doesn't matter visually
but if you look at it the other way
around so you're looking into the
mountain fold of it if the page isn't
absolutely flat the whole thing sags
towards you so that might be what you
want is part of your design but
otherwise the way you cure that is you
move into the the acute angle V fold so
here's an acute angle V fold the
mountain fold is pointing towards you
the base doesn't have to be completely
flat and yet it still stands up stands
up upright it's also good in this type
if you're using it to the right angle V
fold because it's near the front of the
page you don't have much room for
illustration text or whatever you want
whereas this type the acute angle V fold
because the V fold down towards you you
can position the whole thing near the
back of the page and then you've got
plenty of space you know on your base
for more illustration more pop-up text
whatever you like
so you can just look at this book
this is beware of the storybook wolves
the paper engineering is by M Corrine
Fletcher lovely book here's a fairy made
of a fairy made of a v-fold the it's
actually an asymmetric v-fold the v-fold
is pointing up the page so as you open
the page the fairy falls out of the book
and as you close the page they're very
you know jumps back into the book so
that's a really delightful use of that
that type of design you know and the
fact that the v-fold folds down in the
way it's pointing so now I'll show you
how to make the acute angle v-fold so
you get get your base sheet and fold it
in half crease it really thoroughly
again and again right here's the piece
we're going to make the the piece we're
gonna make the pop-up with so fold this
in half crease it really well and then
whereas with the right angle V fold we
just folded straight across third from
the bottom edge in this case we're going
to fold it up at an angle so starting
about half an inch up above the bottom
corner this is the folded side fold it
up at an angle and the angle you fold is
that will determine the shape of the
pop-up that you that you make fold it
back on itself when you open this up the
creases should be giving you a downward
pointing arrow it's really important
that the arrow points down then if the
arrow points up less an obtuse angle
v-fold anyway we'll cut these cut the
bottom in to gluing tacks
right this is this is going to be your
pop-up this is going to stand like this
on the page look at how it is when it's
on the page whether the tabs are
actually going to overlap like if you're
going quite tight like this they're
overlapping so just trim a bit more off
so with these you can decide how how
close you want the the tabs to be
sticking to the spine they've both got
to stick the same distance from the
spine but or quite wide the wider you go
the more the the pop-up will lie down
and then the closer tighter you make the
angle the more the pop-up will stand up
so just again to make sure these the
angles on the page match we start by
gluing one side so this is glowing up
near the top of your page so you stick
down one side make sure the central
crease is lined up with the gully of the
base so here it is fold it into its
close position put glue on the other
other tab making a mess here
and then close the place
there is the acute angle v-fold so the
thing to understand with these to
control it if you want the v-fold to
stand up more either you make the angles
on the base smaller or you make the
angles on the pot that bigger if you
want it to lie down more either you make
the angles on the base bigger or you
make the angles on the popups smaller
and that's really that's really key so
now we just look at a few examples of
how these how these pop-ups are used
here's here's one this is the red bit
the red bit is an acute angle v-fold and
it's got a couple of tabs cut into the
top and that's holding this is raising
up this Bluebird so the whole thing
folds down forwards as you close it
here's another example this is a this is
an acute angle v-fold
raising a figure we've got a couple of
counter faults built into the into the
gullies where it where it joins the page
and those are what what raised up the
arms and we'll just have a look at a
couple of a couple of books so this one
is Sergeant charge and in this one if
you look at this this is the the V folds
are here you can see there's a V fold
underneath maybe looking at it sideways
on you can see there's a pair of v folds
and they're actually raising a whole
series of of parallelograms and the V
fold folds away in the direction it's
pointing so the V fold is pointing up
the page so as you open it it's pretty
good the way it makes all the figures
come down so this is some v-folds used
to raise parallelograms is another
example here this is planes of the Aces
designed by I think it's Keith Mosely
and this is a this is that this is the V
fold and
it's raising up this Center plane that
the plane is completely made of
parallelograms so this is the this is
the v-fold this is the galley the
parallelograms are built into that gully
is a whole array of parallelograms being
raised up up vertically as there as the
page opens and great bit of design that
one and then finally there's a couple
here there's some monster islands this
is I think from 1979 or 1980 it's one of
the really early sort of second wave of
pop-up books and so this one this is a
this is a spread based on the right
angle v-folds and you've got a couple of
counter folds at the top here so this
whole bit it could be like that and by
putting these extra extra creases in it
comes down and gives you this extra bit
of dimension that's a right angle refold
and then on the next page this is a
acute angle default giving you this
monster and the way these arms work
that's all to do with slots we do that
in adult another tutorial
finally and there's a little book called
pop fill pop fill and the first first
spread it's got a whole lot of these are
really tiny v-folds with just one side
projected up to give these these some
tree tops so as you are going to close
it yeah you can go on and the trees turn
into and they start being replaced by
machines they're still defaults all the
buildings are parallelograms that's
another tutorial so that's it for this
tutorial
everything I've talked about is in this
this book pop-up design and paper
mechanics and everything I've talked
about today is in this book
you