scissors glue burns card the details
about these are all explained in v-folds
tutorial part 1 so there are five kinds
of default the first is the the right
angle v-folds this is explained in part
1 the second is the cute angle default
this is also explained in part 1 the
third is the pointed v-fold this we're
going to deal with in this tutorial the
fourth is the obtuse angle v-fold this
also we're going to deal with in this
tutorial and finally it's the asymmetric
v-fold this will be in v-folds tutorial
part 3 okay we're going to start by
making a pointed v-fold so start with
the base sheet fold the card in half no
need to measure no need to score with
this weight of cards at 160 g SN crease
it really thoroughly fold it back on
itself crease it again you can't crease
it too much so fold it back up itself a
couple more times and really crease it
well this is this is the base sheet
having it well creased means that the
pop-up will move more sweetly so we
might as well make a say a red one take
your sheet of cards again no need to
measure just cut it in half
fold it in half no need to measure just
do it by eye again as with all creases
crease it really really thoroughly fold
it back on itself
this time you make the fold from corner
to corner so you're doing a diagonal
fold corner to corner with it with it
folded in half so there's no wrong way
to do this because it's symmetrical it
can go either way fold it back on itself
again so when you open it up you have an
arrow all three all three creases are
meeting at the same point and those
extra creases the diagonal ones again
you can reinforce those one more time
now this is going to sit on your on your
page like this so one question is how
tight you want it what actual shape of
pop-up you want do you want a really
tight V fold or do you want a really
flat shape you can even go all the way
flat and it will still work so I'll go
for something like this the second
question is what you do with the with
the flaps you can either cut them down
into narrow narrow flaps of v underneath
it or you can leave them out wide and
you can use these these folds for making
that counter folds in so I'm going to do
that turn it into counter folds so we
start just cut into the cat into the
folded edge so say we just do a couple
like this here fold it over just crease
it well this one I've made the two cuts
at different lengths so that will give
us a slightly different shape in the
pop-up open it up and push those through
so that's one this is the other
so that's the that's the shape we're
going to get on it on the top crease you
can now do the same on the bottom crease
the bottom two creases so if we want it
all symmetric we do it all with the two
folds to two outer flaps fold it up make
some cuts into those just do a couple
here there's a lot of room for
creativity in this and understanding
something really a really simple option
but you know if you make your own you
can really play around with these you
can make them longer narrower multiple
there's all sorts of options so we'll
open this one up push these through one
two three four push these ones down so
this is a shape you're gonna have now
again you can decide that you want these
other flaps left as part of the design
or you might decide to trim them down so
I'm going to trim them down so again
I'll just follow this sort of very
pointy pointy shape so I'm just going to
cut it like this to the to the point so
this is what your pop-up is going to be
like now again you can decide you want
it really tight or do you want quite a
quite a wide shape so I'm gonna go for
something like this
start by gluing one side with all these
all pop ups you need you need symmetry
so we're just glue one side smear the
glue right up to the crease I tend to
use my little finger so then all my
other fingers stay free from glue and I
can I can use them to touch other things
without cars sticking to them so there
we go
stick one side down maybe move it in a
little bit more make sure the central
crease is lined up with the Central
Valley of the base
fold the whole thing into its closed
position
put glue under put glue on the other tab
smear the glue to the to the creases
fold it into its closed position and
close the base so here it is now you
might you might leave these counter
folds just as they are they're just part
of the design alternatively you can use
them as muscle to lift other pieces of
cards so we'll just try playing around
with that for a bit so take a piece of
card just cut some pieces to play with
and these can these can actually be any
size any shape it's completely up to you
I'm just doing something fairly random
here so we put the put the glue on the
smallest surface you don't put it on the
big surface which is sticking on you you
put the glue onto the small small
surface of the counter fold and you can
just stick the stick the extra piece
onto that might as well do the same on
the other side the card is slightly you
can see it's slightly thin for this this
length of piece so I might just trim
that down in a minute they put one on
there and you can actually use the other
the other faces of the counter fold as
well so let's just put the couple coming
up just so you can see all the all the
possible options so put glue on those
two so you have a piece of lifting up
like that and another one on here
lifting up like that and you can also
play with these these some planes that
we've created
in the top four so I'll just make one
more really narrow piece that will fit
into that fold it in half though again
it doesn't actually need to be in half
you can have a phone anywhere on it if
you wanted a more asymmetric design just
make a fold somewhere somewhere along
this strip put the glue in and you can
just tuck that in there and stick it in
and after you've added these pieces shut
the base and press it firmly so that all
that for the gluing is so and so there
we are
this is just an abstract shape so you
can actually look at it anywhere there's
no right way there's no wrong way so you
might choose to look at it like that you
might choose to look at it like that
equally maybe this or even this it it's
just abstract yeah abstract shape so you
can do what you like with it equally
these two planes can be extended so so
you take a couple of just a couple more
small pieces and I'll put the glue on
the into the video
so you can have a piece coming out like
that and maybe another one similar on
the other side a bit uneven though then
I trim that down so there's a point of
v-fold and now I'll just show you a
couple of examples this this spread is
all made with this is a pointed v fault
with the end cut off and you've got
counter folds on each side which are
used to raise the arms and legs this is
another point of view fold it's got the
very tip cut off that's making the head
so this is a couple of pointed v-folds
there it goes in books this is some ten
little monsters and in this one here's
the point of V folds in this case yeah
here here are the flaps that have been
used to stick it down they're part of
the design and in fact rather than doing
counter falls pieces have been stuck on
to each side that jut forward and the
head is just saying and you can look at
it end on and see how it works
and you get it straight on this is using
the book as background this is jungle
days by Helen bomber and the trunk of
the tree is appointed V fold and it has
as other v-folds added to the sides to
raise the figures it's got slots cut
into it to make these limbs stick out
and anyway the point of this is the
trunk of the tree is appointed V fold
and lastly from Puss in Boots this is by
Wojtek cabassa czechoslovakian working
in the 60s this this is two point of
view files this is an obviously
appointed v fault
this is a point of view fold with a
large amount cut away v files have
converging creases that all lease at the
same points on the spine so if you
follow this crease here and this one and
this one you'll find they all meet at
the same
from this bond so that's the point of a
fold now we'll move on to the obtuse
angle default this one but this is the
obtuse angle V fold the angles on each
side of the central crease of the pop up
are more than 90 degrees it's quite an
unusual mechanism you don't see it very
often I'll show you how to make one of
these so take a base crease it well this
time we take out take the other half
sheet of cards fold this in the middle
crease it crease it thoroughly and then
this time here's the is the folded edge
start about a third of the way up and
fold it downwards to the outer edges of
the card so here it is fold it well when
you when you open this up you see that
you've got an upward pointing arrow
mostly with with them acute angle
v-folds you'll have a downward pointing
arrow that's the normal that's what
you're usually looking for but in this
case the creases form an arrow pointing
up now cut out the from the point where
all the creases meet you just cut out a
thin wedge you cut gluing tabs on to the
bottom cut off the end oh I'll make that
a bit bit tighter so this is your this
is your obtuse angle we let this
re-crease these these sand falls a bit
and doing a bit more thoroughly if your
folds up thoroughly enough crease leave
the pop-up either won't open
clothes very well so it's very important
to increase it well this is going to sit
on your page like this you can go quite
wide you can go quite tight but if you
go too wide you'll see it starts lifting
off the page so according to the angles
you've made and that will dictate how
wide you can go so again we stick down
one side this symmetries is always
important by cutting the by making the
fold with it folded in half we get
symmetrical angles on the pop-up and now
the way we stick it down we're going to
get symmetrical angles on the pant so
there it is stick down one side make
sure the the central crease in the
pop-up is lined up with the gully gully
of the base fold the whole thing shut to
press it well put glue on the other the
other tab
smear the glue right up to the crease
that's pretty important
fold it sucks there we go the two single
V fold this is this is quite interesting
because the the central crease of the
pop-up falls backwards the other one
that the central gully will lean
backwards is the right angle V fold
so here's a version these are the right
angle v-folds the angles on the bottom a
90 degrees whereas on this one they're
more than 90 and these ones because it
because it falls down backwards and I
think the higher you want the pop up
that the nearer the front it has to be
yeah I'll just show you in a couple of
examples of obtuse angle V faults this
is one you can see it just leans back
slightly so that that works nicely for
this design I've got one book that has
them as a to tangle V fold and a pointed
V fold in it so here it is the the book
is Bow Wow by Chuck Murphy and this this
is it under the triangle you open it up
there's the pyramid is a pointed V fold
and the dog is an obtuse angle V Falls
and the best way to see this is to look
at the back of the design and there you
can see the the central crease of the
dog is leaning backwards so the dog is
obtuse angle V fold the pyramid is a
pointed v-fold and that fits at some
v-folds part to all the information I'm
giving you is in booths my book pop-up
design from paper mechanics