materials we'll be using a glue scissors
and cart and details about all these
materials is explained more fully in the
introductory tutorial so extra creases
this is a basic default with added
creases that create two more planes
which can be built extended and a gully
which can be built into this one is a
parallel fold again we've got extra
creases which create another gully that
you can build into also creates extra
planes that can be extended this one
again this is a basic V folds and in
this case the the extra creases rather
than being used to create the gully like
in this one they've been trimmed down to
create two tabs and that's lifting it
another hole pair of planes which again
creates another gully that you can think
of build on so let's just start by
building one of these
so we take a base sheet fold it in half
no need to measure no need to score with
this type of card this is 160 GSM
photocopy card so it's really easy to
fold just crease it really really
thoroughly fold it back on itself a few
times crimp it again and again that's
your base sheet that would take a
another piece of card to make the pop-up
so we just take about a third of the
card just just by eye just roughly the
folded card fold it in half crease it
really thoroughly and then refold you
want two creases coming up at an angle
so we start this is the folded line
start about half an inch above the base
fold it up at an angle crease it really
well and fold it back on itself
you can cut cut that corner out cut this
to make a couple of tabs trim off those
corners just for neatness and so here we
have the basic basic v-fold pop-up shape
the the creases all make a downward
pointing arrow now you've got a choice
we're going to add two more creases
basically they they roughly follow the
the line of that one you can make it
absolutely parallel or you can make it a
bit coming down a bit more steeply this
is the original fold so we fold it over
crease it well fold it back on itself
open it up and now this will fold back
down
so when we stick this onto the page this
is what we're going to get and again as
we know v40 can play with the play with
the angle of the piece on the page as
you as you make it tighter than the
Guddi that you've created the extra
gunny folds points back down low or as
you go wider the gully lifts up so you
can play with the angles on these folds
and it it affects the overall shape so
we'll start by just gluing this down
I'll just cut these a bit more a little
sharper so they don't overlap on the
spine and so we've got symmetry on the
pop-up the angles between the central
crease and the creases on the gluing
tabs they're both the same each side and
now we want symmetry on on the base and
being a v-fold this will fold down in
the direction that the vias pointing so
this will fold down like this so to get
the symmetry we just just glue one side
first
up near the up near the top of the page
make sure the central central crease on
the pop-up is
glue it down so that's one side glued
down firmly moving nicely I can fold the
whole piece into its closed position and
put glue on the other tab smear the glue
to the the up to the crease and then
fold the page shut
so here here we have this this V fold
now has an extra guard created on top
which you can build into or you can add
on you may just choose to take some odd
piece of card like this and you can just
stick it on like this or like this or
you know I can fold it and you can glue
that glue that into the gulley anywhere
you like and you're starting to actually
sculpt with this shape so I'll just glue
that one in
so put it in and as you build with as
you build with pop-ups every time you
add a piece close the base and press it
firmly so as you go step by step you're
sure that the whole structure is sound
that it's but it's working that it fits
in that the phones work but the that the
gluing is working and this in this case
we might as well just add another
another little them parallel fold on top
of that so you can scatter just another
piece of card fold it in half add a
couple of tabs trim them this is going
to fit into that gully that we've just
created so she's going to fit in like
this so you just put a bit of glue on on
one tab smear it to the edges a little
bit this is a parallel fold so it's got
everything's got to be parallel with the
crease in the gully stick it into place
put glue on the other tab smear the glue
fold the whole piece shut so it finds
its natural natural sticking position so
here it is it's a basic V fold with
added creases which is then lifting up
two more planes which has then got a
parallel fold stuck into the top of it
so you can you can look at this either
with the pop-up the base sheet of the
base with the pop-up rising from it or
you can look at it like this so this is
the base sheet as a background did the
pop-up coming forward from it all we've
made here is an abstract shape it's just
playing playing with the sculpture
and again now you've actually from the
original v-fold
that was two planes you've now actually
got six planes and so any of these can
be extended you can come up off the blue
one you can come up off the second gully
where you can come up come off the of
the parallel fold this all just abstract
at this point and it's just yeah use
your imagination see where you want to
go the other way you can play with this
is that rather than creating two planes
with a gully you can create flaps so
I'll just make one of those to show you
how that works take a piece of card fold
it in half crease it really well really
crimp the creases fold them back on
themselves crimp them again and again so
this is your base sheet now we'll build
onto that it's pretty cold here so just
take the piece of cards no measuring
just cut it by eye you know whatever
size you month fold it in half crease it
really well fold it back on itself crimp
it down again and then we're making a
basic V fold so this is the fold line
starting about half an inch up you fold
it up at an angle away from the away
from the central fold fold it back on
itself and you open this up
you've got the basic V fold design
you've got the all the creases make it
downward pointing arrow so now we'll
just trim that to make gluing tabs for
the v-fold trim that a bit more sharp so
it won't overlap and spine so this is
your basic V fold piece now let's make a
phone at the top
so come in like this this up this time
I've got more or less parallel with the
with the original ones you can come in
more or less at any angle whatever angle
you come in at it'll affect the shape
that you make but there's no right
there's no wrong in this case I want the
top to be slightly narrower so I'm going
to trim this down coming from the corner
I'm going to cut in like that and then
I'm going to trim these into two more
tabs so now we've got a v-fold with tabs
at the top so we fold fold fold down in
the direction they're pointing so we
want this to be up near the top of your
page we've got symmetry so the two
angles on each side of the central fold
are both the same on this pop-up piece
now we want symmetry on the page so take
the glue just put glue on one tab to
start off with then work out when you
want a really sharp shape or a wider one
I'm going at roughly 45 degrees but
again it doesn't matter it just depends
depends what shape you want to create
now put glue on the other tab
and close it down so here we've got a
v-fold with a pair of tabs on the top
and you can build into this so you take
another piece fold it in half
I might actually prefer it long way so
now I fold it in half crease it well and
this piece where as in this one we made
before because you are working working
with a gully you can only make these
pieces jut out that the angles created
by the gully in this case because you've
got tabs you can actually see saris
around so you may choose to have it
coming up really steep or you may choose
to have it it can even be pointing down
this way and the tabs and will stick
onto it there so you can just see sorry
surround and decide what shape you want
and then in this case you don't glue one
tab and then the other you put put glue
on both tabs at the same time so we put
the glue on both the tabs smear it to
the edges
beside what angle you want it on really
I'm gonna go more or less horizontal and
you just fold the whole piece down so
there we have it and again you can you
can use this either as a base coming up
looking at it like that you might prefer
to look at it like that you might even
prefer to look at it like that or like
that it's up to you and again you know
you have actually got another gully it's
not a very um it's not very deep one but
you can build into this or again you can
just start you know sticking extra
pieces on that just out just ass all
around it'll make an interesting shape
and so that that's all I'm going to show
you in terms of making things there's
quite a nice one here this is the same
idea but this is a this is a v-fold the
red v-fold lifting up the Bluebirds so
that's just like the piece we just made
I'll now show you some some examples of
extra creases in books
so this one is jumping Kowski dinnertime
here's the fir this is just an
elementary pop-up this is a v-fold with
a decreases so here you can see it's
just a V fold the whole thing will just
close and then with the added creases
you get two more two more planes created
the same with the the gorilla again it's
a v-fold closes down the added creases
make it you can pop it up when you get
to more planes and a more interesting
sculptural shape same again here same
again here the other book I'd like to
show you this is some monster Islands
Monster Island Ron Vandermeer and here's
a spread this is a basic right angle
default but at the top we've got added
creases creating this dimension
this is just you can fold it down can
fold it down flat but by adding these
extra creases he's created a more
interesting sculptural shape at the top
of the pop-up and then this one is this
roaring lion tales by Ron van der Meer
and this is a this is a a parallel fault
with extra creases so if we pull this
straight so you can see this is just a
very grand parallel fold the whole
single just this fall flat and by adding
these extra creases he's he sculpted the
whole shape and made it into a really
solid 3d shape rather than just a sort
of hollow tent and then lastly I'd like
to show you this is robots by MP and
Kowski and the last spread in the book
is this rocket rising from the clouds
the cloud is a basic parallel folds and
the Rockets this is a belt onto a v-fold
so here's a v-fold it's got added
creases that create this gully and the
the rocket is a parallel fold built into
the gully and the nose of rocket that's
a mud modification that I'll show you in
another another tutorial and so
everything I've talked about in this
tutorial is is covered in this my book
pop-up design and paper mechanics