this tutorial is about using the
qualities of the v-fold to create extra
tall structures as the v-fold closes it
folds down forwards when you have a
floating plane built onto it that comes
down nearer to the page and so then you
can build another view fold on it
pointing in the other direction and that
comes down taking another floating plane
again lower to the page then you can
build onto that and so you can build a
sort of zigzag effect by building these
reverse pointing B folds so this is a
pretty crude version I made and I'll
show you how I made this in a minute but
before that I just like to run through
some books that have really amazingly
tall default structures in them first
book I'd like to show you is David
Pelham's like a Lisa breeze and it's got
a really amazing structure at the very
end this is one of these tower
structures if you look at it from behind
you can see in here there is a v-fold
goes down stands up that is raising a
floating plane here which has got other
v-folds built on it it's hard to
actually see into it but here you can
see this is another V fold and the arms
are attached to those planes jutting out
and this at the very top well you can
see this is a v-fold with another V fold
on top of it and then this the face is a
parallel foam so yeah nice design
the next one I'd like to show you is
this is a really extraordinary tall
structure that there's no way we could
explain it in this tutorial but I just
thought you'd really like to see this
one the way it rises up so high above
the bubble page if we look at the
structure behind that you can see it is
a v-fold here raising a floating plane
here but the the actual measurements the
measurements at this side and this side
and on these days is quite complicated
so just enjoy the height and your future
future work so we'll explain it and then
we've got this one this is another book
by Matthew Reinhart jungle book another
extraordinary spread here it is again it
comes up really high above the page this
is a v-fold
these are parallelograms being raised by
it you look behind and you can see it's
an array of parallelograms and people
raising this floating plane which has
got another v-fold
and another so that's how you get this
sort of constant interaction that's all
based on the fact that the v-fold folds
down forwards which gives you a plane
that you can then build on and go higher
and higher so you end up with a
structure which is higher than the total
height of the page of the book so the
next one this is a very pretty little
book big bang pop by philip foo french
book it's really amazing colors but the
only thing i wanted to show you in this
one is is this little pop-up that that
comes up amazingly high for the
considering the size of the page this is
a v-fold that's coming forward and in
effect this is a floating plane but the
dimensions on the base on the two
uprights and on this that's what gives
you that amazing height and then the
last one I wanted to show you these
pop-up Frankenstein and the paper
engineering and this is by David Hawk
and this is similar to the last one I
showed you but it's even more
extraordinary height that you get
this proverb again it's based on v-folds
default folding forward giving you this
equivalent of a floating playing with
another befall built onto it but it's a
bit more complicated and sophisticated
than that so that's that one this is all
I wanted to show you in books and then
I'll just show you how to make a sort of
simplified version of one of these we
start with a base sheet very thoroughly
creased and then I've got these pre-cut
new folds these are I think it was
tutorial two it's the right angle V fold
so they're just crease down the middle
they're both 90 degrees at the bottom
tabs on the top and bottom we're going
to stick it on here and the whole thing
is going to fold forward and there's
going to be another one in front of it
so the whole thing can fall forwards and
hold a floating plane on top of it and
you can get the maximum movement is the
closer you go to 90 degrees to the spine
the more movement you'll get and the
flash little going but if you go at 90
degrees to the spine the whole thing
just falls flat so you can't go at 90
degrees you have to go up something like
85 something like that with all these
you start by sticking down one side so
I'm going as close to 90 degrees as I
can 90 degrees to the spine stick it
down fold it shut fold the base shut and
find its natural sticking position so
that's the first V Bolt and we want the
next one it needs to be stuck down
parallel to it and so I'll just use this
little piece of card to give me a
guaranteed parallel line to stick it to
there's the line we just stick down one
side I'll keep that for future reference
so we stick that to the spline again to
the line with the central crease
with the spine fold it closed we have to
be quite careful here because we've got
the other one already in place so
there's two identical V folds and now we
can put a floating plane in above those
so just take one of these pieces it
should be about right you can always
trim these down after you stuck them on
so you just have to place about the
right size with a crease down the middle
crease it really well make sure that
it's going to fit onto all those four
tabs and you can put glue on the ball at
the same time so put this into place
fold it shout to make sure that it's all
working nicely there we go so that's the
first plating plane as it closes you see
that it goes down and it's given us
between that crease and the outer edge
we've got that much space to play with
so now we can build another layer onto
that one
so this time we'll make the V file space
the opposite way so they're going to be
facing this way these previous tabs
I've had them facing back towards so
that means the best way to be looking at
this structure is from that so this time
I'm going to make the tabs again
although the V is pointing this way I'm
going to make the tabs point towards me
as well so that you get a better visual
when you look at it so I'll stick this
one on stick down one slide close it
that's the beginning of the second layer
this one needs to be again stuck down
parallel to that so I'll use this
template again mark the lines on the
floating plane again only need to do one
side because the other side is going to
find its natural position that's it and
close it down carefully it's more or
less right so we just keep going stick
another layer on top of that let's see
if that one's going to fit a think so so
put a crease in that so put glue on all
these slap in the back on that corner
put it into that close it down
there we are we've gone to layers up and
so he's still got between that gully and
the outer rate so there should be room
for yet a third lesson let's just try it
this card is a little bit light ideally
it would be would be a bit heavier and a
bit more solid but we'll put another one
in this one again it faces points that
way yep still working it's still staying
within the outer page so we'll just get
the next layer parallel with that as
well
still working more or less bit rickety
we'll put one more layer on top of that
blue on all these four tabs and just fit
this in there close it down that is
going up three levels it's getting
rickety rickety or as we go but you get
the idea anyway it's still quite a lot
bigger than the actual size of the page
that it's rising from and you've still
got clearance between here and the outer
page so you can still put a new folder
some sort on top of it let's just try
one like this so I'll make this into an
acute threefold this time the angle in
the middle is less than 90 make a couple
of tabs there just a little one two to
finish it all off and make the most of
the height we've managed to generate so
this again will be pointing be pointing
back towards me this is going like this
maybe I'll put a counter fold in it just
for a bit of extra pizzazz just fold it
like that so here it is you've got a
four level pop-up structure you can see
the idea of what we're aiming at more
rigid card would have helped more
precise measuring with it help but
overall you get the idea of what we're
trying to do and we kind of structure
much bigger than the original pages
built into at the moment I am working on
a book on a highly complex pop-up design
and that's due to be published sometime
in 2018
you