[Music]
this is about how to make a lion card
which is very good for birthdays so this
is a birthday lion card it's based on
curved shapes which is tutorial 13 I've
got some pre-cut pieces here with all
the dimensions on them to make one
exactly like this you can actually do it
by eye in which case you might get
slightly different shapes you might want
to play around with it but if you want
one just like this this is the top jaw
and this is the bottom jaw and so the
dimensions are the length along here
along here this is eight so this is
eight centimeters this length here eight
centimeters and then you come up here
this is six centimeters and then this is
another six centimeters you need three
tabs two one goes here and one goes here
which will stick it to the page and then
this one is the one that pulls the whole
thing into shape to make it into a card
shape the angles the angles here between
the page and this central crease that is
65 degrees the angle here where you go
around the curve the fold goes around
the curve of the nose that's a hundred
and thirty degrees so well way of making
it is you just fold it in half like this
and then you can measure this 130 and
then you've just cut out one side and
leave a tab on the other side it's all
explained in tutorials thirteen curved
shapes this is the bottom jaw so this
will actually stick on like this and in
this case the length along the bottom
jaw here where it sticks
Paige that's 9 centimeters and this bit
where it comes up here that's 6
centimeters
this is actually an acute angle v-fold
that's tutorial 2 here's the base so
coming down from the top where you're
going to stick the top jaw that's 5
centimeters here coming up from the
bottom where you're going to stick this
one down that's one and a half
centimeters and then all the angles
where you stick it down and the central
spine they're all 35 degrees so I've
just stick this onto here so you can
just see how it's going to look because
I measured it you can actually stick all
the tabs at the same time I'll stick and
Dan sticking out normally we stick down
one sides fold it closed put glue on the
other side and fold the whole base
closed so they find their natural place
but in this case because it's all
measured we can stick both sides down at
the same time
that's the first one and just to make
sure it sounds we will close it down in
case my measurings been a bit dodgy yeah
so that's the bottom jaw the top jaw
glue it closed first so you get the
rounded shape so we just put glue on
that tap smear the glue right up to the
crease that's the important thing
fold it shut when it's glued this piece
should just be able to be completely
flat so then again we can stick that to
these lines we can put glue on both tabs
at the same time I'll just turn it round
so I can actually see the lines from the
inside so put glue on these two again
right up to the crease that's the
important thing so stuck that down to
the lines I'll just close it down just
to make sure it all goes flat so this is
your basic head shape using the curved
shapes I've left the measurements on the
outside in this case but normally do it
in pencil and then rub it out or stick
them down on the inside and then how you
decorate it is up to you so if you look
at this the lion's mane these are all
just flat pieces that have been cut out
to stick around it but you might choose
to actually tab ears here or some sort
of rough or some sort of fancy collar or
something like that
the eyes are just pieces that have been
stuck on the teeth these are just pieces
stuck on underneath the edges and the
tongue and the nose they're all just
other pieces stuck on the ear these
little ear pieces again they're just
just pieces stuck on straightforward
there's nothing to explain it's just
your design up to you to adapt this in
the way that you want it to the two jaws
because they're v-folds pointing in the
opposite direction
v-folds closed down in the direction
they're pointing so here we've got one
pointing up the page and one pointing
down the page so as it closes they move
in opposite directions which means as it
opens the jaws chomp and so here we can
look at the lion you can see the top and
bottom jaw of the lion chomping as you
open and close it so this is the lion
birthday card that can be adapted into
all sorts of other creatures
you
[Music]