[Music]
one of the more intriguing and
delightful mechanisms that Louisa wrote
came up with in the thirties was this
one that appeared in The Daily Express
children's annual number five this was
from the early 30s and it's this one
it's called a doggy greeting and as you
open it the dog nods his tail goes up
and his head goes down it's based on the
box that body of the dog is the box
which is in tutorial 14 but then the
folds around the neck and the rump are
what give the movement and they are
really cunning so in this tutorial
that's what I'm going to explain he
obviously liked this mechanism because
it appeared a couple more times in a
couple of other of his books so in this
one this is Baccano stories number three
and in this one I have to be careful
openness when I break the mechanism
he is the same mechanism to give
movement to this dances arms so as you
open and close the spread the dancer
moves his arms it's the same mechanism
also built on a box so if you look at it
sideways on then you see this is also a
box the body of the dancer is a box it's
got a parallel fold on the top that it
is his head but the action on the arms
is the same complex arrangement of folds
that gives the whole bigger movement as
you open and close the spread I'll
explain all that in a minute but there's
one more rather nice example if I just
put something to hold that open this is
bokar no stories number 5
again it's from the 1930s when we open
it it's got this rather magnificent
conductor and the bodies a bit clunky
but the movement of the arms is really
great you look at it from the side again
it's a box and the action is generated
by these folds the way the arms are
joined onto the top of the box
first of all let me explain the box this
is from tutorial 14 this is the box it
gives you these two planes that are
parallel with the base it always has to
have this pillar coming up the middle
which pushes up the center of the lid
that gives you a solid base normally the
box will also need an end on it that is
what locks the two sides into a solid
rigid shape and you can see that in
something like the conductor model there
are ends on the box that are making it
into a solid shape in something like the
doggy model it's actually the dog's head
itself that ties the two sides together
and makes it rigid there is no end on
this box but it's still a box shape with
a central pillar pushing up the lids
pushing out the sides giving you a
stable solid life to build these moving
parts onto so probably the most simple
to explain is the minuet that's this one
the net the plan for making this this is
how the piece looks so this short piece
this is the top of the box as it opens
the arm moves down the end is stuck
together so this is the top of the box
this is a valley fold this is a mountain
fold the creases are both at 45 degrees
and then this where I've scribbled on it
that's where it glues so that you can
see this is glued together
as the Box opens and closes the arm
moves up and down this is probably the
most simple of these three examples I'm
showing you so that's the minuet the
next most simple is the conductor so
here's the conductor this is the piece
that would be his arm so this is a
Valley fold this is a mountain fold this
is also a mountain fold this here is a
is a valley fold when it's all put
together this is
it looks like this is the top of the box
this is his arm that's going to swing
around so when the whole spread is
closed it's right back like that and
then as the spread opens the top of the
box opens and his arm moves right round
and again up maybe I didn't say this
where I've scribbled that's where it's
glued together see look at this you can
see that's where it's glued together so
you just have another look at this you
can see maybe if I hold it round this
way you can see the top of the box is a
valley then there's a mountain the top
of this is a mountain but you've got
this mountain valley in between and that
gives you that magnificent movement
so if I just explain with that using the
box mechanism so you get an idea I'll
swivel it round so you can see how it is
from the side as it closes the top of
the box closes and the arm goes back as
the page opens the top of the box opens
the top of this mechanism opens and the
arm comes down so that's the conductor
and then the last one I want to show you
is the it's actually the earliest one
from The Daily Express children's
annuals this is the dog dog has two
mechanism says the tail and the head and
they both move as the spread opens you
see the dog's head starts off up and as
the spread opens the dog's head drops
all the way down the tail does the
opposite when the spread is closed the
tail is down and as the spread opens the
tail comes up so now I'll explain that
one I've got two examples here this is
the tail section this is the back this
is the tail when it's closed it's down
as the spread opens the tail comes up I
can show it to you on here this is it
this is the box this is the tail when
the spread is closed the tail is down as
it spread opens the tail comes up
and the way the tail is made this is a
valley fold and then this is a this is a
valley fold this is a mountain fold and
then this is a valley fold so these two
pieces will come together and be glued
so here it is you can see it's a valley
fold two Valley folds two mountain folds
and then the bottom of this is a valley
fold with the two pieces stuck together
so that's the tail of the dog and then
this is the head of the dog the head of
the dog is bit more complicated as you
open and close it it starts up and as
you open it the head comes down I can
put it on here as the base is closed the
top of the box is closed as the base
opens the top of the box opens and the
dog's head drops down I did make one
here so here it is I messed up the tail
so I cut that off but you can see this
is the box you can see there's a central
pillar that pushes up their needs when
it's closed the dog's head is up as it
opens the dog's head drops all the way
down and in fact to get this shape this
is just a straight strip of card this is
the straight strip of card but to get
this particular shape it's made with the
two sides both Bend in different ways so
when you look at the actual model
there's a hole in the top the way the
dog's head is shaped the two sides
aren't made from one strip or they are
but the two sides diverge so they had to
be cut in a different shape to give you
that exact shape so that is what I did
here to give you even more and so if I
just explained that one it's quite
complex this is the back of the dog this
short bit then you can see there's
there's two there's two valley folds
and then this short piece is a mountain
fold and then this long bit that's the
dog's head that is a valley fold and
then you've got actually two mountain
folds so you go valley mountain mountain
all the angles are marked so the 105
degrees that's what this big angle here
the 80 degrees is this little one in
there the 65 degrees is this one in
there and then when you look at this you
can see here it starts with the valley
fold so this first one is a valley fold
then there's actually two mountain folds
this one and this one are two mountain
folds and then you've got the dog's head
and this piece here will it be another
Valley fold and that will glue together
like this is glued together so this one
of the earliest pop-up mechanisms from
the very early thirties and I think it's
really one of the one of the most fun
and the the one other thing I'd like to
add actually is when you look at this
you see these big ears
well the ears are coming off these
little triangles on the yellow strip
these this is where the ears are coming
off here and here what we've just seen
has three different examples of a very
early mechanism from the 1930s I don't
think you see it in any books these days
but it is really good fun and so
although if he's dog head and dog tail
moving the other two are armed so I've
called this tutorial moving arms part
three
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]