[Music]
I'm going to show you how to make an
opening flower mechanism that is based
on a design from the 1930s they first
appeared in the Daily Express children's
annual number three here it is it's
called the flower fairy he's got some
quite complicated folding underneath
that raises the flower up off the page
and I can't quite work out why he did
that I think it might be because the
card is used is very thin and flimsy and
bendy and so he wanted some of it double
to give it the strength to lift the
flower up and the version I'm going to
show you is a little more simple so this
is they'll express children's annual
number three and then the same design
more or less was repeated later in the
30s I believe in this book are no
stories number ten and here's the design
that time and you can see the flower is
smaller it's lower on the page it's the
same basic mechanism the different
artwork but the same basic mechanism so
now I'll show you how to make that I'll
start with a flower and just cut a rough
square so I'll just just cut the corners
off and show you how to make the flower
then I'll show you the mechanism that
that raises it up so this is what we
will be aiming for this is the flower
raised up on a very basic v-fold this is
a right-angle v-fold without increases
on the top that creates a gully that you
stick the flour into you I tried
following the earlier design which has
these holes cut in it that give it more
delicacy but with the design that I've
made it doesn't look quite right so I
might do it slightly differently this
time but let's just scope for you to
play with it and work out you know what
you'd like to make really so this is the
basic flour fold it in half and then we
need these two diagonals so I'll just
use the set square to measure those that
would line up the central crease on the
projector with the central crease on
that and that pop-up now I'm going to
score these they're both at 45 degrees
and on this side as well and I'm going
to extend them right across the flower
and this one so this will give us the
basic flower shape these two bits will
come forward and these two bits go back
there we are and then I'll just press it
down just to make sure it's working and
then that's the basic flower
so I've got a base sheet and then I'm
going to want some green to make the the
stand for the flowers so did have some
green here I'll make the base there's
the base now we need one of these
species because he's going to stick on
like this it'll fold forward and the
flowers stick on the top so we'll just
take a small piece of card like this
fold it in half crease it really well
this is a right angle V fold so we're
going to make a crease along the bottom
one centimeter up all at right angles
again crease it really well cut out that
corner cut that off as well fold the
pieces separately so I can really
reinforce those
so these are going to stick on the page
like this and now we want the extra
creases that add to the gully so I'll do
it up something like that and bold that
well and this is a this is a counter
fold so we push that through and now
when this is stuck down this is going to
be like that
the other path of this mechanism rather
the design rather than the mechanism is
this bit at the back this is giving you
the extra leaves that stick up above the
flower this is an obtuse angle v-fold so
as it folds down this this folds down
that way so when we come to sticking
this on to the page this is going to
stick on the page with the flower like
that and this is going to fold that way
but at the same time we're going to have
these two leaves behind it they're going
to fold down the other way so we need to
position this maybe around the middle
there and now we can put the flower is
going to stick into that gully
so when I test this and try putting the
flower into that you can see it's going
to be too big for the base so I'm going
to pull this off because it hasn't stuck
really firmly yet and I'm going to make
it shorter so I cut a piece off there
and add creases and cut that corner out
and fold those back on themselves so
this is going to go in like that and
it's still not not working I'll have to
make the flower smaller now we stick the
flower into that but before we stick it
into that gully let's just check how
it's gonna sit on the page not too bad I
might just cut a little bit more off it
so I'll make the flower a little bit
smaller I can also make it a little bit
more delicate cutting pieces out of
these corners just to give it slightly
more petal defect so now I'll stick this
into that gully that I've created there
quite achieved the the openness that
Jareau got with his flower design a pull
the flower off I'm not happy with these
angles that they're just keeping the
flower more close than I want if you
look at this the flower is much more
open if you look at this the flower is
even more open I'm going to take off
this green piece and I'm going to use
this piece that I was experimenting with
yesterday if you compare the two angles
the angles on the fold on this piece and
much better than the angles on the fold
on this piece I think maybe this piece
is still a little bit high considering
you're gonna have to have an obtuse
angle V fall behind it so I'm going to
make this piece slightly smaller I'm
going to take off a piece there and
refold those this is going to be like
that
and take out that corner
now try again like that I think with any
luck it'll be a much better flower I
want it like that I'm sticking one side
down closing it closing it again that
looks like a much better angle in the
middle for sticking the flower on to
just let that glue go off of slightly
overdone it stick the flower on there
right let's try this and shut it to make
sure it's all working seems to be it's
like a better flower this time and you
think I'm an expert right now I put the
leaves behind it that is slightly
heavier green I'm not quite happy with
it this is it so I'll just take about a
third of a sheet fold it in half now
mostly falls the acutely folds that the
ones we mostly use when you fold the
creases on the bottom to make the tabs
you make the creases form a downward
pointing arrow in this case we want it
to be an obtuse angle v-fold so we're
going to make the creases come up
towards the spine like this when you
open this up you can see the creases
make an upward pointing arrow and
they'll cut that to make
I want it smaller than that but maybe a
bit more leaf-shaped so this should be
able to go behind the flower standing up
something like that
I'll stick one side and then the other
but normally because of their flower
it's all a bit complicated so I'll just
try and do this by eye shut it quickly
so if the pieces need to move they can
move while the glue is still soft
no well it's still soft I'll shut it
down the way this is stuck on the angles
I've got here on this obtuse angle
v-fold they're obviously something wrong
so I'm going to pull the whole thing off
while the glue still sticky I'm going to
change the angles and stick it on with a
tighter angle on the base so you can
bring the leaves in much closer to the
flower and now put the glue on those and
glue it into place I'll do them both at
the same time and then we will shut it
while the glue soft so if they need to
shift around at all they can still move
so it's more like this so it's like that
I'll just shut it make sure it works
yeah that's fine so there it is if I
turn it around in fact you can see a bit
of yellow where I've pulled it off the
page but that's the angle that the whole
thing is stuck down at yeah I'm happy
with that
you know it's slightly different from
hero's version but quite a nice opening
flower
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]