this tutorial is about moving arms which
is a very subtle mechanism which has
numerous variations and uses the most
basic is based on the parallelogram
which we cover in tutorial 5 here it is
the green bit is the parallelogram the
yellow bit is a basic moving arm the
pink bit is adding an elbow to the arm
which makes appear to move even more so
this is the basic variation here's an
example this is the basic parallelogram
you can see that with four moving arms
on it four limbs or moving in slightly
different directions if we look at the
the haunted house by Lampe and Kowski
this has got a really good example so
here's the parallelogram here are two
moving arms so one of them moves rotates
against the page and you see the same
side of the piece of card all the way
through the other piece flips over on
the parallelogram there are two small
triangles and it depends which triangle
you stick it to if you stick it to this
one which is on the small side of the
parallelogram that is the one that
rotates against the page so that's
really the most useful the other small
triangle that's the one that will make
the the piece of car flip over the
parallelogram also creates a gully here
where it joins the page so you can stick
moving arms in for that
here's an example here's the basic
parallelogram this is the moving arm
we've already looked at here's two more
small triangles stuck into this gully
created by the parallelogram joining the
page and so these two have two moving
arms stuck on and so as you see as you
open and close it they have a different
action and here's another example this
is this is using that type of mechanism
so is the parallel fold through to the
page and we've got small triangles stuck
in and so those are giving us moving
arms are moving in different directions
there are numerous ways that this can be
used so here's a really complicated one
so this is this is the basic jumping
figure that I just showed you got those
two of them there's two parallelograms
built onto each other with these jumping
figures other variations there's this
type so this is actually the the moving
arm appears from behind a mask so the
green bit is a big parallelogram and the
arm is actually stuck to the page at an
angle that's what gives it the movement
as it opens and closes and here's
another variation of it if you look at
it this way around you'll see those
there's a parallelogram inside the green
one is just a mask and then there's a
parallelogram inside with the moving
arms stuck to it rather than seeing the
whole mechanism and how it works you
just see the image appearing from behind
behind the green mask
so I'll just make one of those just so
you can see how to make it you'll need a
base sheet sheet of card fold it in half
crease thoroughly you need a piece to
make the parallelogram with so just a
piece of card something like this fold
the tab onto each end of it crease them
well we're making a parallelogram here
as explained in tutorial 5 so you just
fold an extra parallel crease into it so
now what you've ended up with you've got
three parallel creases you've got a long
side and the short side so to find out
where you stick this put the piece on
the page you just need to mark where one
of the creases lies so I'll just mark
the the short side bilities and then
you're going to flip this over flip it
over and stick the long side to the mark
this will be giving you your basic
parallelogram but before we do that
you've got one more set of creases to
make the two small triangles so here's
your card here's your crease just fold
the top edge down so it's it's flush
with that with that crease so it's flush
with that crease there and fold it back
on itself and yeah just push it in just
to make sure it's all working well so
fold it back again so there is so now
making sure that the two little
triangles are on the top this is stuck
near the bottom of your page glue the
long side to the mark you made for the
shorter side so when the page is flat
the parallelogram lies flat so you can
glue both tabs at the same time so
there's the glue
right so stick that down with the crease
to the mark do this one down so that the
whole thing is flat all the creases
should be parallel with the spine fold
it shut make sure that comes forward
make sure it's all working nicely now
you can pop these back in so that's the
basic underlying mechanism the
parallelogram with two small small
triangles added and then you make the
moving arms so this is going to fit on
to the short side so it's going to fit
on to that triangle you can just trim
that off there put a bit of glue on it
right that glues in there probably the
piece I've got here is too long as it
closes is going to crunch against the
spine so I'll just trim a piece off so
if that fits okay but that's now fitting
nicely within the parameters if you want
to make it give it that extra elbow you
can just cut an extra piece off of car
glue that on
so there we have it the basic moving arm
and that's how it works
so now I'll just show you a whole series
of other other examples in books just
all the variations it's a really useful
mechanism so first we've got this is
help the animals of Africa by Roberts
óbuda and so here we are we've got a
moving arm here this is a small V fold
with the tail stock on it that moves
that way and then the body is part of a
parallelogram the moving arm is
underneath the mask the head is on the
moving arm so as it opens and closes the
head moves is the next one this is the
parallelogram is holding up the whole
head of the zebra we've got two little
triangles here and another one under the
mask
so as you open and close it the legs are
moves they're the moving arm the third
one this is the parallelogram I can show
you this way round so you can see really
clearly there's the parallelogram
there's the parallelogram and the image
is stuck to the moving arm and it swings
around as the page opens here's another
one this is the body of the bird is the
parallelogram and you've got the two
moving arms giving you movement in that
direction and the last one here got the
elephant head looking at it this way you
can see really clearly it's a
parallelogram with the small triangles
giving you the actions as the page opens
and closes next one is the Museum of
unnatural history by Keith Moore be
there is is the parallelogram there's
actually two parallelograms here there's
a small one here and then there's a
another one here so one is giving you
this this moving arm and that's giving
you that one so as it closes the two are
coming together
here we have my jungle pop-up book the
turtle is the the parallelogram and
you've got two moving arms coming from
behind the mask and then you've got
these two tail fins so as you see this
it's a subtle mechanism which can give
you movement in all sorts of directions
and this one here we've got the gorilla
in effect this is a floating playing
this is what we covered in tutorial 12
they act as a mask with the the arms of
the gorilla moving and then you have
another one the crocodile head the panda
head all of these are moved by the
moving arms this is so this is Robert's
óbuda of the night before Christmas in
this one he's using moving arms to
actually make wheels turns so in this
example here you can see the wheels are
all moving in different directions and
so this is another really subtle use of
the moving arm to give you give you
turning wheels okay so this is a Little
Red Riding Hood paper engineering by
Bruce Foster so here's the wolf it's got
the main body of the wolf is a pair of
parallelograms and then the tail and
back legs are one moving our mechanism
and the head and front feet are another
one's as open and closes you get really
lovely founding mechanism and then
lastly I've got from mummy by uh Matthew
Reinhart this is a masterpiece it's a
really fantastic book so in this spread
you've got numerous moving arms moving
around but the bit I really like here is
this last bigger you've got the head the
arms the feet that they're all moving in
different ways this is a really cleverly
constructed combination of moving arms
so yeah absolute masterpiece this one
you've got the baby's arm
waving names in so moving arms are all
explained in detail in this my book
pop-up design and paper mechanics
you