I've looked at what's being most popular
in the tutorials we've done so far at
number seven adding extra creases to pop
up shapes is by far the most popular so
this is a sequel to that it's adding
creases part two this is using counter
folds
counter folds were covered in the
introduction but just very briefly and
so I'll just recap some of that and then
show you how you can use those to
enhance your pop-up spreads there are
three basic types take the piece of card
fold it in half and then make a single
cut so with one cut and one crease fold
it like this fold it back on itself open
it up and push it forward so this is the
most simple basic pop-up the most simple
counter fold so there's one you can do
the same below the cut if you want you
could change the angle that you're
coming in at and so then you get a
different shaped 3d piece so open that
up so you can see by changing the angle
that you've creased it out you can get
get two different shapes you can also
just add it to the tip you don't
necessarily need the cut you can work
from the edge so say at the top here
fold it in half add in another fold so
it's like this fold it back on itself
open it up and pop that forward so
they've got the different options this
is all based on befalls the second kind
uses two cuts and one crease so we'll
make two cuts about the same length you
don't even need to cut them they can be
torn they don't even need to be parallel
they can be at any angle it'll still
work in this case you fold it like this
fold it back on itself and when you pop
that one forward you you've got a type
of step so that's the second time this
is about parallel creases the third kind
is one short cut and one long one so
this is actually the it's the converging
crease mechanism but it's a variation so
again you fold it from the ends of the
cuts the fold goes from end of cut to
end of cut fold it back on itself open
it up pop it forward so this is giving
you an angled to more angled planes to
build with these shapes they create
creases Valley folds and they create
mountain folds and any of those can be
worked on so if you take this one you
can actually make an extra cut into it
and you can fold that and then as you
open that up you find you've got the
main counter fold and then you've got
another small one added to it you can do
this with any of them so say we take
this this step one here you can add a
cut to the main step give it a couple of
creases so you've got a small extra step
added in there like that you can also
work into one of these edges we could
try that with a short short cut and a
longer one so when you bend that
you see how you can play with it these
are just examples where any of these
techniques can be applied to other pop
up shapes other mechanisms any mountain
fold or Valley fold you can cut these
into them and then these any of these
planes they can be used you can stick
pieces onto them to make pieces stand up
stick out do what do what you want so
I've just got a few examples I'll show
you in groups here this is Little Red
Riding Hood with paper engineering by
Bruce Foster and so the examples I've
got a quite small but this is a v-fold
this is the counter fold that's been
built into it here and that counter fold
one of the planes of it is being used to
lift up this extra piece then here as
well it's again it's rather small we've
got a a V fold with a counter fold built
into it and that's been used to lift up
this plane this is cookie count by
Roberts óbuda and in this example here
we've got this is a parallel fold here's
the counter fold built into it here and
then this is sticking out raising an
image so the image is built on to the
main mechanism and the last one I want
to show you is the pop-up Frankenstein
paper engineering by David Walker and on
this one here the tab that is holding
the whole mechanism to the page rather
than going backwards out of sight it's
coming forward and so this is the
counter fold cut into it here raising
this image if you look at it from behind
you can see this is the counter folders
being cut into this there's a cut there
and that piece is being pushed forward
it looks as though there's actually a
second one here so looking at it like
this you can see there's a counter fold
there raising this image there's another
one there raising this image so that's
quite a nicely science done
again on on this line as well so there's
three of those so I'll just show you
quickly how to do it on a on a v-fold so
if we take a base sheet nicely creased I
take a piece of card so this is a basic
B fold and a cute angle view fold I'm
making
I'll make the tabs quite big so we can
make counter folds in those so we create
it up like this
the crucial thing with these v-folds is
that you you cut away up to the point
where all the creases meet so here it is
it's going to stick down I'll just
reinforce these it it's going to stick
on to your page like this but in this
case I'm going to keep the tabs coming
forward so we can build counter folds
into them so the whole piece is going to
stick onto your page like that I've just
reinforce these creases so the whole
thing moves nice and sweetly and then
before you glue it down you need to work
out what what can't afford you want this
into it so let's have a step type here
or an angled step up made the cuts to
different lengths so we're going to have
an angled step on that side fold it back
on itself and then on on this side we'll
just have a regular step so we make two
cuts both the same length
so when this is all opened up this is
going to be working like this and we've
also got this mountain fold in the
middle so we make a couple of cuts in
that one one cap will probably be fine
fold it down so little going like that
and let's just add one more on the top
or just an extra little fold in there so
generate a couple more planes that we
can be consuming so here is ready to go
now with all these default mechanisms
you can play around with how how close
to the spine you stick know what sort of
shape you want whether you want it
really tight or whether you want it
further out so it lies down more and
more I'll probably go with sticking it
down at roughly 45 degrees to the spine
put the glue on one side push the glue
right up to the creases it doesn't
really matter about the edges of the
flaps but makes it neater if you do and
then this central crease has to be
aligned with the spine so there is and
then you fold the whole piece shut put
glue on the other tab
close the base so that finds its natural
sticking position place it down well
there's your V folder the whole series
of counterpoint added to it now you can
start building with these you can use
them any way you like really so say this
you can come up or you can come forward
we can or you can do both so just make
one of these going this way and one of
them standing up every time you add a
piece to a construction always close it
down and make sure that it's going to
work but it's going to fit in that
pieces aren't jamming together or
snagging with the spine these angled
ones here we could take a piece like
this fold it could fold it in the middle
or could fold it at one end to make it
all a bit more asymmetric you can stick
a piece on onto there like that there we
go
and this one I'll cut it's a bit more of
a pointy angle so it'll fit in a bit
better into the shape we've got that
should be good
there we go fold it down so hopefully
that shows you how you can use counter
folds with your other pop-up shapes and
use them to add extra planes which you
can then build on to make more exciting
pop-ups there's one other kind I'd like
to show you which is actually a more of
a asymmetric all these ones that we
looked at before was symmetric and
asymmetric type you can't crease the
piece you're building beforehand you
have to think a bit ahead so if we take
a piece like this you need to draw a
guideline where your spine fold is going
to be so let's just say this is where
the spine fold is going to be and then
say this is where the bottom of your
pop-up is going to be so this is going
to be a crease and this is going to be a
crease and then we can come up as high
as we like and we'll put another crease
just here so it's going to be a crease
there now this is the main spine fold
and the distance we've come down from it
is the width of a ruler so I'm going to
use the same thing here this is the
important thing that the this distance
we call it a is the same as this
distance we'll call that a so these two
are the cut lines it up here and up here
and the the scored lines must never
cross cut lines and the cut lines must
never cross scored lines so this is the
spine fold so the score goes from that
cut line to the edge and this is the
bottom of the whole construction so
again it goes from cut line to cut line
this is going to be the leading edge
jutting out so again you go from cut
line to cut line
and the top one so now this is going to
fold there this whole thing is going to
come forward this is going to be a
mountain fold a valley fold and the
bottom is a valley fold so this is your
your parallelogram if you want to see it
more cleanly we can actually push it
through to come out the other side so
then you can use it that way around you
can use it that way around and again you
can add more counter Falls to these if
we make a little cat in that fold it
down so there's the parallelogram and
there's the birds the added step to find
out more about these you can look at my
book pop-up design and paper mechanics
and this goes into counter falls in much
more depth
you