[Music]
this card is a pop-up house that can be
used either as a birthday card or a
moving house cards or anything else you
might think of it's based on the right
angle v-fold and the parallelogram so if
we look at this this is the underlying
structure you'll see as it opens and
closes this is the right angle v-fold
and this is the parallelogram as you
open and close it the parallelogram
lifts up all the walls twists around so
fixing a roof onto it the roof can't be
fixed to this two side walls as they
twist in relation to each other as it
closes the only points that stay the
same in relation to each other are the
two gable ends so to add the roof you
have to build a roof beam into it so if
I just lift this up you can see there's
a roof beam that joins the two gable
ends and the roof sticks onto those
nears the tabs holding the roof on for
this you will need to measure so the
tools you'll need you'll need glue
you'll need a ruler you'll need scissors
and set square alternatively you can
actually use a piece of card as a set
square and I'll explain that in a minute
here's the template the measurements are
I've drawn it up again here I'm going to
cut this one out in a minute so you can
see here the these lengths the short
walls they're four and a half
centimeters
the long walls are 7 centimeters
you've got a 1 centimetre tab and
another one on the end here that pulls
it round and turns it into a rectangle
I've drawn it up here this is the bottom
line you will need to score so I suppose
that's another tool you'll need is a
ballpoint pen or something similar and
so you'll need to score along here where
the two tabs go
you'll also need to score up here where
the tab pulling the whole thing into a
rectangle goes
you'll also need a roof beam so this
roof beam I've actually made it three
centimetres high but it doesn't really
matter and again you'll need to score
here because this is a tab and here this
is a tab these are going to stick onto
the gable ends and then along the top
here yeah you're going to have two tabs
here and so you'll need to score this
line so that those fold down nicely so
if you haven't got a set square you can
use a corner of a sheet of card this is
a 90 degree angle and so when you come
to measuring up you will need the ruler
to measure these distances here but you
can then use a the corner of a piece of
cards just to give you these right
angles where the uprights come and here
as well so I'll just cut this out really
quickly you can either use a pair of
scissors or you can use a craft life
like this so I find craft knives are the
the quickest way to go I'll just cut it
out really fast
so here's the basic piece for the house
make sure all these corners are really
well
creased as always just fold them
backwards and forwards fold them on
themselves crease them again and again
so that they all move really comfortably
when the pop-up is opening and closing
and also crease the tabs really
thoroughly and then I've scored it all
with a barrow with ink in it ideally
you'd use a ballpoint pen with knowing
but as it has got ink in it you've got
these lines so when you fold it into the
half shape make sure those folded lines
are inside and also this tab that's
holding it all together you put that on
the inside just put some glue on that
once you've glued it make sure that the
whole thing will actually lie flat so
you can try it both ways and then you'll
need a base sheet so fold it in half
crease it really thoroughly again and on
this you need to be sure that the tabs
both up 45 degrees to the spine you
don't stick it on corner to corner
you have to have it 45 degrees to the
spine so again you can either use a set
square to give you the the guide lines
like this just draw them on so you know
where you're going to be sticking it
down or again you can use a corner like
this from a piece of card so that you
know this is a 90 degree fold so fold
that in half so the edges are next to
each other that will give you two
45-degree poles so then you can put that
in line up the fold with the central
crease and you can use that to mark
where you're going
since it's all measured up you can
actually stick both sides down at the
same time make sure that the tabs
holding it down that when it's in
position they don't overlap so on this
you can see they're slightly big so I'm
just going to snip an extra piece off
those so they don't overlap on the spine
now we can stick them both down at the
same time as always with glue the
creases are the important thing so you
make sure that the glue goes right up to
the creases and then you can position it
so both those creases are on those
guidelines and then as with all pop ups
fold it shut
press it down firmly just to make sure
that it's stuck down soundly so there's
the beginning of the house now you've
got the roof beam make sure all the
creases are really well reinforced
folding backwards and forwards and then
the important thing with this when you
stick it in it's going to stick into the
gable ends these creases they have to be
vertical so you can stick them both at
the same time and just make sure the
creases are coming up vertically up to
the very tips of the gable ends and
again we can put glue on both of those
at the same time I don't think it
actually makes any difference but I'm
going to have one pointing one way and
one pointing the other way just to give
it some symmetry and again make sure
that the glue goes right up to the
crease and then you you can just put
that in place like that and like this
make sure the the crease for these two
top ones is up against the top and again
we'll just shut it to make sure
everything's in place and that the whole
thing is found
there it is and then when we put the
roof on this is going to go down each of
these when it's going to go one weight
and one is going to go the other way so
this is the roof piece it's got a crease
down the middle make sure that's really
well folded well enforced the dimensions
the length of the roof this will be
going along here this is 8,5 centimeters
and the width of the roof it's 5,5 and
5,5 so this is going down the slope of
the roof so we'll just fold that in half
the other point with these is as the
base closes the corners of the roof have
a tendency to dag into the page so I
just ran them off so you can do that
with it fold it in half just round them
off so that it can move more easily and
then put the glue on your two roof beam
tabs even here and then you have to just
position the roof by eye I'll just smear
the glue keep the dimensions or any
drawing or measuring underneath line it
up so it's equidistant at each end
beyond the gable make sure the crease on
the top is right flush with it that
looks about right to me and then close
the whole base wash it well and there
you have it there's your house the other
dimension I didn't mention is this one
between the corner of the house and the
base here that needs to be 6 centimeters
just in
that's a six so the house basically it's
a parallelogram and in this case it's a
parallelogram built onto a v-fold but
there's other ways you can play with it
so in this example rather than building
it onto a right angle v-fold
you can build it onto a zigzag fold like
this zigzag fold is tutorial 20 and
again the houses are the same they've
got the roof beams underneath I'll just
show you a zigzag fold this is a zigzag
fold which is an uneven one based on a
parallelogram this is the regular zigzag
fold so here it is it gives you three
gullies that you can build into you can
build in here here and here so in this
case the house doesn't stick down to the
base the house sticks into the exact
order houses I'll just explain this one
in this case the dimensions are
different it is based on a parallelogram
in this case the places it sticks down
they both point at the same point on the
spine and then this distance from this
corner to the spine is the same as this
short side here and this long distance
between the corner and the spine is the
same as the long one here now having
built the house you can actually build
onto it so if we just look at this
Roberts a Buddha The Wonderful Wizard of
Oz that's got a really really great
house in it it's a slightly different
style of house here it is you can see
the way he's working is he stuck the
edges of the roof were actually stuck to
the walls of the house and so that means
because everything rotates as you close
it it can't have a proper roof ridge so
you'll see as the house opens and closes
the roof moves so this this is a split I
find that less satisfactory which is why
I prefer this other way of doing but the
really good thing about what Cebu has
done here are these trees that are built
onto the house as the house closes
there are two gullies forum won't gully
is here on this long edge and the other
gully is here
so you can build into those gullies and
in this case this is a parallelogram and
then this tree is made with two
parallelograms and slots that's rising
up holding these layers in it's really
clever here's the gully on a lonely
short edge of the house
he's built a parallelogram into that
gully and then that parallelogram one
side it extends along here and so you've
got this tree these are parallelograms
in effect working off the gully created
by this other side so that's it for how
to make the house card
[Music]
[Applause]