[Music]
this card is a birthday card containing
a boat and in this case I've done the
Owl and the Pussycat it's quite a simple
mechanism it's based on tutorial 14
which is the box is an example of the
box as you can see it's two
parallelograms back-to-back and it's the
piece on the end that makes it into a
rigid shape and in this case rather than
it being just a flat piece that goes
across the end of the box we've got the
boat shape this goes across the end of
the box and holds the whole thing rigid
the parts you need to make this these
are the parts I've already cut them out
and measured them these are the two bits
which will turn into the parallelograms
it's three sections 2,5 centimeters 2,5
2,5 with a tab at each end and both of
them they're just 5 centimetres wide and
then these are the sides of the boat
from crease to crease it's 16
centimetres you've got two tabs on the
end of one of the pieces and the other
piece doesn't need tabs so from the
cottage to the cottage that 16
centimetres and the final piece this is
the mast so now I'll just show you how
to stick them all together first of all
make sure all the creases are really
well enforced so I'll just crease all
those
when you're making these you don't need
to measure where the pieces go on the
base so I'll just start with one you
glue one of the tabs flush with the
spine make sure the glue goes right up
to the crease and you stick that in the
middle flush with the spine and then to
find its natural sticking place you fold
the whole thing into its what's going to
be its closed position
put glue on that other tab and then fold
the base closed so that gives you your
first parallelogram the next one again
you stick it one side flush with the
spine
fold it into its closed position and put
glue on the other tab and then you fold
the base closed so these are your two
parallelograms now is your chance to
stick in the mast in a minute we're
going to stick them back to back to make
the solid shape but before you do that
you can put in the mast or sail or
anything else so you just put a bit of
glue on that stick that in place and now
you put glue all over one of these
surfaces close it so there it is it's
the two parallelograms it's still not a
stable shape because there's nothing
joining these two outer sides so I'll
just glue the two boat pieces together
so these can be glued both at the same
time
so you keep any measuring marks on the
inside hidden from you now this will
come down over here and stick to those
two sides making the whole thing rigid
so again we just put the glue on these
outer edges drop it into place and you
can just really Center this up by eye it
doesn't really matter whether the box
shape is actually writing or not now we
stuck the outside edges on you can see
as it closes the end of the boat
actually lifts up but so this is a
variation on the box mechanism 14 and at
this point this is where you can start
adding your decorations so in this case
the owl is stuck to the side of the
boats the pussycat is stuck to the mast
you can add a flag if you want you've
also got the gully here you can build
into and another one here you can build
out from tutorial 8 talks about adding
small 3d pieces that you could add into
any of these gullies that close as the
card closes so that's your boat if you
did want to build a deck into it you
would actually have to tailor that to
fit so if I just take this piece of card
here you'd need to have a crease down
the middle
you'd have to have a hole in the middle
which the Masters going to go through
you need it to be the same length as the
whole boat so here's the end it's one
end and the other end so this is going
to fit on it like that that will stick
down onto the top of this box shape but
to actually make it fit
you need to just shape it sort of
tailoring it rigid so I just take this
and looking at roughly the shape I've
got on the boat
this could not fit on there you can see
it's still a little bit big I'm nearly
there I'll take a bit more off here all
right there we go so now that will fit
into the boat I can get it out again put
some glue on the top of the box bits
smear it around make sure that crease is
good so the deck it's gonna stay flat
when there when the boat is open and
just drop it in over the mouth you press
it down onto those it's there so now as
you close it the deck closes along with
the boat so you don't really need a deck
if you look at this one there is no deck
and as a design it does work pretty
satisfactorily so that's it's the boat
birthday cards it's up to you to
decorate it with any other bits and
pieces that you like you might use
photographs of the people concerned or
cut out bits and other postcards or
anything amusing fish mermaids Captain
Pugwash up to you
you
[Music]