[Music]
I'm going to show you how to make this
rather complicated father Christmas card
and when you pull the tab it reveals the
message it does take some measuring it
is quite fiddly but I'll lead you
through step by step so that you can
make your own design the pieces you need
number one is this is the base sheet
this sheet here you look at it on the
other side and you can see when you put
it down here's the slot this is a slot
that I've cut in it there's a slit here
this is the slit here the important
thing with slits is that you cut them
back slightly at the end so a little bit
of card can lift up and allow the strip
to move easily within it if you go to
write the strip and wobble around and
then it can actually Jam so the way I've
done this I put the strip across it and
measured how wide it needed to be and
just went a millimeter or so wider each
side and then and cut it back as with
all these strips they need to be double
thickness and glued so here's the street
I've scored it folded it and now just
glue it closed I've also found with long
strips like this up from gluing them
it's quite good if you smooth them out
flat on the table otherwise they can
tend to sort of back in a bit or develop
some sort of bending and so having
smeared the glue all over the back of it
and then then folded it shut
then yeah put it flat on the table and
really pile it out you've got a really
good flat strip the next crucial piece
is one of these so this is a piece like
this the central bit is just a tad wider
than the strip and then these two other
bits fold in and there's two flaps left
on the top and that goes right at the
top of the strip so you glue the three
central sections once you've glued into
place it's good to just let it really
dry because with these poor stripped
mechanisms the one thing you really
don't want is glue oozing that just gums
it all up and stops it moving nicely
here is these two guys come over you can
see the creases meet at the same point
and then there's these two flaps stand
up
we're just pressed up flat you glue this
piece on to the end then you stick this
end through the slit and then you put
these two pieces up through that slot
flatten them out put glue on them smooth
it around and then this glues up pretty
much flush with the top so this is one
of the variations on the full strip
where you can pull a tab and make a
thing slide down the page this is the
amount of movement you've got at the
moment so that seems to be working
pretty nicely so these are the other
pieces this is this actual lineup piece
this is going to go like this I put two
creases on each side so it can fold
round the back of the card with just a
bit of a beard sticking out below that's
like this this bit of beard here and
I've measured this so it should just fit
on there I think this needs to come down
a bit so it's about like that I've made
this skin color
I've cut
these holes in this piece so that the
eyes will show through there the pink
that will go behind the beard so I'll
just glue that on as well so having
stuck the beard on to the skin this now
goes on there so the beard connects that
with the beard below it and you can see
through the eye holes that I've cut into
the skin tone match up with the eye
holes that are cutting the greenery and
so that can be stuck on there just
before I do it I'm going to stick down
one side of the green put glue all down
one side here and this goes flush with
the top there so that's going on like
that and we're happy with it or we can
stick the other side down as well and
then this bits going to go on like this
line up the beards I might need to just
trim that ever so slightly lining it up
like that
you know just that
glue this piece down so all lines up the
beard the eyes so now when you pull this
you get the extension coming down and
now the reason for leaving this so you
could lift it up is now you mark where
the eyes are actually going to go within
this this is all the way up the eyes
here and then when it comes all the way
down we want the eye to be here on the
other side so now we can open this up
and we join up these two marks so it's
going to be something like you can go a
little bit actually a bit wider this is
the eye and we can just shade that in
and just check that so you close this up
push it up pull it down you can see how
the eyes are moving if you're happy with
that and you've shaded them in enough
then you can stick this other side down
so you put the glue in there there we go
with these when you're sticking the
white bit which has the eyes on it and
which is the beard on underneath all
this the white is going right up to the
top here so we've got to leave enough
space for the eyes as you pull down for
the ice to be accommodated
when this bit comes down you have to
make sure it's not coming down so far as
it actually appears under here when you
pull down the beard so now you've got
this pull strip is much too long so of
course you push it up to it fully pushed
up position and just snip it off as it
happens I've got the snuff about the
right length so the amount it moves is
pretty much exactly right but if you've
made this lot a bit too long so this one
before when you when you pulled it you
actually it went too fast or the eyes
started showing so you can actually
govern that by putting a piece across
like this this piece is stuck across
it's stuck to the strip so as you pull
it down it comes to rest against this
knit so that stops the movement so you
can govern and affect the amount of
movement you're getting by adding things
like this better to have this slot cut
too long and then use one of these to
control the movement then have the whole
thing too short so you can't actually
make it do what you want so now you can
add your message you know you might not
want to say
for Christmas you might want to say
something else that's up to you
that will fits in there then the last
thing to do is just add these bits of
festive Reds so the width of the head
it's about like that and then round it
off of it seems to be okay so I'll stick
that on there I want to draw some
features on it so yeah maybe we'll have
a nose here or something like that maybe
some eyebrows would help maybe you're
actually a bit of a line around the eye
might help a bit this is really up to
you your your individual artistic
nature's and then we'll also put this as
this red piece on the bottom so again
that can come you can just measure it
like that it needs to come up slightly
as the beard slides up and down above it
it never goes above this stage there
just really isn't a problem with that
you might want it to actually go all the
way down to the bottom in which case
yeah cut a slit like that in this one
I've written a written happy Christmas
so in this one it's up to you you can
write whatever you like you might want
to say happy Christmas you might want to
say something else you might want to say
happy birthday I don't know what you
want to say one key I would give you is
take a take a pencil and mark very very
lightly just pull it down a slight
fraction and just mark where the lowest
you can come with the writing so now you
push that back up and that mark has
disappeared when you pull it down and
you write your message or whatever is in
here you don't want the letters to be
coming below that mark so that when this
is fully up there's a hint of it there
you just want it to be clean and clear
to make it easier to grab the tab you
can actually score across it so you can
score just here and ideally you'd have
done that before this is put in place
and you do it on the back so then this
the tab fold so it just makes it easier
to get a hold of it
[Music]