[Music]
I'm going to explain how to make a
Christmas tree Christmas card when we're
going to make is very simple looks like
this but before I explain it I'm just
going to run through some Christmas
trees in books that are quite
complicated and I'll tell you which
tutorials refer to them so if you want
to work out how to do it yourself you
can have a go so I'm gonna start with
Keith's more beak oh no Santa and his
Christmas tree is this one quite a
complicated very pleasing design it's
based on a parallel fold here which is
tutorial six and then there's also a lot
of slots which are tutorial 11 maybe
looking at it end on you can get an idea
of how it actually works this is quite a
complicated design I think it's really
really pleasing possibly the best one
I'll be showing him the whole tutorial
anyway that's key small beak oh no Santa
second one I want to show you is the 12
days of Christmas by Roberts óbuda this
is an intriguing one at the back here
under this flap because it's not
actually a tree it's sort of the bits
and pieces on it and this one is a cute
angle defaults these main bits are acute
angle defaults that pretty much go flat
when the page goes flat and then they've
got little 3d pieces at each end where
the leaf all sticks to the page you've
got those stuck in so they give these
extra pieces so sebou de the acute angle
V for this tutorial too
and the adding small 3d pieces this
tutorial eight so that's the second one
the third one is the Nutcracker this is
by Nick Dench fields and he's got a very
curious one kind of a solid tree this is
based on a twisting mechanism raising a
variation on the pyramid quite pleasing
really relies a lot on the all the
illustration all over the surfaces of it
the twisting mechanism is tutorial
seventeen and the pyramid it's a
variation of the pyramid that's tutorial
21 last book I'm going to show you is
again it's another The Nutcracker
by Patricia Frey and the tree is here
this is quite a nice seven I think it's
a pretty good tree and this one is based
on it's an acute angle default tutorial
to raising parallelograms tutorial five
and a floating plane variation tutorial
twelve
so I'll just explain those if you look
at it from behind you can see this main
body of it this is the acute angle view
fold this piece coming up here to raise
this this is the floating plane and then
if you look at it from the side here you
can see all these business this is all
the parallelograms coming up the acute
angle google the last one I want to show
you that I'm not actually going to make
is this one this is from a Christmas
card I think it came from the
Smithsonian in Washington I don't see it
actually as a pop-up card it is a paper
sculpture that does fold flat but it
isn't on a base and it's all based on
slots and smuts a tutorial 11 and then
there's this spiral tutorial 10 we will
now move on to the one I'm going to show
you how to make that's this one because
it's so simple you could actually if
you're making a lot of cards for a lot
of your friends you can just turn this
one out quite easily and quite quickly
so we'll need a base there's a base
priests really thoroughly so when you
lay the page flat on the table it just
goes flat this is going to be the tree
so again it's it's been folded in half
you fold it in half and then you fold
the angle the type of tree you want so
if you wanted a much you know squat or
wider one you could you could follow
this as a different angle and so that's
what we've got this time I'll just cut
all this spare off here and now if you
look at this I've done it in three
layers but it doesn't have to be you
could make it a more complicated tree
with it four five six as many layers as
you like I'm going to go with three
again just so it's fairly quick and easy
to make start by cutting it into three
sections each section one and two and
three they've all got the angle of the
fold to the central crease it's the same
on all three but they overlap so the top
layer overlaps the next and that
overlaps the next so you actually need
to refold them so that the next one can
accommodate the one underneath it so
this is going to be the bottom layer
we're going to refold that to the same
angle but you know say another
centimeter in that's centimeter in this
is going to be the bottom one I'll just
cut those tabs cut off that piece and so
this is going to fit on here this is
going to fit on here so we can glue it
about here looks about right
this is gonna be flat as you see when
the page is flat the tree is flat when
it's standing on our mantelpiece or
something yeah it's in dimension
3d tree so we'll start with this in this
case I was going to put the tabs
underneath but in actual fact you could
have them sticking out sideways and make
a more freely edge to the tree if you
want it to as it's going flat I can glue
both both tabs at the same time so then
just check that position again it's
going to go there
line up the central crease on the pop-up
with the central crease on there just
make sure that works okay the second one
is going to overlap it again
we need to refold this at the same angle
but not take it in as much as the
previous one so the last one it came in
about a centimeter so this one I'm going
to bring it in about half a centimeter
so it's a brought in a smaller amount
there and again I'll cut both tabs but
the other thing you need to do here
because it's going to overlap it you
need to cut away a bit here this piece
of tab will clash with the bit of tree
underneath it so we'll actually take off
a piece of that
saying fold those under and this should
be able to just fit on on top of there
quite comfortably you need to line up
the central crease on this pop-up piece
with the central crease on the page so
that's number two we'll just try closing
that making sure it's still all works
there we go and then the third one we
don't need to refold it at all but we
still need to cut out a little piece at
the bottom so it can overlap
satisfactorily also this at the top as
we're folding them under those two tabs
are going to clash so I'll just cut a
bit off there just so it's there's not
going to be a problem and here we need
to cut exciting over there and again we
can put the glue on both tabs at the
same time
and line up the central crease with the
central crease of the base cards overlap
it with a bit of tree below it there we
go
that's all working nicely and now it
looks put our table up to date at the
bottom so this is just an ordinary
parallel fold it's a piece of card with
three parallel creases and this is going
to glue flat down there as well so you
just put glue on both those tabs and
again you line up the central crease
with that central crease of the base we
got under the tree a bit this is the
Christmas tree it looks best when it's
standing up on your mantelpiece like
that so it's in 3d but you can go all
the way flat and then it's up to you to
decorate it you can put stars on it you
can put bubbles on it you can put any
sort of stickers on it photos on it
candles anything you like it's up to you
this is your design in this case I just
put really crudely cut out bits of bacon
oil
it's just silver foil gives us a bit of
sparkle and if I was doing a really nice
one for friends I probably put bits of
glitter all around the rest of the page
as well so that's a really simple easy
quick Christmas card pop up
[Music]
[Applause]