this tutorial is about palm strips these
are two-dimensional motions also called
interactive mechanisms this is the most
simple as you pull the tab the image
changes behind the window this is the
basic pull strip that has all sorts of
applications I'll just show you the most
basic so here's another example that's
easier to see than the other one here
again you've got the image changing
behind the window the fact is you have
to think about with these are the full
strip itself and then the direction of
movement is governed by these two
sleeves I'll explain those in a minute
and this slit the slit in the page so
they control the direction of the
movement of the slit you also have a tab
that controls the amount of movement of
this strip and you can either have one
built in like I've done here or you can
actually just stick a piece of card
across like that so that as you pull it
it'll move along and come up against
this slit in the page I'll put one
together now so you can see how it
actually goes
these do tape measuring so I've had to
measure it and prepare it beforehand
rather than just doing it off the cuff
here this is the actual strip this is
where the two images are going to go to
make the strip strong score it down the
middle then crease it so rather than
just laminating two pieces together by
having a crease and then gluing it you
get a far stronger strip if it was just
pulling then it doesn't matter if it's
single thickness card but because you're
going to have to pull it and push it you
want it to be stuck together really
strong otherwise it will tend to buckle
so this is your pull strip I'll glue it
together right
here's the sheet that it's going to go
on so I've already cut the window in it
these are the places where the two
sleeves are going to fit this is the
slit that the thing goes through so I'll
just cut this when you cut one of these
slits cut it back a couple of MIL at
each end so that the card can just lift
up ever so slightly that makes it the
whole thing just move that much more
easily so these are the sleeves you have
two creases stick them down one on each
side of the window that the images are
going to appear in so just crease these
quite well glue it down but these you
don't want too much glue or you want to
anything you're gluing like this you
need to make sure you let it dry because
if the glue oozing it does gum up the
works and things don't work so well so
that's one sleeve this is the other
I've already scored it where it needs to
fold and you're adding glue always put
glue on the small piece of card not the
big one so this sleeve is the small bit
and the base is the big bit so you put
the glue onto the sleeve stick it in
place now if we look at the pull strip
itself it's going to fit around this way
around you'll see these sleeves have to
be a couple of millimeters wider than
the strip itself on each side so they
don't actually grip it so they're going
to fold over like this when you close it
down you just need the smallest dab of
glue so I'll just poke it through here
first
that moves nice and easy now we can take
this side close it down put the smallest
dab of glue there's no stress on this so
it doesn't need much glue the main thing
is that it doesn't ooze and gum up the
work so that's one sleeve and here's the
other one
little bit of glue there
close it down this is the pull strip in
action this is the most amazing
hide-and-seek counting book by Robert
Krauser is very old book but it's got a
lot of this type of thing in it so the
one I want to show you is this one here
you've actually got this one the pull
strip it comes up and it comes out of
the page and back down under but as you
put it you can see there's an image
changing behind a window here and
there's an image dropping interview
there and there's another couple here
this is Leon the chameleon by Nina canny
AK and here is down here this is the
pull strip as you pull it you can see
the image changing there's another kind
of pull strip this is a kind which this
is really crude where you actually have
a slot down the page and as you pull the
pull strip it moves the image down the
page if we look at the back of that all
you need is the slit in the page again
it's been cut back slightly to make it
move easily but the construction under
here holds it in place and the length of
the slot governs how far it will move
I'll just make one of those real quickly
so just take a piece of card score it
cut it
fold it in half move it but there's a
pull strip ready to go now we need a
slot that it's going to fit through so
again you need you do need to cut it
with a ruler this time really so I make
slot like this and make it back two or
three millimeters wide make another cut
cut that out and then you're going to
need one slit at the end here so just
judging by how wide that is and just
come across like this make the two
little cuts and now get to the crucial
bit you just need a piece like this so
you glue it onto the pull strip it needs
to come in and shut up you're going to
have two small pieces like this that
shut up through the slot so here's the
other side there yeah so these two ends
will stand up come up through the slot
we'll just glue those down as well just
put a bit of glue under here
this is extremely fast and prude and
just trim that down slightly so feed it
through there the other ends come up
through there they fold over and you can
glue your image whatever it may be onto
these two here
and then you've got a piece that slides
up and down the page like that there's
one here that there's a variation so
this is the main one like I've just made
but this is a strip with three creases
in it this end is glued on to the
equivalent of this this end is glued on
to the page so as you pull this you get
this rising up 3d shape there's another
one here where I've actually stuck a
mask down over the works so this one as
you pull it you see the jaw drop and the
eyes change this one I actually made
before I fully understood this mechanism
so when you look you'll see that as you
put it down there's two which is
unnecessary you only actually need one I
quite like the idea of the mask that
comes across and hides all the workings
so then you've got a much more pleasing
mechanism all these things are covered
in my most recent book pop-up design and
paper mechanics and it does take pull
strips a bit further but the real detail
is in this earlier book can pop up a
manual of paper mechanisms and this goes
into much more detail about pull strips
actually out of print but I think it's
possible to get secondhand versions