[Music]
I'm going to show you how to make a
Valentine card which in this case is a
figure leaping up and the the figure is
going to be holding a couple of hearts
so this is based on the parallelogram
which is tutorial five there's a couple
of other examples I've got here I'll
just show you before I start here's
another one holding a ball or something
but we're going to make it a heart and
actually you can play with this you can
have more than one figure so here's
another example of two figures it's the
same basic principle it's still based on
the parallelogram I find this quite
pleasing really start with a base card
here's the base thoroughly creased and
then here's another piece we want it to
fit in to blend in with the background
I'm just going to make quite a small
parallelogram like this piece here so
fold in a tab on one end and then we
come along something like that put a
crease in it and then a short distance
like that and then we're going to have a
tab on the other end so this is standard
parallelogram
right and then just reinforce these
creases so it all works really well so
the key to this one is this is the
parallelogram long side short side when
the base is flat the parallelogram is
flat and there's there are going to have
two little triangles here and here and
here and here which is what the limbs
fit onto so here's the piece with the
three creases and then it's here we
won't fold it in like that and we'll do
the same on this side as well when we
open that up we've got these four little
triangles and so we just make sure
that's all really thoroughly priest so
that all moves really
sweetly when it comes to being stuck
together
now with all parallelograms you have a
long side stuck over a short distance to
the spine and you've got a short side
which is stuck down a long distance from
the spine so I get the pencil and I'll
just mark the short side here where the
crease lies so that's there and because
the whole thing goes flat when the base
is flat we don't need to measure the
other end so I put glue on there
that's the long side of the
parallelogram stuck down parallel to the
spine and just a short distance from it
stick this side down so that should go
flat down just actually do it this way
round so folding it into its closed
position close the base it finds where
it wants to stick and then we open that
up and it goes flat when the base is
flat here we have these four little
triangles and that's where we can stick
the limbs on so I'll just make a series
of limbs from this piece these can be
tricky because as it closes they all
move in in different directions you
might need to play around and tailor
these so that as it closes they don't
like this hand you can see there's a bit
of a bend there it looks as though at
some points it's snagged against the
page or the spine as the page is closed
so you might need to play around with
these to find the ones that work for you
in this example the limbs are in a
different formation so this one as you
close it you can see the way this leg is
going it is in danger of snagging
against that page but it's okay and it
has been worked out nicely so I'll just
make four four limbs from this so we go
with a bent leg I'm just going to make
these quite crudely in this case
so here's a leg let's make it a bit
shorter and we can stick that on like
this now I just put some glue on this
triangle stick the leg in and I would
just check that that does actually work
as the page closes that one's swinging
around against the page so that one
seems okay but try another one if this
was just stuck on straight on to here I
think we might have some trouble so I'm
going to change the shape at the top of
the leg so that you can bring this down
so I'll tape that that corner off there
and now I'll put some glue on there and
try this one out so as you can see this
it's not actually doing what I want so
we're gonna have to change this take it
off and start so this was the leg that
didn't work that was like that like that
and that one didn't work so let's just
have a look at these I've adjusted this
a little bit more put a bit more glue
back on there try it again
that's right coming out at this angle
this time close to page yeah okay so
that's four legs working now we want a
couple of arms let's come up to
something like this we don't really need
to worry about the hands too much
because it's gonna be holding some
hearts so that's just
if you look at these and they're stuck
on the small side the piece is actually
rotate against the page so there's very
little chance of there actually being a
problem there
it's these ones stuck on to these two
triangles that are on the long side as
the page closes they actually flip over
that's where the problems start arising
we've got that limb okay and now we'll
just do one more I'll try making it come
up it's a bit of an angle like this I
think judging by that that seems to be
okay and this one
something like that
maybe I'll just just give it a try
close it down that's looking good just
about it's slightly not quite happy but
not too bad and then we need a head so
I'll just do something really basic for
that this time no I'm gonna change it
and put it on this side because we know
this this side is safe it rotates that
way rather than flipping over so we know
that stuck on that side the head will be
okay in fact when you come to making
your own design you'd probably make all
these out of one piece so the two arms
would be one piece of just a crease down
the middle yeah you can see that's what
I've done in this case the arms are one
piece of the crease and the legs are one
piece of the crease but to do this I had
to go through a number of dummy ruts
attempt till I got the angles all right
and then now this is working okay so now
we can just add the hearts so this one
doesn't really matter where the heart is
because we know it'll move safely
there's one on there that's working okay
you've got to be careful here because
we've got to look at where is it tending
to snag and you can see it's tending to
snag at this bottom bit whereas the top
bit here is the safe place to have it so
let's just stick it in there and stick
that on as we close it yeah it's working
in your own design of course it's not
going to be as crude as this you might
even put your own photo in here and you
can put all sorts of stuff around here
there's plenty of scope for more design
work but this is the basic mechanism
that's the the bringer of hearts
Valentine's card
you
[Music]