[Music]
I'm going to show you how to make a
sitting dog pop up which is just a fun
way of using the acute angle v-folds
this cute angle v-fold is quite an
unusual mechanism not used very often
but this is quite a nice way of using it
so here's the base sheet I've already
folded it I'll just give it a bit more
folding we're gonna use a sheet like
this fold it in half and creased really
well and I already started making one so
the stage I'd got to is this is the
original sheet here's how it fits onto
the original sheet here's the first
crease and we put a crease coming up
from that corner at roughly 45 degrees
depending really on what angle you want
your dog's sitting at like that folded
back as you can see this is the crease
so there's tabs along the bottom we've
cut tabs off cut the tabs off here we'll
sort that out some more in a minute we
also want the front of the dog to be
coming down here so I'll just cut
straight up there you can draw your
sitting dog onto it so we have the back
legs as sort of like this and coming
forward so they're part of the tab we
have the dog's chest coming up like this
and these front legs coming down like
there
and from there no can cut those out
which is well I've already done so
here's my drawing here's what I've done
these are the tabs they're going to fold
in underneath or outside let's have a
look how it's it's going to sit on the
page like this like that probably have
the front paws in and the back paws out
I've also made a little slit at the back
here so we can fit a tail in I'm also
going to make the very top into a couple
of tabs so we can stick a head on there
bend those over you open it up there's
the two tabs at the top then we're going
to stick the head on with now we'll
stick the dog down on the page just see
you know what sort of angle you want him
at you want them really wide I think
pretty narrow is best
I might actually put the tail in before
we go any further so I'll just cut a
nice curly tail curling up a little bit
bushy Soviet foxy maybe
put a bit of glue on one side and put it
in there so it shuts up
now we glue the two back legs maybe on
this version I made them slightly small
for such a big dog so we'll just do one
side and then we'll fold it down before
we do the other though he's going to be
something like this so there's one leg
now close it down put a bit of glue on
the other side should have done the
front feet while I was at it but here we
go shut this down sorry I've made a
mistake with this tail it's just an a
bad angle
move it up there we are now I can shut
this down he's sitting up this foot
hasn't been glued I better put some glue
on that I did certainly be better
pointing in I've got that one pointing
out I'll make this other one pointing in
[Applause]
I've glued it in place it's the glue is
still soft so I'll just shut it down so
if it needs to move it can still move
there we are that's the basic dog and
now we need a head so something like one
of these trial just take a nice
triangular bit of card this looks like
quite a good dog head actually maybe
something like this see what that looks
like all the tabs out
that is not too bad maybe too big maybe
alright yeah that's probably okay really
I might make a couple more flaps so I
can put a couple of ears on as well so
bend those over bend them back and then
individually now I'll stick the the dog
head on a little bit of glue on each
side slide that on while it's soft just
see what you think there's that a good
angle down a bit more up a bit more
quite like it see how that's working it
seems to be okay though the ears and
again I just make them quite floppy
looking ears something like that maybe
and that should be able to stick on like
that move on
stays Olivia
quite a simple pop-up quite easy to make
a nice useful use of the pointed v-fold
if you want you can always stress the
dog up you could you know stick a hat on
it but a jacket on it socks you know
just play around you can also of course
decorate and the base of it sitting on
so that's it nice simple pop-up
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]