[Music]
this Valentine card is about how to
raise a heart really high mother page so
here's an example without the heart just
showing how the whole thing folds down
and lifts up high there's another little
example here it's the same idea that you
open the page and it just lifts that
it's all based on a really mechanism
that's expressed really well in this
book by Philippe look big bang pop and
the colors are really fantastic in this
book the pop-up is actually fairly easy
most of the time but the book I just
think the book is really beautiful this
is the one we're going for when you open
the page and it rises really high above
the page so you do need to measure in
this it's based on the acute angle V
I'll just look at this one this is the
acute angle V fold the that's doing the
main lifting and then this bit here this
is the asymmetric parallel fold which is
tutorial 6 I've measured up some an
example here this is the base the V is
going to stick down here the angle is 67
degrees and I measured both sides so
I'll be able to just stick it straight
down and then if you look at these they
have a piece here that's pushing up the
the arm that lifts right up this is
going to stick to this line 2,8
centimeters behind the
and then this is the actual piece itself
this is the v-fold 77 degrees on each
side this height is ten point five
centimeters and then where the arm this
will be the arm that will stick behind
it the arm sticks onto this upper limb
1,5 centimeters above the crease and the
arm itself this takes some pressure so
it has to be double thickness I scored
it down the middle it's got a tab on
each end the distance between the two
tabs is eleven point eight centimeters
so I'm going to glue that shut in a
minute and just so you understand the
maps in this as you look at it here's
the dimensions the lengths this is if
you look at it as it folds down it's
asymmetric you're actually working from
here you've got the length of the
pushing up strip plus the little piece
on the top that is this eleven point
eight plus one point five that gives you
thirteen point three and the other bit
on the base you've got two point eight
and on the upright you've got ten point
five so you add those together you've
got thirteen point three so that's
giving you balance this is a balanced
asymmetric parallel fold I just think it
all together make sure that it does
actually work this is going to go I'm
going to stick it on this way round so
all these dimensions as I've measured it
I can put glue on both sides at the same
time
as usual glue all the way to the crease
rather than the edge of the piece of
card glue this down and then we'll just
close that to make sure it works okay
when you have a double thickness strip
this is double thickness because it does
take some some pressure so I stuck this
down with all the measurements there
hidden behind the v-fold and the same
with this it's eleven point eight
centimeters between the two creases but
I'm going to fold that in glue it shut
so you won't see that again all pull
strips or push strips strips a double
thickness to give it extra strength
always good to glue them always good if
they have a fold that makes it also
stronger that's that there we go and
then this lose on to this guide line
that I've drawn on the page I'm going to
stick it onto this top bit first because
I haven't marked how far along this line
it actually glues but with luck it
should all all just work nicely so put
the glue on there stick that to that
line
incidentally well everything is parallel
this crease here on the v-fold is at the
same angle as this line here this crease
with this arm it's going to lift up is
at the same angle to this central crease
as this one and then this is glued on
also parallel so all these creases
they're all parallel now this should
when it comes down
this should stick like that I'll just
put glue on that side and glue that
shirt this is gonna go down like that
this is the closed position you know we
can open it up and see how it works
there we go actually it seems this extra
piece I've done isn't quite strong
enough it's actually buckling a bit
ideally I probably would have made that
three or four three or four thicknesses
and then we can just stick ideally I
think it would have been either thicker
card a bit more rigid I would have made
this a bit stronger that's the basic
idea and as you close it it folds away
so no we have the sky high Valentine's
cards this is a smaller example and
because it's all smaller it doesn't
matter that the cards are not so rigid
and it does stands up it does seem to
actually work slightly better than the
one I've just made so maybe we could
just pull this heart off here and stick
it onto this one there is the sky high
Valentine card
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]