this tutorial is about exploiting away
parallel fold to move as you open close
the spread here's the example as you
open it the flower opens and you can see
the way it works there's a flower stem
is stuck to the spine and it comes up
through a hollow to you the hollow tube
is then attached to this parallel fold
and as it closes the spine fold goes
down and the top of the parallel fold
comes up and as the whole thing opens
the spine fold comes up and the parallel
fold goes down and so it's the mechanism
transfers that movement to the top of
the flower and it's quite a new
mechanism but there's two or three books
that I'll show you that have it in so
the first one I'd like to show you is
trail by David Pellom
it's a really beautiful book this all
done in white and the flower is here in
the middle and as it opens you see the
flower open and if you look at it end on
you can see there's the stalk that comes
up through the middle and all the the
parallel fold is extremely fancy and
then you've got more parallel folds on
the top and counter folds the whole
thing is really quite spectacular the
second one is Leola chameleon by Nina
connieyc and in this case it's not a
flower opening it's a flamingo spreading
its wings and the whole structure is
down here it's pretty small slightly
disguised by these floating water lilies
parallel fold if we look at it and done
you can see there is a stork comes up
the middle and that's the body of the
flamingos attached to that as you open
and close it the bird open zeroes it
wings and the last one is paper blossoms
by Ray Marshall this is slightly
differently flowers aren't on such high
stalks all of them work on the same
principle there's a stalk up the middle
pushing up the middle of the flower and
then those pieces on the outside pulling
it down all the flowers on this have
built onto the strap which is tutorial
nine that as the page goes flat
the pop-up goes fairly flat and it
creates these gullies off-center and
then these two flowers are built into
that those gullies these run that
working on the central gully if you look
at it end on you can see there's a
pillar goes up the middle raises the
middle of the flower and then there's
pieces on the outer edges pull down the
outer edges of the flower so now I'll
just make one so we start with a face
sheet
well folded creased really thoroughly
and then this is the piece that's going
to be the stalk up the middles I'm
making it several layers thick I've
scored it already beforehand so I can
just fold it up put glue in I've also
measured it I've cut it so it's got
flaps at the bottom flaps at the top so
these are the ones that we'll stick it
to the base these are the ones that will
stick it to the flower and I've measured
it so I've put the crease where it's
going to stick to the spine there and
you can see the top of the whole thing
is going to come here that's where the
flower is going to stick on so we'll
start by just gluing it shut and gluing
it to the spine so just fold this all
shirts so here it is this is the stock
that's going to go up the middle it's
got two flaps
the button we'll just stick those to the
spine
so that's duct flush with the spine then
this is the parallel fold that's going
to go over the top this is how it is
it's got a tab on each side and it's got
a hole in the middle for the stork to go
through so just check that out that's
going to be like that fold these
underneath so I'll glue them both at the
same time that will follow that method
of gluing these stick one side down
first and then let the other one find
its natural position
there's one I fold it all into the into
the closed position
shut the base so it knows where it wants
to be I'll just make the sleeve that
goes over this stalk so they need to
score lines I'm just one cut line fold
it well make sure it folds neatly into a
tube and then at the bottom this is
where it's going to attach to the
parallel fold so we'll just fold that
layer and take one of those out so it's
just got two flaps at the bottom here's
the sleeve this is going to click over
the stalk we need to measure how high
this is coming up and slit it to that
point that comes up to there make sure
it's flush against there and slit it
down to here I'll just cut another piece
off so it's just left with two flaps you
cut that down to here
and split it up to here so there's two
flaps and we can glue it shut not too
much glue
and now sit this over the sleeve
I just wanna poke this into it to open
it up a bit settle or work easily no
y'all we glued these two onto the
parallel fold
oh yeah now these are going to float
back this is the flower piece we can
glue this onto the flaps we've made at
the top of the stalk
when this is flat these will be coming
up to join onto it so you now need to
add the creases where it's going to just
fit on on to the flower at the top so
you've got one there and one here let's
check that the height is all right bit
by and large this but you'll get the
idea and now we glue these onto the
flower in its open position so with that
flat that's straight up we just glue
that on and then we need to wait a
minute for the glue to go off because
then then we'll close the whole thing a
little front these two pieces meet need
folding them so we'll close the whole
thing and it'll find its natural place
just before I do that I'll just say you
can learn more in this my book pop-up
design and paper mechanics but there's
nothing about this mechanism in it
there's all sorts of other interesting
stuff so with luck now this glue has
gone off enough we can close it and make
sure that these folds crease in the
right place there you go
you