this tutorial is back flaps so here we
are there's two kinds this kind as you
pull the tab tip pulls in the direction
of the pole it's a very very easy
structure and this type is more
interesting as you pull the tab it moves
in the opposite direction to the pole
I'll just start by making a couple the
first one here it is the pull strip the
basic pull strip is explained in
tutorial 25 and so all pull strips must
be double thickness they also need
measuring so I've done all the measuring
and prepared these pieces beforehand
just to make it quicker so this is the
pool strip it's been scored down the
middle folded and then always glue it
when it's going to fold in it and it's
glued it just makes the whole thing
stronger so you can push it pull it no
buckling and this one the pull strip is
double thickness and then at the end one
thickness you just have this little tab
which is what's going to stick onto the
flap and lift it up this is the flap I
prepared the flap has a tab on the
bottom that that will stick to the page
and the place I've measured it to be put
the glue on the tab and glue it to the
page the pull strip is going to stick on
here and go through these two slits in
the page the slits need to be cut so
they go back a bit this end they only
need to go back
couple of meals that the car just lifts
up and very little bit but this but it
needs to be cut back about a centimeter
so it can lift up more so you just feed
it through feed it through this side as
well and then we can stick the tab on
top but I think it's just nature it goes
underneath so it's hidden from you put
some glue on that one and stick it down
let it go off and yep there you go see
it's lifting the flow there is another
way of doing this where the strip goes
through the flap and there's a good
example in this Robert crafters book the
most amazing hide-and-seek counting book
and if we open it up this is one we're
looking at as you pull it it lifts up
the flap and it's actually got another
flap underneath so you can see this has
been pushed through there's a slot in
the flap here again the slope will be
about two millimeters wide and to
construct this there are creases here
and here so these two bits have been
folded up and pushed through the slot in
the main flap and then unfolded again
and then this end is pushed through that
page so that's just another variation of
this type
the other kind which is more interesting
really is this type which lifts up away
from the direction of the pool and it's
based on earth I guess the slotting the
pages of fulcrum I've got a bigger one
here so you can see it much more clearly
the strip has these two little tabs on
each side and they fold up while you
push the whole thing through this slot
then you unfold them and they keep the
whole thing in position
here's the one I prepared this is the
pull strip double-thickness
so I'll just glue that so that's the
double thickness pull strip and now here
these are the two little tabs which will
fold down as you can strut the whole
piece this is a another fold here which
is what makes the whole thing work the
important thing is to between this point
between the little tabs and the main
flap this point and this point where the
crease is that's about seven mil that's
fairly crucial you have the main flap
and then you have these two little tabs
which fold up and go through the
slotting the page and then unfold again
and the rest of the strip goes through
this slit here you fold them down this
is a not a slit so this is two or
three millimeters wide whereas this is a
slit it's just it's straight cutting the
page so you can fold those down you push
the whole thing through the page and
then you unfold them on the other side
that's now holding it in position this
comes through here and that gives you
the moving action the first book I'd
like to show you is jungle days by Helen
barber and this is the type of flap that
moves away from the direction of the
pull and it's got an image attached to
it so as you pull it the flap lifts up
and the crocodile jump
you look at it end on you can see
there's the flap underneath it that's
moving away from the direction of the
pull strip then it's got the image
attached to it and the other type we've
looked at here it is this is the type
that the flap is pulled up in the
direction of the pull strip so as you
pull it it comes down that's the other
kind the other book I'd like to show you
this is quite an interesting variation
this is Little Red Riding Hood's by
Bruce Foster and in this case this is a
flap and these are the tabs but instead
of pulling the tabs to make the flat
move you lift the flap and it makes the
tab smooth you pull the flap down and
these move up and then in this case the
flap has got to be folds underneath it
the next one I'd like to show you is
color surprises some French coolies
surprised by David Pellom and this one
here it is this is the type of flat
where the flap moves away from the
direction of the pull and in this case
there's a couple of the folds underneath
it the the main head of the critter is a
parallel fold and then you've got two
v-folds each side quite a nice one there
the next one I'd like to show you is
robot by Lampe and Kowski these are two
flaps on one pole so as you pull it this
near one is the type that lifts up in
the direction of the pull and this one
goes in the opposite direction so as you
pull it they both lift and this one has
a v-fold underneath it this one has a
parallel fold underneath it quite a nice
example there I'd like to show you a few
more of these ones I've got here this is
just a really simple example of how you
can get the two flaps working together
you look at the back of it it's just the
strip is double you can see it all
pretty clearly though this is where
you've got the flap moving away from the
direction of the pool but in this case
it's got a
parallelogram built on the back of it
and it's going to pop up on the front of
that so here you can see the
parallelogram you can see the action
underneath the page you can lift it up
this has got these two tabs now that
come up against this slit and stop it
moving that makes it stop when it's in
the vertical position this is delayed
double action so it's a bit more
complicated as you pull the strip first
one flap lifts and then the other one so
the way this works this flap is actually
a pocket it's not just one piece of card
it's actually hollow inside and so when
you look at it this way around you can
see the end of the pull strip actually
goes up inside the pocket so as you pull
it it comes that it lifts it up and then
slides back the second flap is moved by
this piece and these come through this
window in the page so as you pull it it
doesn't engage initially it has to go
that far
then it engages and can lift the second
flap and so the key thing here is the
distance between you look both the flaps
are working through a slot in the page
so here you see the two slots in the
page the distance between them is the
same as the distance between this crease
and this point in the window in the
slide where it engages so that's the
crucial thing with this one and I can
show you a really nice example of that
in action this is robot by young peon
Kowski it's this snakehead here as you
pull the tab first the tongue comes out
and then you carry on pulling and then
the snake head lifts up and the eyes are
built onto that flap you might be useful
to look at it sort of sideways on like
that you can see that tat is when it's
down first the tongue goes and then the
head goes and the eye
flip over and there's one more I'd like
to show you this is Alice in
Wonderland's and the paper engineering
is by Roger Diaz this is the one I want
to look at as you lift the page the pull
strip is actually turning over the flap
this is the automatic pull strip in
action working with a flap I think the
automatic pool strip is tutorial 16
that's it for this tutorial on flaps
that there's more about them in these
two books of mine this is the most
recent one pop-up design and paper
mechanics there's a bit more about flaps
in there there's a lot more about pull
strips in this book pop up a manual of
paper mechanisms this is the first book
I did and there's a lot about pull tabs
in it
you