this tutorial is about how to use
asymmetric v-folds to raise a structure
on one side of the page the first
example I've got is mommy by Matthew
Reinhart
illustrated by Maurice Sendak and the
final amazing spread on the right you've
got this flap this is the structure the
sculpture being made this is the gully
down here and this is the sculpture
being raised on one side of it and these
two little pieces here these are the
asymmetric v-folds that lift the whole
thing really delightful piece of work
that the way the head moves the arms
move I can tell you which previous
tutorials lead up to this tutorial for
is asymmetric v-folds tutorial 5 is
parallelograms which it's built onto
tutorial 15 is moving arms and tutorial
24 is circular movement so those are all
used to make that that mechanism and the
other one I'd like to show you is this
one very different
this is pop-up book and Nursery Rhymes
again it's by Mathew Reinhardt this is
the spread so in this case this is the
structure that's been raised on the one
side of this crease here and the
asymmetric V pod is actually hidden
underneath this floating plane so here
you can see this is the floating plane
this is the asymmetric V fold which has
been used to raise this structure if you
look at this structure end on you can
see it's all parallelograms all being
raised by
one plane which is lifted by the
asymmetric v-fold so now I'll just run
through some angles for the isometric
viewpoint even a couple of examples in
this one this small angle is 30 degrees
and this is 90 degrees and on the page
the angle between the spine and where it
sticks down that's 30 and the angle
between the spine or it sticks down here
that's 90 when the whole thing is flat
the whole single life left and as you
can see as it closes like this the whole
thing moves forward so you can build
parallelograms onto this flap here in
this version the angle and the base is
still 30 but the small angle and the
asymmetric v-fold is 35 and the angle on
the base is 90 and the angle on the
asymmetric v-fold is 95 so I've made one
of those here here's the piece you've
got the big angle on the asymmetric
piece is 95 and the small angle on it is
40 degrees on the base you've got 90 and
35 so I'll just stick that band so you
can see how it goes with all these
asymmetric so you have a the small angle
on the pop-up goes over the big angle on
the page the big angle on the pop-up
goes over the small angle on the page so
it's going to stick though like that
I'll just glue this and stick it on as
I've measured the positions on the base
and on the pop-up I can just do it all
rather than sticking down one side and
letting it find its natural position
stick that down there and that down
there there it is close it down I've
left this flap on the top just so you
can build parallelograms onto it and
that's it really the useful tip for
building things on one side of the base