[Music]
this is a pleasing little mechanism
called the jack-in-the-box the base is
very tall and narrow and when you open
it the pop-up is wider than the base so
quite an unusual piece and so you do
need a ruler and a pencil and a biro to
score it with the pleasure of it is is
wider than it is tall so when you come
to measuring you're measuring it on a
half sheet like this and you're
measuring it this way round start with
the piece folded in half always with
pop-ups you start with it folded in half
that way everything is symmetrical so
we're going to be measuring from that
I'll do it with our pen so you can see
and then we'll make that the back of the
design I'm putting the ruler up against
the central crease and do one line down
there one line down here one line across
the top and the second one and then you
actually need to mark a third distance
down just you just need to mark at the
central point so this is the basic grid
that you're going to be working from
we're going to have tabs on each side
here and here where it glues on to the
background and then we need to score to
make these creases here these are
starting from here you score up like
that
and this one here as well so we score
all these diagonals for diagonals and
then cut it out so it's going to be a
tab down here so we cut away from that
line that's the tab that's going to glue
it to the page
and on this side as well these are the
arms so we just cut along those lines
the head up here
here's the basic shape it's got a crease
in the middle it's easier to actually if
you fold it in half and then fold along
those diagonals so you just fold it like
that along the diagonal and this one you
fold it along the diagonal and then when
you come to push it into shape it all
moves nice and easy so it goes like that
and then don't forget these side tabs
don't think I scored those actually I'll
just give them a quick run over with the
biro so they fold nice and cleanly so
here it is all the guide lines are on
this one so we're going to take it on
that way round so we need to actually
refold it slightly just so it all works
nicely and then I've got a piece here
this again is it's the basically the
same size as this it's a half sheet of
a4 but that we're going to stick it on
this way round you can stick it down
flat and I'm going to actually leave a
little bit at the bottom that we can
play with later so put the glue on both
tabs at the same time because we're
gluing it flat
I'm gonna stick it just above the bottom
edge line up the central crease of the
pop up line it up with the central
crease of the base so here it is just
make sure it works nicely there we are
and now you can actually make the base
even smaller you can close it down and
just see how near the outer edge that is
how near the top these are and just trim
it down so I can look in there I can see
it's to about there and trim all that
off and I can also make the whole thing
about a centimeter half an inch narrower
so I can trim this off as well we've got
this quite small card that when you open
it quite a big Jack in a box appears now
when it closes you'll see the top of the
arms come up flush with the spine so you
can't put anything above the top of the
arms but you can have anything you like
hanging down below them because as it
closes you've got that space between the
bottom of the arm and the edge of the
card now you can actually turn this into
a pop-up standing on a base so here's a
base we're just going to make a basic
right angled refold so that's where I've
left this space at the bottom a
centimeter there so I could actually
score that and make that into a pair of
tabs and then as with all of these you
just need to cut out that corner below
where all the creases match and I'll cut
off those so this can now turn into a
v-fold rising off the page I've pushed
that in too far there we are so this is
going to sit on it
you just fold these this is going to sit
on the base like this you need it near
the front of your card so as it closes
it's going to fold down this way and we
just need to make sure it's going to fit
within the corners of the base cards and
in this case glue one side and stick
that down and then the other side so
I'll put glue on them both to start off
with right so we've position it on the
base it's all fitting nicely within the
base card that side stuck down close
that close the base that finds where it
wants to be okay up and there's the
pop-up now in actual fact we've got too
much background here that is not really
necessary so we can just cut a load of
that off you can cut it in from here you
might actually want even less so we
could take the the craft knife and just
cut a whole lot more off cutting down
here I probably should have done this
before sticking it to the base and the
other side
there we are pop-up jack-in-the-box
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]