this tutorial is about curved shapes
that is the taking the crease around the
bend so this is at its most simple it
gives you a beak or a nose this is a
more more extreme example so in this
case you're taking the the crease all
the way around a complete curve and here
isn't another example again it's taking
it all the way around the curve
the difference between these two this
one is based on parallel folds this one
is based on refold the difference
between these two is explained in
tutorial 1 the introduction so I'll just
show you a couple of examples
obviously in action this is a very
simple simple one it's just again it's
just going around one curve and the
other this is a point of view fold
that's in tutorial 3 this example this
is the parallel fold curved shape giving
you the fish it comes all the way around
you can see here we've got a small piece
added to make the tail with these curved
shapes you can stick pieces on any point
on the curve and they'll stick out at a
different angle so it's quite fun to
play with there's another example here
in this case this is based on the v-fold
and in this case the ears these are the
tabs that glue the piece to the page and
the whole thing is quite a solid rigid
structure so you can cut chunks away
like the
the math of the dog has been cut away so
I'll just start by showing you how to
make a small curved shape a beak or a
nose onto this built into this gully of
this this floating plane that we made in
tutorial 12 take a small piece of card
fold it in half lengthways crease it
really well and make this into a V fold
as we did in tutorial 2 so you make a
crease like this this is the first
crease up this side what you're making
here is a pair of folds that give you a
sort of downward pointing arrow and just
cut that to make a couple of gluing tabs
so here's the piece now make another
fold it can be any angle really
depending on what shape you want to
create so make something like this fold
that back on itself open it up so now
you've got another downward pointing
arrow cut out one side of it so you're
cutting a longer crease so here you've
got a cottage that is matching this this
folded edge the other side you make that
into a gluing tab and fold that down and
crease it well so this is now just going
to fold shut like that put your glue
put it on the put it on the tab here we
are
fold it shut and now the whole piece
should just go flat and according to how
you stick it down that will affect what
shape you create and so we're going to
stick it here into this gully created on
the the floating plane I'm just going to
cut these back a bit I think I've got
the tabs a little bit big so put glue on
one side decide what shape you want to
make so is it going to be you know
really wide coming down a lot or
sticking out quite a lot
make sure the central crease of this
glue so make sure the central crease of
this this nose piece is lined up with
the gully on the floating plane and you
put glue on the other tab close the base
press it firmly there you have it
the most simple variation on the curved
shapes show you how to make one of these
that the fish was based on take a base
sheet
drink precip screens thoroughly take
another piece cards we'll go with yellow
cut it in half just by eyes learning to
measure fold it in half crease it well
and unfold two more creases onto the
outer edge these are the gluing tabs one
centimeter or half an inch wide you've
got these three three creases or
parallel now you only actually want
gluing tabs in the middle about one inch
to centimeters two and a half
centimeters something like that so you
can cut cut away the bulk of what you
folded so you have a piece like this
open up you've got a tab on each side
you can reinforce those individually now
now take a pencil and starting you make
a mark on the top this is the top crease
so make two marks that are in line with
deep with the corners of the tab so
you've got two marks like this make two
more marks about a third of the way up
the outer edges so this is going to be
your curve so you can draw your curve on
to it something like this and then you
you break this curve down into a series
of short straight edges so I'll just go
for two so you make a mark like this and
this now these are going to be straight
edges here so you start by just cutting
out this is crucial you just cut it on
one side so cut out here and cut these
straight lines
and the same on this side okay so you
have a piece like this now fold it into
its closed position and mark where those
those cup lines lie so here they are so
when you open this up now you can see
you've got lines that exactly match the
cut lines so these are going to be tabs
built onto those so cut away
now you can fold ice to make the tabs
fold along those lines fold them back on
themselves
there we go make sure the creases are
pretty good and then in this case you
put glue on all four tabs at the same
time and then you can just fold it down
and fold the whole piece right
so just make sure that it's all all
working okay that it opens up nicely now
this is going to stick along your spine
something like this but you'll see
because these corners are still there it
bags into the page so you're going to
have to cut these off in a curve to
match the page and it all depends what
angle you cut it out all depends on how
wide you going with the the basic shape
so let's just try it right like that no
no you can see this this will now fit
down on your page and it you can have
the tabs out or you can have them in a
weekly how how wide you're going to go
see what the distance is that you need
from the spine stick down one side so
it's about there put glue on the other
side close it down
takes quite a lot of strain this so you
know make sure it's it's glue really
firmly and there's your shape well there
it is
this shape creates those gullies on each
side you can build into there's also
this mountain fold running all the way
around that you can build on top of you
can also cut holes in it and here's just
a really and abstract little example of
pieces added on to it so here we've got
v-fold stuck into the gullies on it on
each side we've got slots cut into the
into the main body of it with these
pieces sticking out here we've got a
extra piece stuck on over the mountain
foam all these the v-folds the slots the
small additional pieces they're all
covered in other tutorials finally I'll
just show you some examples in books so
jungle days by Helen bomber here is a
really beautiful use of the curved shape
this head of the elephant haunted house
by lampion caskey is a pretty strange
little curved shape rising up from the
page with with spirals attached this is
dine Autopia
James Gurney's diner topia and here it
says this this is the curved shape the
top of this dinosaur is the colored
shape in this case it's built onto a box
mechanism and the box mechanism is what
we're doing in the next tutorial
tutorial 14 and lastly this is wonderful
earth by Nick Butterworth and Mick
Inkpen and it just has one pop-up in it
but it is a really amazing use of the
curved shape and you've got we've got it
on the outside of the structure you've
also got it on the
side and everything we've looked at in
this tutorial is covered in this my book
pop-up design and paper mechanics
you