[Music]
this card is a Valentine's card and I
call it shower of hearts here it is this
is based on an M fold tutorial 19 this
is how the em fold goes it's basically
an acute V fold with acute v-folds built
into the gullies but all made in one so
this is tutorial 19 and then in actual
fact that as counter folds added to it
added into all the creases
that's tutorial 22 so here's an M fold
with added cats and creases giving you
these counter folds that give you more
planes that can all be extended like
this you'll see that all the little
different planes have got these arms
stuck onto them with hearts and stuff on
the end so I'll just show you how to
make one of those really quickly here's
a base sheet folded in half
creased really thoroughly this will be
the M fold so again we just fold it in
half
we cut a wedge out of the up to about
third of the way up something like that
fold the two sides back like this
so we've got the two angles and you open
it up the angles on each side below that
point they're both the same and then you
just take one side fold it up now this
crease must be leaning out away from the
spine it mustn't come to the same point
where all the other
is me so you just have it folding up
something like this fold that back on
itself and then on the other side it
doesn't have to be the same we can just
fold it up and again we creat it leaning
out away from the middle fold so fold
that back on itself and now we can
concertina this so these folds come
forward tricky there we are and then
fold that back when it comes like this
crease it all this will be your M fold
I'll just trim it down a bit it's a bit
too big
that's it back something like this and
now we have the counter folds into all
these creases I might even make that
slightly lower because we're going to
have to do the arms that hold the hearts
will be jutting out quite a lot sort of
stake like that on any of these creases
you can have extra cuts fold them back
on themselves and back again push that
through so we've generated two more
planes there that can have things added
to them this one maybe we won't cut it
we'll just fold it if you look at
tutorial 22 you'll just see all the
different ways that you can add counter
folds to the creases on the pop-up
there we go
so you have things some on this other
side as well
so generated quite a few more planes
that can be extended so now I'll just
stick this down to the page this is a
basic acute angle v-fold that's the
heart of it all and as the page closes
that's going to fold forward so you want
this to be up near the top of your page
and as with all these things to make
sure that the angles match we just put
the glue on one side first stick it down
with this central crease flush with the
central crease on the base card you can
see what angle you think would see you
sit best this looks pretty good to me
then you fold it down shut put glue on
the other tab smear it always right up
to the creases glue up to the crease is
the important aspect of this the actual
outer edges don't really matter so much
and then we shut the base which finds
its natural sticking position that's
your starting point now you can take
just these little pieces little arms and
you can stick them out just hang out at
any angle really so you just put them
say like this
like that and you need to check it every
so often and as you add them just to
make sure they're not going to be
clashing as the place closes so we shut
this and you yeah so far so good
there we go coming out like this you can
add arms on to arms I've actually cut
all these straight they could be curved
but you could come out say like this so
you're starting to create quite a
complicated interesting sort of almost
of web but it's just an array of arms
sticking out that you can then add the
hearts to I'll just check again make
sure that it's all okay and on and on I
think you get the idea without me
necessarily needing to to build more of
these I got some quite big hearts here
but not really enough I just put the odd
one on so you can get the basic
impression so put the glue on the arms
rather than on the hearts when you're
gluing you always put the glue on the
smallest surface rather than the larger
working so I think that's probably
enough so you get the idea of how it
works
and you can just build it up and up and
up as complicated as you like just keep
checking and it's gonna work like this
and that they aren't gonna clash with
each other that the arms aren't going to
tangle up and and snag you can actually
use this technique on all sorts of other
basic mechanisms so there's one here
this one is based on a twisting
mechanism which is tutorial 17 this bit
hasn't quite work the cards too bendy it
should have gone gone like that but what
I'm really interested in here is all the
different arms with a flower stuck onto
the end of it so this is an example of
the
mechanism when you open that up it's got
six planes it's got two on the top here
then it's got two underneath here and
here and so any of those can have arms
sticking out with flowers or hearts
stuck on the end you can also make
counter poles of these if you have a
extra cut there you can bend this down
bend it back push that through and so
again there you are you've created
another two planes so you can do that
all over it and end up creating
something like this other mechanisms
that you can use of the zigzag fold so
this is tutorial 20 is a zigzag fold
I've made a couple of cuts as it stood
originally it would have been like this
and then I've added extra cuts increases
so it's generating more planes and you
can take these little arms and you can
stick them on shutting up shutting out
coming up at odd angles again every time
you add stuff shut it down I've got a
couple sticking out here those could be
trimmed off but you just keep adding
arms to it building up a complicated
array of arms that you can then stick
your hearts or flowers or stars or
whatever you feel like onto gliding
around a bit I'm afraid no and then
again you can add to those so you make a
more complicated structure with everyone
going back like this
I have another one coming coming down
off that one there and of course they
don't have to actually be stuck on the
end so you can know maybe put one here
give it a t-shirt so all of these can
have other hearts stuck onto them again
just close it make sure it's all working
I've goofed here it's actually sticking
out of the edge but that's the thing
with popper you have to make dummies and
experiment and just see that everything
is actually fitting you're fitting in
within the base when you close it but
you understand the basic technique that
I've used here there's another type of
mechanism this one is based on a
spreading Roberts a Buddhist book Alice
in Wonderland so this is based on the
art lifting small 3d shapes that then
have they're actually rectangles stuck
onto them but they could just as easily
be hearts I'll just show you the the one
in Sabonis book this is Robert's a
Buddha Alice in Wonderland and the
spread at the very end is the arch
raising these small 3d shapes which then
have the playing cards stuck all over
them creating a really amazing chaotic
effect this what I've done here is a
similar type of thing it's creating a
chaotic effect it could be hearts this
is obviously a rough when you close it
you can see they're all sticking out of
the edge I'd need to make another one
with that in mind bringing everything
down to size so it stays in the base so
there isn't actually a tutorial on how
to make an arch so I'll just show you
quickly how to make an arch shape so you
can build the underlying structure of
this one here's the base sheet you're
gonna build a basically it's a acute
angle v-fold built onto that
so we take half a sheet fold it in half
this is all in tutorial - how to make an
acute angle refold fold it well fold
this up this is a crease side so you're
folding it up at a bit of an angle
please see it well and then you cut this
down to make a couple of gluing tabs so
this will be gluing up at the back of
the page like this but you want it to be
an arch so if you just cut an arch way
away and then stick it on randomly you
might well get it a sort of twisting
shape and not very stable shape so you
need to first of all you work out what
angle you want the basic pop-up to be
but what the why do you go the more
it'll lie down and the narrower you come
on the base the more it will stand up so
the same will go something like this now
you need to mark the angle on one side
where it sticks down so take a pencil
here I marked this angle and then the
really important thing is you also mark
the end of that edge so here's the line
here's the end of it that's the really
crucial thing now you can cut the arch
out so we'll just cut a piece out like
this
and I'm going to before I stick it down
I'm going to make another counter fold
just in the top so that's to give it a
bit more interest I think so buddha did
that in his Alice in Wonderland example
no here we are this is going to stick
down to the base and so the important
thing is you stick to decrease against
the line and you put the outside edge up
against that mark so you know it's
exactly where it was when you first test
so put the glue on one side to the line
into that final mark and then you can
close the whole thing down put glue on
the other tab and close the base so
here's your arch shape which you can now
build the other pieces onto again as you
close it you can see this is a dummy
those pieces sticking out doesn't matter
we might as well just trim those down
just so they all fit within the base
please so now we shut it and that's okay
now we'll add a couple of small pieces
onto it so the easiest way we're just
taking the absolutely easiest way to do
this is to just fold a tab onto one end
put glue on that
fold it into a loop so you got a loop
like that and then squash that flat fold
it in half again there we are and fold
it back on itself now when you open this
up you've got a square shape and so you
can stick this into that gully where the
arch joins the page and before I do that
again I'll add a couple of small counter
folds I'll make a cut there bend it down
bend it back push it through so now
that's rather than just generating an
extra two planes we've generated an
extra four planes that you can stick
extra pieces on put glue on the whole
lot
make sure this crease goes tight into
that gully so there it is and then we'll
shut the base and press it well so make
sure that's working if we do another
similar thing on the other side I'll
show you a different way of making it
this time just come up with an angle in
this case we don't want such a big piece
I'm not going to make it a complete loop
I'll just do something like this fold it
in half fold an angled crease on to it
so it's maybe like that pair of tabs
this is going to be glued on like this
so it's sloping down towards the middle
or you can actually have it the other
way so it's actually sloping away from
the middle I think in this case I quite
like it sloping towards the middle as
it's not a loop like this one so you've
got a crease to put into the gully you
have to measure it so you just put it in
like that so the central crease on this
base is tight into that gully and you
just mark where one of the creases lies
on the base just mark the ends of it so
you make sure you know exactly where the
piece is going to go and now you flip it
over so I put the crease into that gully
now you're going to flip it over and
stick it like that to the line so I'll
put some glue you just stick one side at
a time this time I put it on that mark
move tightly down close it glue on the
other tab smear the glue to the edge and
then close the base that finds its
natural sticking place on the earth
so there it is and now both of these
this is created a gully here and a gully
here you could build more of these maybe
smaller or the same size into these the
same here you could build more into this
and this if we look at this one look at
it end on you can see there's a square
one and there's a angled counter folder
and the same on this it's got actually
got three layers built into it you know
one two three and then you just start
sticking the pieces on and sticking them
onto themselves and just build this up
bit by bit oh there's one other way I'll
show you to stick onto here take a small
piece like this fold it in half you can
make a short cut and a long cut you can
fold it back on itself so I've cut in
from the creased edge I'm folding it
back like that so the piece looks like
that fold it back on itself again and
then when you pop that through so we pop
that through this is giving you the
shape like this and now this one this is
a this is an absolutely standard counter
fold you can put the glue all the way
around on both sides smear it well
and put this crease tight into that
Gunny
so that's giving you another two planes
to play with shut it down make sure it
all works so then you can just start
building up you take the hearts like
this and you can just stick them on
stick and that's the shower of Hearts
Valentine's card
[Music]
[Applause]