this tutorial is about open top shapes
there are a number of configurations so
this is the most the most basic it's
based on a parallel fold stuck down here
and here this sister fold at the T chain
it's really just the strip of card with
a tab on one end gluing it into a loop
and then stuck down next example in this
case it's the same thing it's a strip of
card with a tab at one end gluing it
into a loop but in this case the tabs
that attach it to the page run the hole
of each side and then there's a crease
above each corner and then you need
another crease two creases above the
base fold so that's that one this is a
similar idea this is a square but in
this case this is based on a v-fold
so it's a v-fold lifting a parallelogram
whereas this one we just looked at
although it's square
this one is based on parallel folds not
refunds this one this again this is
based on v folds but there's one crease
where the v sticks to the page and
another at the other end is still just a
loop of card with one tab holding it
together then we get more interesting in
this case we start getting tapered shape
so for these you will need a compass to
draw the draw the basic pattern
the net so you can make this type the
like a volcano shape you can also make
this type it's like a funnel shape and
this lends itself to being turned into
flowers so here we have an example of a
flower design so we've got two layers of
petals and then we've got a pyramid in
the middle that the pyramid design will
explain in tutorial 21 all that the
planes there are actually six planes
that are lifted so you can add pieces to
any of those there's also gullies
created where where it's glued to the
page this is glued down parallel folds
so that there's two sticking places
parallel to the spine and so where they
glue down you create a gully that you
can build into so here's another example
this is a basic flower with a pyramid
type mechanism in the middle and then
this is a counter folded piece load into
the gully
so as you open rather than just being a
straight piece like this one we've got a
piece that lifts up three dimensionally
so we just make a really basic open top
shapes just a loop glued together so
take a base sheet use your base sheets
so just cut yourself a strip of card
right long
folder gluing tab onto one end fold it
well now you bring the other end round
and you can just glue that on glue it
shut you might want it underneath
doesn't really matter anyway glue on
that so we glue that into a loop and
then you crush it flat because you will
need a that you need it to be like this
so this will open up like this folder a
gluing you know file tabs on to the
bottom of it so all the way along one
sides you just make a big long crease
fold it back on itself and now you you
just want a tab left in the middle of
each side so you can just cut along that
crease
and just leave a section in the middle
just for a little gluing tab
so here it is this is the loop with two
tabs on it make sure they work nicely
take your base see how why do you want
it watch what sort of shakes you want
you just want a long oval shape or do
you want it nearly round to see how far
away from the base you wonder if we go
fairly round that's the point of this
mark have one side lies from the spine
put glue on on just one tab and then
glue the the crease on that to your line
parallel to the central gully and then
fold the other tab down flat put glue on
that one fold the base shut this again
it will take quite a lot of stress so
make sure you give it a chance for the
glue to go off and there it is you'll
find wear as long as it's quite the
walls are quite short it's fine but the
higher you go the more they will tend to
to lean in the bend of the card starts
influencing the shape I'll now make a
flower type design so that is a tapered
shape so for that yeah you will need
your compass so start with a base sheet
folded in half crease really well fold
it back on itself crease it again again
now take a piece of card and let's go
for a yellow one and put your compass on
one one side and you need to draw as big
an arc as you can the way this works
that the flat of the arc the more the
petals will stand up
the tighter the ark the more they will
lie down if you take a if you take a
circle and just break it into six
sections equal sections that will be
flat like this thing we just made that
in effect was a completely flattened out
art it was strength and so now we're
going as wide as we can
so with this compass this is the widest
it'll open so do a big arc and then
decide how tall you want the petals to
be so I just move it in randomly really
and draw another another RMS and then
mark the center point where the point of
the compass is that's quite important so
there is and now change the diameter
change the gap between the pencil point
and the point you don't want it to be
the same as well as the radius of this
this arc is so I'm going for what's it
son four four centimeters roughly and
just measure off start with one point
and just measure off six sections it's
really important that you do six so
there's one two three four five
six okay now you need your scoring
implement I'm using a biro and you just
score lines from the center point where
your compass point was put it on the
mark you made with the compass and just
score across between the two the two
parallel arcs
okay and now you will need tabs on the
inside that will stick it to the page so
score a line between two and then this
is the important thing you this one is
going to stick to the page then you
leave two blank and then you score
another line where there's going to be
another tab and finally don't forget the
final tab the tab that's going to pull
the whole thing into a loop that needs
to be marked on one end I'm going to do
it on this end where I can see the the
guidelines this is the time if you want
your petals to be shape this is your
opportunity whether you want them
pointed rounded you know something more
interesting is this is the moment to do
it so yet we'll just go for something
fairly basic here now cut it out
so make sure you have this these two
tabs on the inside that are going to
glue it to the page
okay here it is so freeze all the score
lines between the petals fold them all
one way and then back on themselves
don't forget to fold order all the tabs
as well the three tabs so now you glue
it into a loop but in this case make
sure you keep the guidelines on the
underneath so turn it around like that
so you've got a clean surface showing
and then you glue that and we're going
to glue it behind then we are
so that's your basic flower shape and
then you need to line it up on their
face taps again you can have them going
inside or outside if you're going to
make it like this one then the the tabs
are all on the inside and they're all
all hidden underneath it if you're not
going to build anymore
you might be better off having the tabs
on the outside so so they're just hidden
underneath the lean of the petals and
then make sure these these creases are
above the spine fold and then you can
glue glue down one side so get it as
round as you can get it
make sure these these two creases are
above the the central gully stick it
down now fold the whole thing into its
closed position
put glue on the other tab with because
it's going to be on the outside you want
that tab folded back so it's a glue
press it firmly make sure it's glued
really soundly and then open it up there
it is if you want the petals to lie down
more you need to make the initial arcs
more curved and less flat if you want it
to stand up more make the initial arc
flatter this is one of mine this is from
cutter make pop-up cards published by
Dover which is now part of twin each
side of the boat is a slight arc sort of
banana Shh piece and it's glued down on
each sides the these ripples on each
side those are the tabs that actually
glue it to the page and the figure with
the oils this is this is made with a
series of default
the next one is worms wiggle by David
Pellom and here we have the lion's mouth
this is just an open-topped one of the
first ones I showed you
based on a v-fold it's stuck down with
two converging creases converging on the
spine so as it closes the whole face
actually lifts lifts up lifts away from
the page where's the parallel fold it
stays down so that's the that's worms
wiggle by David Pellom okay and the next
one pop up boardgames by Matt Johnston
here is the outer ring that is a basic
open top shape made out of a straight
strip of card that's like the very first
one I showed you this tower again it's
actually an open top shape with a cone
stuck in the top but it's not a box if
it had been a box it would have had a
lid inside it should have pushed out the
edges and made the whole thing a bit
more round but because it's just an open
top shape you can see it's just tending
to to lean in a bit and the last one
this is blue two by David Carter a whole
series of conical volcano shapes and all
operated by the automatic strip the the
automatic pull strip is tutorial 16 and
so so these are really if you are making
a flower but instead of putting the tabs
on the inside so you get a cone you put
the tabs on the outside and that gives
that gives you the volcano shape all
this and more is explained in great
detail in pop-up design and paper
mechanics
you