[Music]
after the pacano books which the last
one was in 1949 there was quite a gap in
much Papa action and the next one that
I've got to show you is from 1950 this
is called Beauty and the Beast by Roland
PIM beautiful little book very very
simple paper engineering it's all based
on parallel faults which are tutorial
six if we just look at it end on you can
see it has these six breads
six scenes each of which is made of four
sheets with a fold in the middle so
we've got this is the front one then one
a bit further back third one and the
final one and if we then look at it I'll
just tie it open and then we can go
around and look at it simply what I
really like about this is the way
incredible perspective is created if we
look at it like this I'll just go
through all six of them and you'll see
how the sheets are cut away in very
clever ways to give a really
extraordinary sense of depth each scene
has a different sort of tone to it I
just think it's a really beautiful piece
of work the next two books are from 1960
I don't know who the paper engineer was
these are 1960 they're all made with
floating planes which are tutorial 12
and parallelograms tutorial 5 I just
think the illustration in these is
beautiful they've got two spreads each
here it is and if we look at it end on
you can see the floating plane mechanism
with the parallel fold in the middle and
then the parallelogram is coming out
from
and they have these crazy little pull
tabs very crude mechanisms that the the
effects are very pleasing that's the
first one in this book and then the
other spread at the back in this case
well the top here and the Seas pop up
out of the jars and the other one in
this series that I've got is Aladdin and
his magic lamp
from 1960 it's the same it's floating
planes and parallelograms beautiful
artwork here's the tab and it brings
this monster interview so the next step
forward was Wojtek cabassa working in in
czechoslovakia he did two types of books
he did these panis Copic models and he
also did these children's stories so
I'll just run through these three panis
Copic models first this one is
Christopher Columbus 1960 so here it is
and this spread is an absolute classic
Christopher Columbus's ship and if we
look at the mechanisms
these are zigzag folds which are
tutorial 20 here's a zigzag fold is
another zigzag fold most tutorial 20 and
again if we look at this this is a
zigzag fold with added parallelograms
past tutorial six all fitted together
with slots
that's tutorial 11 lovely piece of
design this and the second one I'd like
to show you is 1961 this is called the
castle tournament
Wojtek capacitor again and here it is
amazing pop-up castle basically the main
mechanism is a v-fold so this this is a
v-fold which is powering the rest of it
a lot of it I like the illustration
showing actually the inside of the
castle even though it's nothing
full-color like the front it's still
just adds something to the whole design
if we look at it end on you can see this
is a second be fault here and this is a
parallelogram joining the two come round
and look at it all and these bits these
are asymmetric v-folds that are holding
the these two pieces this piece here and
this piece here these are asymmetric
meatballs tutorial for these these are
just very straightforward little
parallelograms coming off these planes
here the parallelograms a tutorial five
so we've got these little moving
mechanisms here very simple very basic
and we've got the same on the other side
and then this this final bit that's a
symmetric parallel fold tutorial six and
the last one this is Marco Polo from
1962 and we open this one up quite an
extraordinary pop-up this really really
lovely piece of pop-up design these at
the back
these are zigzag folds they're a
modification from what I explained in
the tutorial this tutorial 20 this is a
basic V fold here tutorial 2 it's cut in
the form of an arch which is hovered in
tutorials 34 this is extra creases
that's tutorial 7 there's a parallel
fold this piece jutting forward
that's tutorial 6 and there's also
counter folds like this piece right in
the back here is counter fold
that's tutorial 22 all held together
with slots less tutorial 11 highly
complicated bit of pop-up design but
really amazing spreads now we just have
a look at capacitors fairy stories there
are literally dozens of these this is
sleeping beauty from 1961 all the
mechanisms in all these books are
counter fold tutorial 22 they usually
have some interesting little
moving parts are very very simple so
here we have the the Prince turns into
the witch and if we open it up that same
thing we've got these windows or empty
and by pulling that strip we get these
three Grace's or whatever they are it's
all counter fold so when the page is
flat everything else goes flat they're
all cut out of one piece of card if you
look at it end on you'll see that the
whole thing is actually it's a
concertina it's just one long strip of
cards with all these very clever counter
folds cut out of them giving you
ordinary parallelograms angled folds and
we just run through this it's the castle
this has got another one you can pull
see what goes on so I like the way this
this stained-glass window turns into an
owl we have this which here turns into a
stained-glass window very simple bit of
pull strip and here we have another one
I don't think there's anything to move
on that and then this one I don't think
there's anything to move on that either
this there up there are these these
heads that rock well there's no pull
strip to do it you just have to do it
with your finger they're all nodding off
to sleep the very last spread is this
one and you can actually pull the tab
and the Prince comes through the arch to
give her a case this is sleeping beauty
from 1961 these very early capacitors
had eight spreads later on they reduced
them down to six so I'll just show you a
few others this is French version the
little train
this is 1973 all made with counter folds
the same as a previous book tutorial 22
every spread in this one has some really
simple movement in it so in this one the
you know the Train does some interesting
moves now this is a really good one as
you pull these little mice we get some
fun
plastic action there drumming again the
actual mechanism is really really simple
and so you actually have to hold it
right or it starts going wrong but yeah
I just think that's delightful the way
he drums and the next spread this one
yeah there's nothing to actually move
these are just dangly bits and the next
one this is a windmill again it's you
know there's no pull strip or anything
it's just you can make it turn if you
want and the last one so this is this
from 1979 and then this is still
capacitor still the same technique all
made with counter folds this is
moon-rocket this is 1986 and here's the
first one you press that and it launches
the rocket number two this this is
tutorial 27 hubs and pivots you've got a
whole series of things changing here
you've got this reading on the computer
changing you've got this dial changing
and you've also got places around the
world you've got Paris Moscow Beijing
Cologne and Italy New York the other
action on this spread is this when you
pull his head up and down you get the
arms on the robot moving pretty Kroenke
really but this is what you pull then it
moves the view out the porthole window
all these movements they're quite fun
about they're pretty crude paper
mechanics this is made with slots
that's tutorial 11 all the rest is
counter folds tutorial 22
it's the next spread you want to make
the rocket go you just lift it up
there's nothing nothing clever about
this it's just a simple up-and-down and
then we've got this red
this is the last spread just pull these
up and and again that's all there is to
it so they're just very simple toys
really these are slots holding this
that's tutorial 11 all the rest is
counter folds tutorial 22 if you make
the book flat the whole thing goes flat
it's all made out of one great big
concertina with a lot of these counter
folds cut into it this was capacitor
working in Czechoslovakia and he
inspired Waldo hunt in California to
start the company called graphics
international in 1965 and this is JC
Chitty Bang Bang from 1968 and here is a
really fantastic spread beautiful car
this is all made basically with the Box
mechanism this is tutorial 14 and if you
look at it end on you can see there's a
pillar underneath that pushes the whole
thing open it then has parallel folds
creating this you know in the back
parallel folds a tutorial six and then
these are actually V Falls tutorial two
built into the gullies created by the
car and so I just think that's rather
beautiful spread really the paper
engineer on all these the next three
books I'm showing you they're all by
Paul Taylor and the second spread from
this I want to show you this is
basically v-folds tutorial 2 and this is
the arch tutorial 34 this the way the
lid of this box is made that's the
45-degree fold which is tutorial 23
there's actually a pillar underneath
which is parallel with one of these
sides that pushes the top of the box up
to make it absolutely square
and this of course is just a
parallelogram joining these two and the
next book this is also designed by Paul
Taylor this is dr. Doolittle from 1969
and the first read I'd like to show you
is this one at the back we have an M
fold
that's tutorial 19 raising parallelogram
here
that's tutorial 5 the fish this is a
v-fold tutorial too and the back of the
fish this is a parallel fold raised by
the V fold the parallel fold is tutorial
6 and both of them this is added creases
and also down in here this is added
creases so both of those tutorial 7 and
so it it's a bit Square and clunky but I
think I think it's a really cool feature
actually very nice nice bit of design
and the last one in this book is this
one the main piece of this one is
obviously this pink snail this is a
curved shape tutorial 13 behind it we've
got this is an M fold this is slightly
adapted I turn it round you can see but
basically it's an M fold which is
tutorial 19 and the way these pieces
have been built onto this snail this is
the 45-degree fold which is tutorial 23
as it closes you can see in here these
are 45 degree angles these are coming up
at right angles to the main body of the
snail and then the last of these
graphics international books I've got
one of my favorites this is from 1969
20,000 Leagues Under the Sea also
designed by Paul Taylor and the first
spread is this fantastic boat
based on the box mechanism which is
tutorial 14 if we look at it end on you
can see there's a pillar in the middle
which is pushing up the deck and then
these are coming up through slots so
that's tutorial 11 and the wave this
sail is added on these are two 45-degree
folds that's tutorial 23 I just think
this is a lovely bit of design the
unusual thing about this a lot of boats
they just go straight down the middle
they follow the spine that's the easy
way to make them and this has been made
going across the spine which is really
unusual so it is actually a box
underneath here is actually a flat plane
so there's the three planes one here one
on the spine one at the back that's
giving you the box and then the way the
sides have been added on that enables
you to have the pointy brow at the front
and the next spread is this one I think
it's very effective but it's very simple
it's it's all V faults V folds here
pointing this way they fold down this
way these V folds fold down this way
they're all in that tutorial too and the
Joker is this one this is an asymmetric
V fold
that's tutorial for this is unusual this
graphics international used it quite up
as a piece of wire that holds this piece
up so it gives you the effect of
something just floating in space and the
last spread is this one this is here we
have a zigzag fold
that's tutorial 20 this one is a pointed
v fault
that's tutorial 3 the spirals a tutorial
10 and the other thing here is this pull
tab mechanism giving you the Axman
hacking at the tentacles that is
tutorial 27 hubs and pivots that's all
the books I'm going to show you in this
tutorial but if you're interested in
pop-up history this book the art of
pop-up the magical world of
three-dimensional books this is the
business
and if we go here you can see it has got
a really fantastic timeline you can pull
it out and you can see the way pop-ups
that develop from the very beginning and
concertina it all back in if you're
interested in pop-up history or other
paper engineers this is the book you
also have all sorts of stuff about other
paper engineers a lot of modern stuff as
well as history covers all sorts a lot
of really fantastic books in it really
excellent information it's just a lovely
book I can't recommend it highly enough
[Music]
you