[Music]
this tutorial is about this type of card
I call a stage set as you pull the tabs
on each side it opens up and you get a
3d Vista so this was one made it's a
birthday card then I've got one here
which was made as a Christmas card pull
the tabs bit more simple inside and then
I've got one I made myself just checking
how it all works is you pull the tabs
and it opens up its two main pieces one
is the frame and then the other side is
really one long strip this is the back
of the scene the two sides and then the
two bits that you pull the measuring is
slightly complicated because the pieces
that you pull because they come in like
this they need to be each of those pulls
pieces has to be half the size of the
whole frontage and the two wall bits
these bits because they fill in the gap
they need to be half the size of the gap
so I've made all the pieces in advance
with all the measurements marked up on
it so you can see what they are this is
the main frontage this is half a piece
of a4 card the 21 centimetres across and
the height is half a sheet of a4 the
important thing is this window so that's
ten centimetres by eight centimetres
this is the piece that goes at the back
of the room that you're looking into so
that's 10 by 10 as you can see it's a
little bit it's the same width as the
window but it's a little bit higher than
the whole
window and then these are the two side
pieces that are going to glue on so if
we look at how this whole long piece the
two sides the back and the two bits that
you pull you'll see that the sides have
these slots cut in them and then the
images are on bars that go through the
slots here's a couple of bars that I've
cut out these are the sides that will
stick on to the the back of the room so
this will be the back of the room these
are going to stick on like this so these
are the measurements the whole piece is
21 across so each of these has to be ten
and a half and then the width of the
window is ten so these have to be half
of that so these are five so when it's
in position it'll be like that and then
it has these slots that the bars go
through the one nearest the front of the
window that'll be one and a half
centimeters high from the bottom and the
one behind it will be two and a half
centimeters high they're both two
centimeters deep and they're one and a
half centimeters in from the edges so
there are two of these pieces they go
one on each side of the back so now I'll
just stick these together I'll keep the
measurements out of you so when you open
the whole cards you won't see all the
measurements I've got that one room so
it's gonna be like that so I'll stick
these together let's put some glue on
this tab here I've already pre scored it
and folded it and creased it so it's all
going to move nicely but when you're
actually making your own don't forget to
really crimp all the creases so they
they move really well so that's gonna go
like that right so stuck one side on and
now I'm going to stick the other side on
to the other side to make this really
long strip so to put there
the tabs go behind the back of the room
as I call it and put the glue on here
smooth it when you're gluing always
smear the glue right up to the crease so
there it is
well that round to make it go smoothly
so that's how the main long piece looks
so when it closes down it'll close like
this so now we have to add it to the
frame for that we have these two sleeves
so we've got these two sleeves they're
the pieces that go at the back you can
see I haven't got them colored but
there's a sleeve here and a sleeve here
they're the ones that hold these sliding
pieces in place and make them move the
way you want them to move so I've got
two of those they're just a fraction
longer than the whole height of the
sliding piece so they are ten point five
centimeters and they're going to glue on
the back of this so I've got the
measurements here but I'll keep the
measurements on the back I'm going to
stick these on this they go right up
flush against the window I put glue on
the two tabs 1 2and these go like this
ideally I would have measured it so that
they're exactly equidistant above and
below the window frame so there's one is
the other one and just make sure that's
creased well as well but glue on those
two
then be careful with this gluing you
really don't want it losing too much and
gluing the sleeve closed that's it so
there's the two sleeves flush up against
the edges of the the window now we take
this piece and thread it all through so
it's going to go like this so put one
side through there and the other side
through there so now you can see as it
closes these will come in looks as
though my measuring is ever so slightly
off because there's a this still a bit
of a gap and then when you pull it it
opens up now we put these bars in place
so the length of the bars a ten point
two which is just slightly longer than
the width of the window and the height
of the bars is one point seven which is
just slightly less than the height of
the slots and each bar has these two
tabs on each end these you just fold
them down you don't crease them and
score them you just fold them down so
they'll feed through their slot so I'll
just fold these down like this and feed
them through the slot oh yeah
once it's through the slot you can
straighten out the tabs again and on the
other side fiddly
right there we go there's the fat bar
fitted in I've made a slight mistake
there I put it in with the numbers
showing but not to worry then here's the
other one right so now you can see the
two bars are in place like that now we
can add the images and stick them onto
them as it closes if you look that way
you'll see that the slots get closer and
closer together and so the closer the
bar is to the front of the stage the
smaller the image has to be this is the
front image it has to be not more than 3
centimeters wide
so I'll just glue that into place of
glue it with the blank side showing
because that's slightly more aesthetic
want the glue on the back so the image
is just standing there rather than
behind the bar you can actually glue it
to any point on the bar and as it all
closes the bars will slide around at the
back so they find their own place
so if you look at it end on you'll see
how the two slots as it closes they'll
come closer and closer together and
that's why it can't be more than three
centimeters wide known as you pull it
open there it is now I'll put on the
second image this is going on the back
bar this is not more than seven
centimeters wide let's now put some glue
on that one and that can go down there
just close it up and press it all down
so that's the whole thing now there's
one other thing you might feel the
slides on the side they can actually go
in too far which makes it a bit a bit
tricky so you can just put a bit of card
down each side that will just act as a
governor and just stop it pushing in too
far so I'll just cut a quick piece of
this to do that with and this should be
half of this should be long enough I
think so these need to be ever so
slightly longer than the width of these
sliding pieces so it goes on like that
cut it off there so you get the sliding
piece into its fully closed position and
then put some glue on the on the actual
sliding piece I'll position the slides
at the most in that you want it to be so
there it is the edge of the slide is
flush with the edge of the frame and
then we'll stick this piece across it up
against the sleeve so it won't slide in
any further when it's pushed and I'll
just tidy that there so that's that side
so that can and I'll do the same on the
other side but the slide so it's flush
with the edge of the frame but a little
bit of glue on here and then stick the
governing piece again I haven't cut it
to size beforehand
get the sliding piece in position and
stick this governing piece across just
stop it going in any further so there we
are now you can see it's like this
maybe these extra pieces are looking a
little bit clunky so you could actually
just trim them right down they only need
to be about half a centimeter longer
than the actual sliding piece just
enough to come up against the sleeve and
stop it going in too fast so I'll cut
both of those back a bit oh yeah so
that's it the opening stage set if it
was kept flat for longer with a book on
top of it or something all the creases
would reinforce and it would tend to
hold itself shut the way this one does
so that's it quite a fun card the stage
set type to
[Music]