[Music]
I'm going to show you how to make an
angel Christmas cards and before I show
you how to make this one I'll just show
you a couple of books with how other
people have dealt with the subject so
number one we've got angels by Chuck
Fischer and actually he has a lot of
angels in them but not I mean these they
do have some 3d wings but they're fairly
all the way through there's angels but
they're quite small and not super super
3d that's similar to the first bread
anyway quite quite an interesting
subject and that's Chuck Fischer's
angels the other two books are both by
Roberts óbuda so there's the twelve days
of Christmas and here we've got a whole
array of angels based on the twisting
mechanism which is tutorial seventeen
and that's that one the other one also
by Roberts óbuda is this one the
Christmas alphabet and this a is for
angel it's quite a curious design he's
done there it is based on a v-fold and
then as a floating plane and a slot
so now I'll show you how to make this
one and just before we go into it I'll
show you how the wings can be decorated
this is another card I made before this
is a bird card you can see the bird but
ignore the bird it's just actually
looking at the way the wings are done
and the way the wings are decorated then
it's with three different tones of
yellow card and cut into these shapes
and I just think that works really
nicely this angel is actually based on
this if you look at it underneath from
end on you'll see that it is a floating
plane the floating plane is tutorial
twelve and then these are the head the
head is a pointed v-fold it's just
slightly angled to make it a point and
though it's being cut off and then the
trumpet is held in place by slots on the
hand and a slot on the head
that holds the trumpet search that's out
these are the pieces you start with the
base sheet of course thoroughly fold it
and then to make the floating plane
here's a piece it's got three parallel
creases cut it into three so the three
more or less even chunks then you take
the biggest one of these and this is
gonna stick over the spine like this and
you want this very steep the steeper it
is the more rigid the shape it's all
underneath it doesn't really matter
which way the tabs go but I'm going to
have them sticking out so I can keep the
central Ridge really closely into the
spine so I'll put a bit of glue on that
side there I'll stick that down it's
only you know maybe even only half a
centimeter from the spine and some more
glue on the other tab smear it around
[Music]
close the base that can find where it
wants to glue down so that's the
beginning of it that's a parallel fault
the other two pieces are used to make
parallelograms on each side so put glue
on that and this time you stick the the
crease
absolutely flush with there the ridge on
the top of that so there's that one and
now you fold it up into its closed
position put the glue on the other tab
and now close it down so it goes into
its closed position close it so it finds
where it wants to stick down put the
other one on the other side
absolutely flush with the Ridge on the
top and put glue on the other tab well
smear it around and then close it down
so this is the basic floating plane you
look at it that way on you can see
there's a parallel fold in the middle
and then a parallelogram on each side
creating these two planes above the page
they're both parallel with the page this
is the main body of the Angel needs a
crease down the middle that crease is
going to go into the gully here I've
made it symmetrical but it doesn't need
to be you might choose to make the two
wings in different positions it really
doesn't matter they're just going to
stick onto these two planes here and
it's up to you when you're designing
just play around with it we can stick
this all at the same time we've got the
glue on both surfaces and the important
thing is to make sure that this crease
goes right into that flush into that
gully there and we'll close this just to
make sure it's all
Safety's sound so that's the main body
of it so this is the heads you can cut
it out in profile you see the shape that
you want the profile of the head to be
you add a tab on each side and then
there's a little slot here which can
hold the trumpet so the trumpet can go
in and be stuck in sides here it is if
you look at it this way you can see the
trumpet goes through that's not and then
there's actually slots in the hands as
well so that holds the trumpet so it
juts directly out from the page so we
stick this on it's up to you really you
know how high or low you put it I put it
off about half way up there it's it's up
to you this design so again I'll put
glue on one side this can go as flat or
as pointy as you like I'll stick it down
there and then I'll put glue on the
other side and close it
close it down so there's the head in
place now the arms so you can see the
arms that actually if you look at it
this way you'll see there's one fold
here and one fault here these two folds
are parallel and then I've cut the shape
of the arms to give an elbow and make
the arms go down and come up again to
holder jumping again it's been being
folded in half and all cut symmetrically
so when you open it up it gives you this
shape and so these tabs are gonna go in
underneath they're gonna stick down
something like this so this is actually
parallel fold you want to be thinking
about where the trumpet coming straight
out is going to be so you need the two
slots sort of in line with each other
and again I'm just going to stick down
one side roughly where the shoulder
would be that's about right it should be
glued parallel with this crease on that
main body and then we put glue on the
other side and close
this is the trumpet it's just got one
little crease at the end so there's just
a very small tab there
that's what's gonna hold the piece in
place this is going to go like this it
goes through the slot in my hands and
through the stuffing line it and that's
going to glue in there like that so I'll
just put a little bit of glue on there
spider York would this just getting it
down inside the head there I'll actually
use something like a pen to press it up
against the against the head to make
sure it sure I make sure it sticks well
okay I think that's got it now I'll just
close it down to encourage it to stick
soundly so this is the angel Christmas
card the angel blowing a trumpet there
we are
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]