[Music]
this tutorial is about quite an unusual
pull strip where you pull the tab a flap
appears and flips over the key to it all
is a little strip underneath here which
has 5 sections there the key to the
mechanism so I've got all the pieces
prepared here this is the base it's got
a crease here so when you look at this
one the bottom end folds over so that's
the crease there I've also put a crease
down each side so you've got tabs so
that there's tabs here which will fold
it shut so I'll just cut those off so
you can see how it's actually made this
section is 10 centimeters and this is 15
centimeters
I'll just cut these off
this is your base sheet and this is
going to fold over like this here's the
flap five centimeters by five
centimeters this is the little strip the
key to it all that flips it over
I'll just score it so it'll all move
really smoothly
so here it is and we just crease all
those really well so they move really
nicely when it's all assembled take the
strip and the very end strip is going to
stick onto the full strip the second bit
is going to stick onto the flat it's
going to be like that
so I'll just glue that piece on one
section in from the end so that's going
to be like that
and then with all these things they'll
pull strip is double sickness so I've
already scored it
I've already folded it now to make it
extra strong we'll glue it back to back
we'll just fold these so we glue them at
the very ends but we'll just fold in
beforehand and this is going to glue in
the pull strips going to go here this is
going to glue onto the pull strip and
this is going to glue in here so I just
check the distance in and it's pulled
out like this this end this is going to
be like this this is going to be down
here when it's glued in place it's going
to be like this but with the flap
underneath so that's going to be
underneath there we now put glue on this
bottom end
so it's going to be like that glued into
place so when it flips over it can flip
like that and just make sure when it's
in it's going to be like that this is
going to stick on there
just make sure this works as you pull it
comes up and flips over slightly off my
sticking so that's all working all right
my measuring is slightly off so I'm
going to trim that off in a minute but
first I'm gonna stick these two ends
down and the other thing is you need a
slip like this one that the strip is
going to go through so that it can be
held in place and move nicely so I'll
just mark where that's going to go so
it's about here before I fold it down
I'll just cut that slit now we can feed
that through and glue these bits down
I have made a bit of a mess you can see
I've got glue everywhere my measuring is
slightly off so I'll just snip a little
bit of that blue off so it disappears
there we go and there you got this flip
over flat last thing you can actually
trim this this tail end down so push it
in it's going to extend out like that so
with it pushed in you can just trim it
off so you just have a little bit there
so what you can use this for you can
have a surprise message here or a
surprise image you can say happy
birthday will you marry me you can have
a message here and then a subsequent one
there you can also have a piece written
in there all sorts of things that just
appear and then suddenly even more
appears you could also have some sort of
image on here and when you pull it out
and that comes in that can change that
can be an addition to the basic image
you had to start with there's also all
this bit that's extending you you might
play with that so there you have it the
pull out and flip over flap surprise
[Music]
[Applause]