in this tutorial we're going to look at
the twisting mechanism which is a very
pleasing mechanism it has a very unusual
action as the page opens the mechanism
twists around it's it's made of two V
files pointing at each other when when
the base is flat they lie flat and then
you can build a number of things on top
of it so here is an example as it opens
the figure twists around and opens up in
essence you've got six planes so there's
two on each top and bottom on each of
the V folds and then it's got two on the
parallel folds on top and then the
gullies that you can build into the
gullies that that close as the base
closes you've got one obviously in the
top underneath the parallel fold you've
got two under top and two on the bottom
where the V folds are and then within
the v-folds you've got another two so
you've got four there two there six and
then one there so seven gullies to
building and this one hasn't actually
built into any of the gullies it's just
extending the plains so that these the
head and arm that's coming off one plane
this is coming off one and then these
are coming off two others so it's using
four of their planes
you need a base sheet here's the base
sheet folded in half crease really
thoroughly and then you need another
another piece about this big I've
actually already creased it in the
middle that way folded it really
thoroughly I've added a a crease at each
end for gluing tags and then you want
another crease going down the middle of
it so you fold it lengthwise so make
sure this time make sure those two
central creases line up with each other
so that you know it's all going to work
nicely so there's the there's that
crease fold it back on it so fold it
really thoroughly so you've got you've
got a cross shape now you actually need
two more creases going across like this
so one way is to just fold it across and
bring the creasing lines so you can do
it like that but that's one way of doing
it and fold that back on it so the other
other ways if you find that really
difficult you can use a cassette square
so the causes of the set square of 45
degrees and what you're aiming for here
is 8 angles and they're all going to be
45 degrees so you can just put that down
that central crease mark it with a
pencil or score it with your bar oh so
there's one and then you can do the same
on the other side so that's the that's
the line we want we won't fold it so now
you just fold it along there you can
check it by just making sure that these
these creases line up and they look the
early so that is a bit tricky it is a
bit tricky but so that is you end up
with the with the creases all making a
star shape and now you should be able to
push it in like that so this is the
shape you end up with and these these
two central creases should be flush with
each other
ideally there is a little bit of leeway
but
more flash they are with each other the
better and then sometimes you can just
cut out that final point because there's
a whole lot of cards all come together
there and it makes it a little bit thick
so just to make it work a little more
smoothly you can just cut that it off so
this is the shape you've ended up with
now you only want one tab on each end
and so make a tab on this end up here
and just cut it back a bit further
rather than just cutting along the the
crease there cut it back a bit bit more
otherwise you'll end up with a point
here which might snag on other things so
you just cut that off to the to the
corner take it off there so you've got a
gluing tab off one end there and then
the crucial thing is the other gluing
tab must be diagonally opposite not on
the same side so here's the second
gluing time this is the shape you want
to end up with and now you're going to
put the glue I'll need four central
panels and that's all going to glue down
flat with the central crease lined up at
the at the central crease of the base
and these four glued down and you can
glue the whole thing can glue down flat
so you can put glue on all those four at
the same time so just to make sure we
don't miss the glue up which we fold it
into that position it makes it easier to
get the glue up to the creases and not
beyond
right so open it up flat
central crease with the central crease
on the base and glue it down there is so
glue those down flat and now you close
it and these these two pieces they
should lift up and come together so
there as you can see the two V fonts
coming together as you open and close it
so now you're going to stick another
piece across between these two let's try
a bit of red
we don't want it any wider than this
piece we've already attached so aim for
the same with more or less and then it
mustn't be shorter than the distance
between these two creases if it's
shorter then the whole mechanism can't
open it can be longer the longer it is
the more it'll stand up so we start by
just folding it in the middle so you're
going to a crease across the middle like
that and then this is going to fit in
like that so if we look at this it's
about well we'll just take say a
centimeter off each end so fold it in
half
keeping it symmetrical we can just take
a piece off like that this is going to
glue into in this position and so these
tabs they can either go on top which
case they're visible or you can hide
them underneath so we put them
underneath
okay make sure the edge is flush with
the grease and then that one goes there
you can shut the base and made it all a
bit big so it's just enough that's the
way it goes with dummies so you make the
dummy and then you see the dimensions
and you can see what you grow you need
to change so this is the dummy of the
twisting mechanism so this is Little Red
Riding Hood
paper engineering by Bruce Foster and we
open this up and this is the twisting
mechanism and he's done into the wolf
hiding from behind the tree you can
probably see it this way you can see how
it moves how it twists as it opens has
extended the different planes anyway
that's that one the next one is the
night before Christmas by Roberts óbuda
and under this flap you have a really
amazing example of the twisting
mechanism so who is opens up and he's
got all the six planes or at least five
of them have been extended with these
these cutouts so as the flap opens and
closes so you see it the whole gang of
deer reindeer they all put me a
pirouette around the action very nice
example and then the next one is the
Nutcracker by Nick Dench filled this has
got an unusual variation he's using the
twisting mechanism to raise the
Christmas tree so this is actually a
solid shape being lifted rather than
just a couple of planes so you can see a
nun you can see the see the v-folds
going down again coming together and
holding away in the Christmas tree
spinning around so the last one I want
to show you is my jungle pop-up book and
this has a really interesting variation
so here it is and in this case the
v-folds don't lie flap when the page is
flat they stand up and it's the piece
lifting up on the top
ends up flat rather than being a high
right you know pointing up parallel fold
so it folds down in between those two
V's so yeah a nice example there and
that's it for twisting mechanism it's
all explained in more detail in my book
pop-up design and paper mechanics
you