this u-turns about pyramids so here it
is a basic pyramids you can vary the
proportions and change the type of
pyramid that you're producing so this is
the most simple here's an example of one
that's tolerance deeper this one is
stuck down parallel to the spine whereas
these ones are based on default so these
the creases converge on the spine as it
closes down the corner lift up this time
is stuck down parallel to the spine so
it closes up in a different way also
this has six creases whereas the other
just has creases on the corners of the
pyramid this one has to have creases
above the spine there are other
variations so there's and this is an
asymmetric pyramids quite complicated to
calculate but they're quite quite fun
this is a another variation this is
actually a cone but it's the same
principle as the pyramid again it's
stuck down parallel to the spine just
hasn't got any angle creases making
corners but it's the same basic shape so
this is a stretch pyramid it's a
parallel fold tutorial six with half a
pyramid on each end in this spread the
camel is made with an asymmetric
pyramids and the neck is maybe the
counter folded piece that is covered in
tutorial AIDS and so whole chunks of the
basic pyramid have been Castle
to give the camel there is a very rigid
shape so you can cut pieces away so I'll
just show you how to make make a regular
simple pyramid take a base sheet fold it
in half crease it really thoroughly and
then you can take half a piece of card
you need a compass you need a scoring
tool a ruler and the usual scissors and
glue so take the compass mark where
you're going to put the point draw a
semicircle the bigger the circle that
the flatter thee the pyramid can be you
then adjust the the gap between the
point and the pencil on your compass the
bigger the gap the flatter the pyramid
will be the smaller the gap the more
steep and pointy it will be so it all
depends what type of pyramid you wanting
so make the first mark and measure off a
let's round the art do it again so these
are the four base sides of the pyramid
so there's the four bases now you need
to score between those those marks and
the and the points where the point of
the compass was one I'll just note this
off store onto that
two three four and the last one you'll
also need two straight scored lines
where the tabs that glue it to the page
you're going to be so we just put them
adjacent to each other so there's one
there's the other these other edges will
just need to be cut off straight so
might as well just cut them off with the
ruler so you get a nice straight cut one
and then this last side you're going to
need a gluing tab to to pull the whole
thing into shape so we'll just cut that
ruling tab down you need to be aware of
the angle at the top of the pyramid and
make sure that the angle of the tab is
going to fit within that and then you
can cut down this line and you need to
gluing tabs for lo these these scored
lines
right fold along creases not forgetting
that the crease is where the tabs will
stick the whole thing to the page and
then you glue it shut
make sure those creases are really good
and then glue ease into shape so put
glue on that and glue it shut
so before you glue it to the page make
sure that you're cutting and gluing will
actually fold flat and make your base
sheet he's going to glue underneath so
look and make sure they're not going to
overlap and then this is going to stick
down like this and you don't actually
need to measure where it's going to
stick down just make sure that the
crease between the two tabs is on the
line and make sure that the other grease
is also on that spine line and then you
can glue them both down at the same time
it just makes sure the two tabs are one
on each side make sure that they points
the corners of the pyramid are flush
with that line and then you can you can
close it down press it down and there
you have it in your design you you might
want something hidden underneath some
image or other little v-fold or
something so that as you open the page
that disappears under the pyramid or you
have it this way around so you get a
better optical illusion it just seems to
be flush with the page I'll show you a
few commercial ones so this is great
pop-up buildings of the world and the
first spread is a couple of pyramids the
next one I've got one is blue two and
the pyramid is step-down parallel to the
spine you can see what it's rigid shape
it is that you can cut away an awful lot
of it and it still keeps its shape and
in fact there's two more pyramids inside
it both parallel folds and you can see
this the folds over the spine that these
parallel folds need in this case they're
going inwards rather than outwards and
finally in this this book come flying
machines by it Pennock in this case the
airplane is based on the basic box which
is tutorial 14 but if you look at the
nose cone of the plane that is a pyramid
that's a parallel fold pyramid it's
stuck down to the two walls of the plane
so that is a pyramid being used not as a
pyramid but part of it it's the same
mechanism used as part of a different
design and that's it for pyramids
there's more about them in this mod book
pop-up design and paper mechanics
you