[Music]
this tutorial is about the unfurling
mechanism it's a quite an unusual little
mechanism that I took from this book by
David Pellom called the Raven really
fantastic but really beautiful
illustration and very clever pop-ups so
I'll just run through it so you can see
just how great it is really and then
I'll explain the unfurling mechanism at
the end these are the spreads so this is
the unfolding mechanism this is the one
I'm going to explain in this tutorial
and then this is the end of the book
this is the unfurling mechanism I think
the best way to understand it is to look
at it from behind you'll see that the
whole thing is powered by a v-fold in
here and the v-fold is the type of
v-fold where the angles on the v-fold
are the same as the angles on the page
so when the page is flat the v-fold lies
flat the v-fold is extended up and
there's a piece that pushes up the back
of the fingers easiest to show you on
this one that I've made so I'll put that
there so here it is this is the V fault
this would be the front of the hand this
is the piece that pushes up the fingers
it pushes up at the back here and the
the finger is actually hinged on the top
of this extension to the v-fold so as it
opens and closes you can see how that
works in the book rather than to just
being one flat level here yellow as I've
made there's a whole series of different
heights for the different fingers so if
we look at it sideways on here there's a
whole lot of different heights to all
different shapes but all pushed up by
the the piece that's pushing it has all
these different levels and the piece
that it's pushing against has different
levels so when you look at this it would
be really the yellow piece would have
different levels and also the red piece
would have different levels but I've
just made one to make it clear so you
can understand it so now I'll make one
I've cut out all the pieces in advance
so I'll explain them all they're all
quite simple this is the base sheet
folded in half folded really thoroughly
this is the V fold both these angles are
45 degrees I have increased it yes I'll
just crease that now so that crease
really thoroughly you look at this you
can see where it's positioned on the
page so that piece is going to be the V
it'll be near the top of the page
pointing down it something like this
that's about right so I'll just put the
glue on there and as it's flat when the
pop-up is flat you can glue both sides
at the same time
I'll position it on there make sure the
central crease of the pop-up is
with the central crease of the base
stick it down fold it shut just to make
sure that everything is working smoothly
oh yeah
so now you'll see that this yellow piece
is stuck to one side of the v-fold so
here's the yellow piece I'm going to add
on and you can see that that yellow
piece is glued to one side of the v-fold
so here's the yellow piece that low
yellow piece and it's going to be glued
to this side of the v-fold make sure the
corner is right in the corner otherwise
well it obviously won't won't close
properly so put some glue on this
triangle here bit too much glue there
I'll just give it a moment to dry off
I'll close it make sure it's working and
give that a minute now the second piece
this is a piece here with the slot in it
that the red piece goes through so
that's going to go on here the slot is
going to be just above the level here
you could probably make it all out of
one card but I think it's also quite
good to keep it tough so it's several
thicknesses so I've marked slots it's
going to be parallel with the crease at
the bottom I've just cut it out
okay
that needs to be just above the top
edge and I'll just glue that one on as
well right again I'll just close it make
sure it all works this is obviously a
dummy you can see it sticking out of the
edge but it doesn't matter it's just
explaining the mechanisms so there we
are that's moving like that now the red
piece this is going to be pushing up the
whole thing this is what actually makes
the mechanism moving the way it does so
here's the strip I've made it's got a
crease down the middle I'm going to glue
it in a minute
but first we'll just make a tab at one
end so I'll cut a little piece off there
so that's going to be a tab that's going
to glue it onto the page now if we look
at this you'll see there's a tab at the
bottom in the book this red piece is all
made in one piece but because of the
complications with measuring and stuff
I'm going to make it out of two pieces
this piece that the piece that comes up
that needs to be the same height as the
total yellow so now having made the tab
on one end I just need to measure how
high the whole thing needs to come this
time so I'll just mark that so that's
flush with the bottom this is where the
other tab is going to be so I'm going to
cut that to make a tab on it and cut
that off
right so this is going to be the other
time now I can glue the two sides
together just to make it a really strong
pushing strut there we go
and just while that dries you see here
because I've made this red piece out of
two pieces I've put a little hinge on
the top of the yellow that's so you can
attach it all so this is the hinge it's
just a small piece with a fold in the
middle needs to be lined up with the
slot
put a bit of glue on that and that's
gonna go there okay now we're gonna
thread this through this is going to
stick down it's going to go up
through the slot and stick them in the
front of the whole thing in line with
the hinge I've put on so I'll just put
some glue on that tab there stick it
down just make sure that's all still
working nicely clicks as I'm slightly
off up there and it's straighter now
when they when the base is flat this is
the whole finger is flat so I'm going to
make this flat this is the piece I'm
going to add on it's going to stick on
to this urn this let's close it down so
this is going to stick on there and I've
just put glue on the two tabs this top
one on the Reds that should be pointing
this way when you add the finger to it
the end of this strip goes on to that
crease as it lies down you can see it's
going to be too long this is going to
come down here so I'm going to trim some
of that off immediately and then fold
this down and that you can see I'm
actually slightly off there so now you
can see this is unfurling possibly it's
still slightly long tending to dag into
the page a little bit so I could cut off
a bit more might help then it so this is
the this is the unfurling mechanism and
if you want to make multiple fingers
like in the hands then you can make the
yellow at lots of different levels and
you can make this red piece that's
pushing up at lots of different levels
the other clever thing with this book is
this mechanism is hidden in David
Pelham's design so I'll just show you
how he's done that when the page opens
you see that the hand is actually
holding a locket and so actually this
locket is attached to the top of the
yellow up here and it slides up and down
this is a separate piece so if we lift
that up you'll see that this piece with
the thumb is one piece and this is
another so that locket actually hides
that so in effect there's one piece
stuck on here that's coming up and
there's another piece stuck on here
that's coming down over and hiding it
I'll just make that so you can see how
it's hidden I'll make that with a
different color I'll make that with some
green so I'll just make it very
basically so
so this is going to stick onto the red
piece there put a bit of glue on
that sticks on there and now there's
another overlapping piece of green
there's an overlapping piece of green
there so that will hide the the
mechanism really just put a small amount
of glue on to stick it on there so stuck
nice piece on the top there this is
hiding the mechanism I need to cast it
down so that it's long enough to go over
the top edge but it's short enough that
it doesn't crash into the alley down
there there it is in the book
obviously you know it's clever it's a
it's a locket so the fact that it's
moving is it's fine
that is the unfolding mechanism
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]