in tutorial 15 I was talking about
moving arms and this is an extension
living arms how you can use it to create
circular motions so here it is you open
to spread and you can make wheels turn
and there's some very nice examples I've
got down here this is Little Red Riding
Hood paper engineering by Bruce Foster
it's actually in this flap as you open
it you see the newspaper spins around so
it doesn't have to be wheels on the car
it can be any sort of circular motion
and then this is the Castaway pirates
paper engineering by Ray Marshall and I
think it's an absolute work of genius
actually it's beautiful book as you open
the spread you see this is the circular
motion based on the mechanism that I'm
about to show you so there's one example
in this book he's spinning around watch
the shark as I open the page and he
spins around this is circular motion
based on moving arms so now to show you
how to make one of these this is an
example this is based on the parallel
fold which is tutorial 5 and so here's
the parallel fold with a little counter
fold folded into the corner up here and
then you have this l-shaped piece and
that's what the wheel is stuck to the
key thing is there's a crease across one
arm of the L so that this piece can bend
up and down and then the other crucial
thing is the center of the wheel
goes right on this point so the inner
corner of the l-shape goes where all the
creases meet and then the center of the
wheel goes on that point so I'll just
make you one
so here I've prepared the bits and
pieces we've got another base sheet
here's the parallelogram piece so I'll
start by sticking the parallelogram on
and we need to measure that so put the
central crease of the parallelogram
piece onto the central gully of the base
mark where one of the creases lies there
is flip the whole thing over so I've
marked the short side and now the long
side is going to stick to that with
parallelograms when the base is flat the
whole parallelogram is flat so we can
keep it flat and just put glue on the
other tab here and glue that down make
sure it's actually working all right I
haven't put too much glue on or anything
like that now I've got this piece this
is the l-shaped piece that's going to
stick on like that so that needs this
the dotted line that's where the crease
is so I'll just do that by eye no need
to measure it or anything that top
sticks on to there bit fiddly this I
have seen some books where the whole
piece is made out of one piece of card
folded over and glued down so that glues
on there making sure the inner angle of
this l-shaped piece is right on where
all the blood converge and then you need
to get this central point of the circle
right on that same point
so this is already starting to move but
as you see because it's on one of these
angled pieces the circle will tend to
lift up at an angle so you've got two
choices you can either like this one
have a piece stuck onto the
parallelogram that goes behind the
circle like this that goes on here and
that actually holds the circle up the
other way you can do is have a piece
below it so you can stick it on down
here and that holds left bottom of the
circle down so I think I'll just do one
of those in this case cut a piece off
make this a bit better size and just put
a bit of glue on here glue that down so
this one would be improved if this extra
piece was a proper parallelogram coming
down and joining on to the page the
wheel trying to lift up is actually
lifting up the parallelogram its lifting
up this plane whereas if this came down
and joined the page that would just hold
it up flat and you get a nicely turning
William if I just add a few marks on
there you'll be able to see that it is
actually turning so as I turn it you see
that it does have that turning movement
you can see because it isn't attached to
the base it actually the wheel pushes it
up if you look at this one this piece is
actually another parallelogram so it
comes down and joins the page and you
see when it's closed it sticks out that
far that I can't actually fix it onto
that way so I'm just going to pull that
off it's pop ups quite a forgiving
medium really you can chop and change as
you go along I've got a piece that's
it's been cut to the right dimension so
I can make a proper parallelogram that
will stick down behind the wheel
and that'll hold it into position so
being a parallelogram you can stick the
whole thing down flat and then I put
some glue on this parallelograms tab and
smooth other bits and put it all flat
goes underneath the wheel if it's at the
top stick it down let's hope it works
yeah there we go there's the turning
wheel as a turning way they say okay and
you can see it can be used to make cars
and things but it's actually more
interesting used to make you know things
like the newspaper turning heads turning
things like that there's one other book
that's got really good examples it's
Robert Cebu ders the night before
Christmas here's an example here the way
the hand on the clock is made to move
that is using the turning wheel
mechanism but if we look under here
there's a whole array of wheels for
turning in different directions so
turning wheels quite a complicated
mechanism the real detail is in this
earlier book can pop up a manual of
paper mechanisms and actually out of
print but I think it's possible to get
secondhand versions
you