[Music]
this tutorial is about how to make a
moving piece a pull strip which when you
pull it it makes a vertical piece slide
across the page well I'll show you my
version first which is quite simple and
basic here it is you've got a v-fold and
as you pull the strip it makes a piece
glide across the page so it's quite
useful then it's quite a simple
mechanism the example I've got in books
is this one the Peter Rabbit pop-up book
and this one is slightly more
complicated the v-fold when you pull it
the figure is articulated its using hubs
there's a hub behind here and there's a
hub owner on the moving piece so as you
put it the figure can move so I'm just
going to show you how to make this
moving piece and hubs are explained in
tutorial 27 hubs and pivots
the base sheets that you see it that way
it has a the pull strip is going to
go underneath and then the moving piece
is going to come above it first we have
to stick on a v-fold this is a regular V
fold this is tutorial number two a
symmetrical regular right angle V fold
there's going to fold down backwards as
the page closes I'll just glue that to
the page
I've made it with the is going to
be in front of the v-fold
you might want to do the behind the
v-fold in which case you'd probably need
these two tabs to go forwards instead of
backwards but I decided to make them go
backwards out of you so there it is it's
aligned with that that I've already
cut is about two millimeters wide
then we can shut this down close the
page so it finds its natural sticking
position all that's explained in
tutorial one there's that now we're
going to need a piece in front which is
going to hold the moving piece upright
so maybe I'll put that on after the
movement this is going to be the moving
piece this is going to be the pull strip
that moves it I'll glue this into place
first so a little bit of glue on the
moving image stick that on one end of
the pull strip pull strips always make
them double thickness it's scored down
the middle to give it extra strength and
then put glue all the way alone pull
that shirt glue it shut it's quite good
when you glue these things to put them
flat and then smooth them out otherwise
they can end up slightly buckled anyway
that's that's now we can slop this
through there through the slots in the
page now this actually at this point it
does look as though it's quite good at
just staying upright of its own accord
but just to make sure we'll put another
piece in front so I've put a little tab
on one end and then this other end it's
going to fit tight into that it doesn't
need to be this long so I'm going to cut
it off you might want to leave it as
long
another sliding image on the other side
put a little bit of glue there and some
glue on there be careful with these tabs
if it's too long it could get in the way
and start cramping the style at the
moving piece but I think that would be
okay so now if we pull this you can see
it moves up and down nicely
you still need another piece behind it
so keep the strip out flush against the
page so I've just got a big piece like
this it's slightly too big so that's
going to stick on like that so you just
need a thin bead of glue along each edge
to be careful but it doesn't lose
underneath the strip and gum everything
up so just put a very little boost on
each side of it there like that smear it
nicely let's see yeah you might want to
play around with the end you could
either cut it off or you might you could
cut it off anyway cut it off like that
so you might want to a little curve
there so you can cut it off flush with
the page and and still be able to get
hold of it
there is the the sliding vertical image
of course you could put out Suzy's one
one behind the other and you can
probably if you're clever enough you can
put them all working off one pull strip
but I'll need you to work that out for
yourselves
[Music]