[Music]
this tutorial is about zigzag folds
here's is self-explanatory it's just
four planes two tabs gluing it to the
page you can vary it somewhat here's
another example this is based on the
parallelogram so the important thing is
this length on the pop-up is the same as
this length on the base this length on
the pop-up is the same as this length on
the base where it's glued to the base
they're angled so they meet at the same
point on the spine you can also play
around with it these two types the
creases are all vertical but you can
actually vary the creases and make them
lean in or out and that gives you more
interesting sculptural strengths to play
with so here's one example there's the
central crease and you've got the two
outer ones pointing in towards the
middle and then in this example this is
the central crease and you've got those
two creases pointing out but it's still
just the two places that it's stuck down
and then when you build these they
create gullies that you can build into
so yeah if we just look at well this
you've got you've got these 3 gullies
you can build into there's the first one
I started with this one so here these
are the two gullies that you would
normally build into there is one here
and so here's an example this is the
basic zigzag fold with these houses
built into the gun
if I fold it shut you can see how it's
being glued down underneath and the
houses are based on on parallelograms
and yes I've only got one commercial
example this is the fairytale village
bilats low back and here it is you've
got a zigzag fold and the houses are
built based on parallelograms built into
those gullies and you've got another
zigzag fold there and then these zigzag
shapes that explained more fully in my
book pop-up designer paper mechanics
[Music]