[Music]
this tutorial is about a very simple
mechanism I call it the stage set
mechanism it's very good for giving
depths when you open the base like this
you can really play with perspective
this book is Cinderella by rolling pin
made in 1950 and I'll just run through
it so you can appreciate the way he's
used the mechanism to create an enormous
sense of depth in each scene there's six
scenes you can actually tie the book
back-to-back to make a complete roundel
I'll show you that in a minute but this
one the threads are shot so you can't
really do it with this one that's
Cinderella the other one I've got is
Alibaba this is also 1950 1947 something
like that if you look from the top
you'll see that there's six sections or
like six segments you'll see there's
this is the base bit and then this is
the front piece that dictates how wide
the whole spread will go and then you
have two other pieces this is slightly
longer than the first one this is
slightly longer than the second one and
they're all slightly shorter than the
final one so now I'll make one so you
can see how to do it
I'm going to make this the base piece
this piece I've already made this is
going to be number two it's going to fit
in like this and so you can see there's
going to be one piece that's longer
that's going to go in there and another
piece that's shorter that's going to go
straight across the front
they're all already folded I'm going to
make the front piece grey if you want to
make it six pieces to make a roundel
like that Alibaba then you have to bear
in mind that this angle will have to be
sixty degrees because there'll be six of
them adding up to 360 as it is I'm just
making the one so it doesn't really
matter it's just what suits me so I'm
going to put this in position to see
roughly where I need to make the folds
to make these tabs that will stick it on
I'm going to make a mark so I can just
see roughly where to put those
bowls it's going to be about here fold
that in half
hold it there so this is how wide the
whole thing is gonna open up - so
there's gonna be two tabs on each side
of that and before I put that in I've
got to make another one that's coming in
between the blue one and the yellow one
I'll use this as a guide and make it
longer than the blue but it'll still be
shorter than the yellow so let's make it
about here so I'll fold that
and we'll just check how well this is
going to all fit together okay
yellow is number four blue is number two
and gray as number one so it's going to
be like this you look at it Endon it's
going to be like that and before you
glue them you need to cut the holes you
need to make your design on all of them
and cut the holes into them so this gray
this is number one this is just going to
be the screen that you're looking
through so I'm just going to make that
really simple and just cut a rectangle
out of it
so that's going to be the front this is
going to be the back we don't cut
anything off that this is going to be
number two that you're looking through
and then this will be the final one so
on this you really need to work out your
design whatever you want you draw it on
and cut it out I'll just do something
quite basic I think but quite big
because you want to be able to see
through it to the third level and then
this is the final one this will be
number three that's the final thing you
look through so that could be a smaller
hole so you have bits of it showing bits
of it hidden by the blue section right
so we take the base folder crease is
really well and just glue them on glue
on them both at the same time
okay this is going in here if you want
at this point this not too late you can
actually stick other pieces on a
different color you just want to add to
it this is your chance to do it easily
and stick pieces on like this now we put
level two on just shut it down and press
it firmly make sure it's all working
nicely and now we put the third level in
looking at this I don't actually like
that blue piece are stuck in I'm just
going to take that off I think maybe if
it had been red or something completely
different it would have worked but it
was just muddling up the whole design
and then this is the final piece this is
the one that dictates how wide the scene
will open there we are so this is just a
really crude design showing you how it
works and how to put it all together but
the whole point of this mechanism is
that you can generate a really wonderful
sense of depth and perspective by
playing around with it and really
working on the design and thinking about
it asymmetrical here we have Alibaba you
can see the way he's played around using
the mechanism to generate perspective
and some really nice interesting designs
I think these are really clever
beautiful little books from the 1940s
1950 and that's the final spread i'll
just untie it so you can see the camera
so here it is the cover Ali Baba and the
Forty Thieves by ionic Asst
[Music]
[Applause]