this tutorial is about hubs and pivots
it's ways of joining two pieces of card
together so they're flat and they can
turn in this case you've got this
turning wheel it's got a window in the
wheel and the images are on the page
behind it or you can use it the other
way around so you have a window in the
page as you turn the wheel the image
changes this is the way you make it
basically there's a wheel with a hole in
it and then you have this hub the hub is
just a circular piece with two little
tabs that fold up it sticks to the page
they come up through the wheel and fold
down flat again and so in this example
this is what the hub looks like these
are the two little flaps and then this
blue piece has been stuck on to hold it
steady just to hold it all down as it
moves there's a tendency for the flaps
to lift up a bit so it can be quite good
to reinforce it so I'll just put this on
together so you can see easily how it
works and then I'll show you some
examples so when you put the glue on you
just put it onto the main body of the
hub and again with all these pull strip
type mechanisms you don't want the glue
oozing or it really gums up the works
and stops them moving I've already
marked where this goes so the wheel will
fit with this bite out of the base page
so it makes it easy to turn so there is
where the flaps are cut back to you
don't want it too tight or too loose or
the wheel just wobbles around so you
need it fairly precise to fit within the
wheel and here you can see so maybe
again if I put some marks on this you'll
be able to see how it moves more easily
so there is obviously just spins around
quite easily and so I just look at some
books there's Leon the chameleon by Nina
can yak this is it there's a hub here
behind the page which is enabling the
color of the chameleon to change as you
pull it around it just keeps moving on
and then this book trail by David Pellom
fantastic book this one so here it is as
you turn the wheel the text in the
window keeps moving on there's one of
these on each page so if we look at this
one the text is down at the bottom of
the page down here as we turn it you can
see the text keeps moving on so this
book robot by yam pions Kowski it's got
a nice example here where you've got the
the wheel is behind the page as you turn
it you get these optics so that's pretty
good and then on the other side you've
got the same wheel as you turn it you
have the earth spinning in the window
the actual mechanism has a lot of
different uses so I'll just show you
some of those this is a really
interesting useful mechanism as you pull
the strip it makes the image on the page
rotate here's the way the mechanism
works
this is a basic pull strip that we did
in tutorial 25 it has this additional
flap on it the hub is a normal help just
like we made here but in this case it's
not attached to the page the arms go
through the page and have the image
stuck onto them the other main body of
the hub has this arm stuck on it again
make this double thickness because it
does take some stress that goes through
the hole in the flap as you put it the
amount of movement is governed by this
sleeve that controls the direction and
this slit that controls the direction so
those two control the direction of the
pull strip they also control the amount
of movement and here's another example
it's just a different image rotating on
the page it's the same thing you can see
there's the pull strip moving the arm on
the hub in this case the hub has been
made with its arm it's all one piece the
other thing to remember with these to
get the maximum movement you need the
pull strip to be as close to the hub as
possible the further away it is from the
hub the less movement you'll get so keep
it as close as you can when you're
making one of these this I think is just
yeah this is just that just shows you
how you can really just budge it up you
know this is the governor that controls
the amount of movement it's just a piece
being stuck onto the pull strip to stop
it moving any further it's as much to
stop this end of the pull strip pulling
out from the sleeve there no images just
as the piece moving
the hub can also be used to articulate
movement so here's one the mechanism is
the same as what we've just looked at
there's the hub with the arms going
through the page and it's got an arm
attached to it going through this flap
on the pull strip so as you pull it it's
exactly the same as what we looked at
just now on the other side you've got a
chain this is where there's a hub behind
here which is what's being moved by the
pool strip there's one here which is
attached to the page and then these two
are linking the three pieces of cards as
you pull it the whole thing is
articulated you can only use three if
you have just two arms then it's
triangulated it's just rigid it won't
move if you have more than three then
it's a chain so one end or move but the
other end just thought it doesn't do
anything they'll just sort of move
around and this is very clear what it's
doing and there's two good examples one
is in robot by NP and Kowski has a
really nice example of an articulated
image so it's the the mum robot dumping
the baby robot in the washing machine as
you pull the strip down goes the baby
and so again this is three pieces one is
attached to the pull strip one is
attached to the page and the other two
are attached to the baby and if we look
at it from behind you can see there are
the two hubs that holds the three pieces
together and there's another example
color surprises College who prays by
David Pellom here is it's this dragon as
you pull the strip the dragon is
articulated so it's working in a
different way but you can see the pull
strip will be attached to the middle
piece here and then these two hubs
attaching them to the page so the whole
thing can just just move around as you
put it
another one I'd like to show you this is
quite it's quite a surprising movement
as you pull the strip the image swoops
and extends across the page and so the
way this one works again here's the
basic pull strip that we looked at in
tutorial 25 here's the flap here's the
hub the hub is attached to the page and
then these two arms come up and go
through the hole in this purple piece
the purple piece you have to do it with
a compass so there's three circles one
here and then one here and one here so
this slit that the whole thing appears
through that is aiming at the center of
all these circles so it just moves
through it quite smoothly so this bit
takes quite a lot of stress it needs to
be quite broad or it'll tend to buckle
and this arm as well needs to be double
thickness or again it'll tend to buckle
because it does take quite a lot of
stress again a very pleasing mechanism
and you can always put a image on the
end here so you have an image swooping
across the page and the last is another
quite odd little variation it's the same
type of pull strip with a flap on it and
a sleeve controlling the direction but
in this case this arm it has two little
tabs that fold down push through the
hole so that the end of this arm is
fixed to that square flap then the whole
thing just comes up through this hole in
the page as you pull it it gives you a
different action from the front you look
at the front and you can see it it gives
a different kind of action from all the
other ones hubs and pivots are looked at
in more detail in these two books of
mine
the most recent pop-up design and paper
mechanics but the subject is looked at
in much more detail in this book pop-up
a manual of paper mechanisms
unfortunately out of print now but you
can still get secondhand copies
you