this tutorial is about automatic bull
strips the principle is that you have a
strip of card and it's stuck to one side
as the page opens this strip goes across
the other page under and out again and
as the page opens it pulls that strip
and so this end that's moving can be
used to make it raise up a bowing shape
raise up a flap raise up a parallelogram
you know it has all these uses so I'll
show you examples of these other ones so
here's one this is raising up a bow in
shape and in this case that the strip
that's pulling it just goes underneath
this edge you step down and it goes
through a slot underneath there but it
doesn't actually go under the page which
means this end this side here can tend
to lift up a bit but in this example
it's actually behaving pretty well this
is another example here's the strip if
you look at it this way you can see it
does go under the page and come out
again and that lifts this flap which
then lifts this parallelogram and then
in this example here is this is the pull
strip pulling up this bowing shape and
because it's a curved shape you can
stick straight pieces of card onto it at
different points on the curve and they
will all lift up at different angles so
I'll just show you one more example of
the mechanism this is the most simple
this is worms wiggle by David Pellom and
as you open this
it pulls the fake price across so now we
just make the simplest kind so you'll
need a base sheet something like this
fold it in half crease it really
thoroughly right no take another sheet
of card and just cut it in half
lengthways so draw a couple of
guidelines use your ruler to draw a
couple of parallel guide lines down the
length of it put the ruler in the middle
for the two guidelines
now folder a tab on to one end this is a
gluing tab so it's about half an inch
wide or one centimeter fold that really
well the other end cut off about an inch
two and a half centimeters something
like that just make it slightly shorter
and fold a gluing tab on to that as well
like now take your base sheet put one
name against the crease so it's like
this here's the central gully of the
base sheet and now fold it over so it's
just within the outer edge of the card
so that when the when the thing is flat
it doesn't doesn't just out now on the
long side this is where the strips going
to be on this long side just draw a
little guideline here again it's about
one centimeter in this helps the whole
thing move more smoothly when you stick
it together
now take a craft knife or scissors and
cut out the strip just a couple of
millimeters on the inside of these guide
lines so that the strip you're making is
just going to be slightly narrower than
the guide lines you've drawn and then
cut along that second second guide
right now the other ends take out a
piece in between the two guidelines and
this one you start just a couple of meal
or a millimeter above the fold line and
take it to a millimeter or two outside
the guidelines so you're getting a wider
gap here and now you can can just trim
all these gluing tabs just take those
corners off okay now just fold it over
this is your piece with a crease there
just this fold is over and make sure
that the that the pull strip fits snugly
between these two so when when you pull
it it all just moves moves easily
there's some clearance between the strip
and these two tabs activation lay it in
place so you've got the very tip of the
of the pull strip up against the central
gully now these two tabs fold underneath
you put glue on them both glue them at
the same time so they're going to be
folded underneath like that put glue on
them both all the tabs on this mechanism
take quite a lot of stress so make sure
the glue goes right up to the creases
and you know that there they are well
glued put it underneath put the tip of
the pull strip up against the spine
press it down okay and you can just test
that it's working you can now you can
just pull this and make sure that it is
lifting up okay so that's lifting up all
right now you put glue with the tab flat
you put glue on the top of the tab this
tab really takes a lot of stress so make
sure this is very very well glued
and now you can close the base so it's
going to find its natural sticking
position give it a moment for the glue
to go off and then open it up so there's
your bowing thing and then yeah if you
want you can stick pieces onto onto this
so you can see the different angles that
lift up according to where you stick
them and you can stick them on either
side of this but if you stick them on
this side coming up this way they're
more likely to bashing to the base as it
as it closes so the easiest one is to
have them coming up this way and you
just need a little bit of glue these
don't take any stress at all so there's
one stick one on the on the top I'll
stick it a completely different angle
you can stick one halfway up so you can
see that's something you can really see
the plane then as you see I've done a
bit low on this rough so they do get out
you've also got a gully here so you can
you can stick other pop-ups in today so
here we have um help the animals of
South America by Roberts óbuda and the
very first one he's played with this
idea of having the pieces stuck onto the
the rounded shape to make these scales
and as it closes opens and closes those
all lift up at different angles the next
one is is fly machines by a penny
here's the spread and so this is the
curve shape here's the strip it's glued
down on this side it goes across the
spine dives under the page there then it
will come up again underneath the
balloon and be attached to this side of
the balloon so as the page opens the
balloon goes up so if we look at it this
way you can probably see underneath here
you
TV the strip coming up underneath the
balloon there's another example further
on I'll just go through the book and
they have a look so this is the one
we've just looked at not this one
this one so here here in here these are
two the for this one here's the strip
it's attached to this side of the page
goes across the spine goes underneath
immediately goes right across comes up
there underneath the wing of concorde
pulls up the flaps and then the concorde
is built onto a parallelogram so on this
one the strip is attached here on this
side of the page then it goes across the
spine and goes underneath and then here
you can see it comes up and it's lifting
a flap which is then lifting
parallelogram if I hold it up like that
you can see see the parallelogram
lifting that and the helicopter east up
on top of the parallelogram so that's
that one next one is some Wizard of Oz
there's a couple of examples in here so
this one it's a multiple strip it all
pulls by this this here is the mr. strip
that's stuck to this side it goes
underneath under the back of the page
there's a whole series of pull strips
they all come up through the page and
then lift these poppy flowers up and you
can see this bird the wing here's the
strip emerging from the page as as the
page opens you see that that strip is
disappearing back under the page pulling
up the bird wing and then a bit further
on here we are this is the curved shape
the son
the strip is is behind here it's hidden
behind this flying monkey or whatever it
is it's stuck to this side goes across
the spine under the page and then if we
look look up inside the tower you'll see
here there is the there is the strip
emerging and pulling on this side and
pulling this out into a curved shape and
then we've got Little Red Riding Hood
by Bruce Foster and on this one this
wolf head is a move by pull strip as you
open the flap you can see here's the
strip it flips the wolf head over and
the strip is attached to this flap here
it's attached behind the explosion goes
under the page comes up again that as
the flap opens it turns the wolf head
over and then the last one is the very
end of the book it's the last page it's
the this strip is attached to this side
it's hidden underneath the cat it goes
through through a hole in the in the
curved shape comes across as attached to
collate and pulls it up and then they
the all these pieces are taken advantage
of the of the curve to give you pieces
lifting up it at different angles and
the next book is the night before
Christmas Roberts a Buddha and at the
very end you've got this quite
spectacular winter scene if this is a
this is a v-fold lifting up these ones
but it's these two houses these are
raised by the automatic pull strip so
they are actually underneath the bridge
and they come across as you see as it's
closed they all shut down but as it
opens the pull strips you can see that
that under the bridge they go under the
page hidden pull strips except one is
attached this side goes underneath and
pulls up this house and this one the
strip is attached this side goes
underneath pulls up this end wall which
then raises the parallelogram
that pulls the whole house into shape
and finally and this blue 2 by David
Carter and this has got a whole series
of them open top shapes that are dealt
with in tutorial 18 so this is it all
the strip's are really really obvious
here you can see them coming out of the
page looking at it this way around you
can see how it's attached on this side
goes underneath on this side comes up
again and pulls up this this open top
shape so this is just a whole a whole
array of and four pull strips you can
just see really clearly how they're all
working if you look look at it end on if
you can you can just see them all
they're all just moving like that and
pulling these pulling these cones up
into the straight so that's it for pull
strips Paul strips are covered in this
my book pop-up design and paper
mechanics
you