this tutorial is about em phones in
essence impulse
it's a v-fold and the tabs that glue the
v4 to the page then have other defaults
glued into them this design is based on
an acute angle V font which is covered
in tutorial to this one this is based on
a asymmetric V font which is covered in
tutorial 4 and so here is the asymmetric
V fold and then it just has a ketone
v-folds built into the gullies the
difference is the apart from one being
asymmetric and the other symmetric in
this case all the tabs are behind in the
model in this one there's just two tabs
which come forward in front of the model
and it's all just a question of design
mechanically it doesn't matter which you
do in this example this just shows you
what you can start doing you can turn
thee the em fold generates a whole
series of planes there's six planes but
there's also a whole array of gullies as
well and the gullies you can add counter
folds to them like this you can you can
cut lemons and push pieces through so
you can use those mountain folds and
gullies to create a whole lot of more
planes that you can then play around
with this is this bird's this is made
with an n-fold it's just a
straightforward n phone
the tabs that glue it down have been put
behind it so they don't mess up the
design this one this is an EM fold being
used to raise another plane so this is
actually a parallel fold it's a curved
fold all the clouds are made with an end
fold so we take a base sheet fold it in
half crease it well and take half a
sheet and fold it in half so just fold
it in half crease it really thoroughly
and what what we're making here is is a
basic V fold as we looked at in tutorial
2 but with the difference that instead
of just starting near the bottom corner
and making two small gluing tabs we're
going to start about a third of the way
up so this is the first crease start
about a third of the way up and you have
a crease coming up towards the outer
edges and it doesn't really matter what
angle you do the different angles will
give you different shapes so if you want
to want to a specific shape just play
around with it till you find the angle
that you were so here it is open it up
the creases all make a big downward
pointing arrow there's the creases there
now fold it in half and just cut a wedge
where all the creases meet just cut a
wedge after that so now you have this
shape so now just fold up one side and
you're going to add another crease so
here's your initial fold now you're
coming up like this mustn't start here
at this point it's got to be somewhere
along this fold line so say a third of
the way and then fold it up this fold it
has to be leaning away so here's your
first of all this sort of spine one and
then
to be leaning away if it leans in with
that way it won't work and then fold
that back on itself that's one side now
we'll do the other side fold it up it
doesn't have to be the same angle you
can play around with it as long as the
angle of the fold is leaning away from
the center fold data
crease it well fold it back on its own
right now open it all flat so here it is
now you concertina it so start with the
middle fold that into a mountain fold
the next fold is going to be a valley
and the next one a mountain the next one
a valley so you can concertina and the
same on the other side starting with the
mountain fold in the middle next one's a
valley next one's a mountain next one's
a van you just pinch it all well now you
can open it up now this is going to
stick down something like this you've
got to have this central crease lined up
with the central gully the whole thing
as it closes it's going to fold forward
so the side where you want it on the
page you can have it right up at the
back if you want depending on your
design or you can have it quite near the
front you can also have it really tight
so you've got a really narrow Ridge in
the middle or you can go wide the wider
you go the more it'll lie down and then
these are the mountain folds with the
gullies behind them that you can play
with so we might just experiment with
that before we before we stick it down
so they take the top one we'll just turn
that into a counter phone so we fold
that that will then push back in so now
we've generated two more planes that we
will be able to play with we could do
the same for these next two we can just
fold them over you have to do this
before you stick it down it's much
easier so there we are
I've got two more planes and we can do
the same here you can make these folds
at any angle it really doesn't matter
and it's all just depends what what
shape you're trying to
luckily so we could we could just leave
it at that and now to glue it down you
just you decide first of all what what
angle you want it how tight how much you
want it standing up how much you want it
lying down I'm going to go for something
like this so these first two creases
there is about 45 degrees to the spine
and so put glue all over one side and
just glue it down like that now you fold
it shut put glue on the other one and
then you follow that Shutts fold the
whole base shot so it finds its natural
sticking position press it really firmly
to make sure the gluing your sons open
it up and there's your M fold I've just
ran through a few examples in commercial
books so this is where the wild Pirates
go sailing this if you look you'll see
this the main V fold and then it has
little counter forms here that are the M
fold and it's got additional tentacles
stuck onto those so in this case the
outer bit pieces are being used as the
muscle to lift larger larger pieces of
card this one is actually it's not an
n-fold these are extra little pieces
stuck in and they're pointing outwards
Rose on this one the M fold the the
angles are pointing in this one is an M
font so here it is this is the main B
fold here and then this is a v-fold on
on one side and on this side it's
another V but it's got an additional
piece of card stuck on the next one is
the Museum of unnatural history by Keith
mobic and here we have there's a whole
array this is a whole series of M folds
giving you the
legs of the spider and I think there's
another one near the end yeah this
figure here this the structure that it's
all built on is an n-fold so you've got
the main body with the shoulders that's
the original v-phone and you've got an
EM fold here lifting up this arm you've
got another end fold here lifting up
this arm and it's got a whole series of
complicated bits and pieces this is a
curved shape this is a parallel fold all
lifting up the other bits and pieces of
this design so the next one is the
Nutcracker by Nick Bench fields and it
has this extraordinary spread at the
back you've got the main body of it is
an M fold and then this is a box at the
back this is tutorial 14 this is a
floating plane here which is tutorial 12
but the bulk of it is this this this is
the main V fold in the middle and then
you've got these unfold wings out on
each side and the last one is Alice in
Wonderland with paper engineering by
Andy Mansfield and get ready this one is
really loud when you open it up so
Hey
and finally all M folds although
variations and varieties are explaining
this my book pop-up design from paper
mechanics
you