this tutorial is about 45 degrees balls
so here's an example you use two pieces
that are each two 45-degree folds and
they use to raise a piece vertically
above the central spine of the spread
there's an example here pop-up book of
nursery rhymes by Matthew Reinhart and
in this spread you can see here inside
here there are two 45-degree folds that
are used to raise the central pillar
that holds up this square spread and
that's actually hiding a v-fold that's
underneath it but the main point in this
tutorial is the two 45-degree folks
there's another example here this is The
Wonderful Wizard of Oz by Roberts óbuda
and in the final spread the pillar that
holds up the throne if you look at it
underneath here there are two 45-degree
folds so that's the main use of this
this mechanism so this is another way of
making a 45-degree fold this is using
slots which is in tutorial 11 take two
pieces of cards they both got a crease
along the bottom a gluing tab put them
reverse them around this is classic
slots the way you make slot so they're
put together like this and then you cut
up to the middle two cups about two
millimeters apart three millimeters
apart
so the two pieces will easily interlock
this one can stick down to the spine
flush with the spine this one will come
down on top of it and interlock with it
but before we do that we need to add the
45-degree folds so 45-degree fold is
very easy where you've got a right angle
you just fold the two edges up against
each other then one side crease it
really well so here are folding one
45-degree fold and then you fold the the
crease up against the line so that's
dividing the right angle into two
45-degree folds there it is crease it
well and now we stick this one down
flush with the spine I'll just take
these these corners off here
there's that one the other piece these
are going to stick down the two taps are
going to stick down at right angles to
the spine probably to give it some
balance so you can put one each way
again I'll make sure these creases are
really good snip off the corners just so
there's no points that are going to snag
you can stick both these down at the
same time I put glue on opposite sides
as they're going to face in opposite
directions smear the glue right up to
the crease
looks about right and then just fold the
crown through to make sure it's all
working comfortably so there it is
that's another way of doing it and then
having built this you can actually take
other pieces and just stick them on so
you can start constructing some sort of
tree or flower or you know whatever you
want to make really you can stick pieces
onto these you've also got two gullies
that you can build into so I'll just
stick these on as it closes you'll see
this is a gully that's closing and this
is a gully that's closing so both of
those you can add counter folded strips
too so we take a piece like this crease
it well fold an extra pair of creases
into it so in tutorial 8 we looked at
counter folding pieces so you can take
small pieces like this and you can just
stick them into these two gullies
created by the main mechanism so I'll
just stick one of these in and then any
of these planes that have been created
you can carry on building on those so
I'll just make sure this closes down
okay let's just trim it back a bit so
there it is and you can just keep
building adding extra pieces onto these
to create whatever sort of sculpture
you're interested in making you another
piece come on up like this any of these
planes can be built on I'll just show
you another example this is one red duct
by David Carter and at the back here
he's made of tree using this technique
if you look at these two claims this is
the mechanism you can see that these are
45-degree folds on each side on these
two these other ones are coming in at a
different angle so that creases have
been adjusted and then you can also use
it for things like this this is using
the same idea this is a bridge so these
are the two 45-degree folds they're
pulling up the whole mechanism you have
to have to they work in opposition to
each other in this case you can see
you've got to have some balance so the
top of this bridge piece a is the same
length between the Spiner where it
sticks down and on the other side B is
the same length there so that you've got
balance and the last thing I'd like to
show you is this one this is using the
same technique as we used here where
you've got interlocking pieces but the
whole middle section has been cut out so
we've got this dragon again if you look
at it straight on from above you can see
that two of the feet are stuck down
parallel with the spine and the other
two feet is stuck down at 90 degrees to
the spine and in each case there are
these these creatures on these two legs
those are the 45-degree folds and then
these the head and the tail these are
counter folded pieces looked at in
tutorial 8 and you can find out a bit
more about 45-degree folding this my
book pop-up design and paper mechanics
you