[Music]
my name is Duncan Birmingham my
speciality is teaching pop-up design and
this is the first in a series of
tutorials showing you how to make highly
complex pop-ups very easy way so I'm
going to start by just running through
the materials the basic materials that
you need are glue scissors and card the
type of card I recommend is 160 GSM you
can use heavier card 180 gsm up to 220
you can also use heavy-duty cartridge
paper really it all depends on the size
of the pop-up that you're making but for
these tutorials will be using photocopy
cards which is 160 GSM the best glue is
solvent based adhesive water base works
okay but it tends to make the card
buckle and it goes off more slowly so
it's much harder to work with stick
glues are okay they're nice and clean
and easy to use but they tend to crack
and so after a while yeah your pop-ups
will fall apart the other materials that
you won't need in these first tutorials
but in the later ones which are more
complex
you need a craft knife the type I really
like is this type with a extendable snap
off blade you'll need a ruler a metal
ruler is good you can cut long straight
lines against the edge a compass for
drawing circles with and again there's
only a few mechanisms that you need this
for but it's just a handy tool to have
your tool box you can also use it for
measuring with measuring notes
transferring lengths from one one model
to another a protractor and set square
for measuring angles and a ballpoint pen
without any ink so scoring on big pop up
scoring can be really important to get a
nice clean fold you score it a ballpoint
pen with no ink it tends to it just
compresses the fibers in the card rather
than cutting them so yeah I really
recommend ballpoint pen without any ink
and of course yeah
pencil and rubber you know just always
handy less materials now I'd like to
start with the most elementary of
pop-ups the most elementary pop-ups
we're just going to use a small piece of
card like this fold it in the middle all
these early tutorials there's absolutely
no measuring everything is just done by
eye so you can just cut a small piece of
card by eyes fold it in half folds are
really important in pop-ups so the more
you the more you fold it the most sweet
little moves its I always think of folds
as like they're like hinges and creasing
the fold thoroughly is like greasing the
hinge so you take this piece of cards we
cut into it just one cut from the folded
edge and then just bend that over so
we're bending that over like this so it
looks like that fold it back on itself
open it up and push that through this is
the most elementary pop-up this type is
converging creases so all the all four
creases the spine folds the spoke fold
in the middle and the two on each side
all converge at the same point the other
type of pop-up is parallel creases so we
take another card fold it in half fold
it thoroughly as usual
if time make two cuts again this is the
folded edge I'm cutting in from the
folded edge you don't even actually need
to use scissors you can actually tear it
the lines don't have to be straight they
can be they can be Wiggly jagged at an
angle whatever you like again fold it
back so you get this shape fold it back
on itself to enhance the creases open it
up push it through so you get a kind of
step these two these two pieces
demonstrate the basic underlying
principles of all pop ups all pop ups
either all the creases meet at the same
points they're converging creases
meeting at the same point on the spine
the other type of parallel creases so
all the creases are parallel to the
spine and these are the two underlying
principles in all pop ups so this type
of proper mechanism is called counter
folds and here's an example that I did
with some school kids and so this is
counter folds it's it's this type with
converging creases and it's made made
into a face and it's just glued on to a
background so this is really basic
simple stuff there is a book with some
in it this is this is dinner time by
champion Kowski look at the first spread
and it's one of these v-folds converging
crease converging creases pop-ups we can
also look at the last spread in this
book and here it is this bottom jaw of
this shark is converging creases this is
the V fold and the top drawer of the
shark is a parallel fold you can always
tell parallel folds if you look at the
book end on you can look down the spine
and you can see that although all the
creases are parallel this type of
mechanism can be applied to any folds in
any pop-up and so you can use this type
of mechanism as actual part of the
sculpting of the
the sculpture or it can be used as just
the muscle to raise a larger piece of
card so if we look at this book and this
is jungle days by Helen bomber and this
is an example of a counter fold being
used to scalp the actual pop-up so this
here this is the counter fold as the
book closes as it opens you can see how
it moves and yet this is all made from
one flat piece of card you can actually
close the book and just open and close
it like that so this is the counter fold
being used as part of the sculpture of
the design this book this is robot by
champion Kowski in this pop-up spread
these counter folds he's used these type
of converging crease counter folds these
are the muscles to move larger pieces so
this is a parallel fold and then here on
each side you've got these small counter
folds that are used to as the muscle to
lift these two little robots and so as
the page opens and closes you can see
the counter folds that muscles are
moving those two two small robots but
this type of pop-up these elementary
pop-ups when the page is flat the pop-up
is flat and they're not actually true
pop-ups they're more like something you
can add to pop-ups so I'm going to show
you how to make two pop-ups one
converging creases one parallel creases
there are three principals three
important principles that apply to all
pop-ups the first one is that every
pop-up must span a galley so this is a
base sheet we fold it in half do it by
eye crease it really thoroughly fold it
back on itself crease it again this is
your base sheet this is the galley
it's the galley opening that will power
the pop-up I'll take a piece to make the
pop-ups with
so do it again everything everything is
done by eye you just cut the piece of
card in half fold it in half crease it
really thoroughly and the second
principle is that pop-ups must must
balance on each side of the galleys
so pop-ups maths Panigale they must
stick down to both sides of the galley
and then they must balance on each side
of the gully so in this case we're
making a converging crease of V folds so
with v-folds it's the angles that
balance so here's the pop-up piece we're
folding the tabs onto the bottom which
will glue to the page by doing it this
way we've made the two the two angles on
each side of the pop-up at the same in
this case they're both ninety degrees
again reinforce those those folds so
we've got there the angles on the pop-up
a balancing now we've got to stick it to
the page and the two angles on the base
we've got to balance so we get the glue
my secret with glue is to put the glue
on on just on one side and then I always
use my little finger I use my little
finger so that I can spread the glue
really evenly but my fingers remain
dextra so I can handle other things and
without them getting stuck it's really
important that the glue goes right up to
the crease the crease in pop up is
really important the glue goes to the
crease all measuring is done to the
crease so here we go the central crease
is lined up with the gully and stick
that side down now you fold the whole
piece shut put glue on the other side
again smear the glue up to the crease
shut the base press it well and here's
the first pop-up so in this case every
pop out spans a gully and then the
second principle is every pop-up
misbalance on each side of the gully
with v-folds where the crease is all
converge at the same point
it's the angles at balance so the angles
on the base here are both the same size
the angles on the pop up are both the
same size so if we call this a and this
B we've got a plus B on one side we've
got a plus B on the other side so the
angles balanced this is the basic v-fold
[Music]
there are five configurations of these
folders so I'm going to show you the
other the other five so this is the type
we've just made this is the right angle
v-folds the angles on the pop-up are
both 90 degrees this is the acute angle
v-fold the angles on the pop-up they're
still both the same but the angles are
both less than 90 degrees this one is
the pointy v-folds this is a variation
on this acute angle but in this case
even more extreme this is the this is
the obtuse angle default so the angles
on the pop-up are both more than 90
degrees they're still the same on each
side and the angles on the on the base
are still the same on each side so
you've got balance and then this is the
final most most intriguing of the
v-folds really this is the asymmetric
v-fold so the angles on each side on the
pop-up are different and the angles on
the base are different you've got four
different angles but the angle on the
base on one side plus the angle on the
pop-up equals the angle on the base on
the other side plus the angle on the
pop-up so you still have balance even
though all four angles are different
[Music]
now I'll make a pop-up version of the
parallel fold take another base and
here's a pop up piece so this is
parallel fold
so in this case we make the the fold at
the outer edges when you make when you
make gluing tabs they should never be
less than half an inch or one centimeter
because pop-ups tend to they generate
quite a lot of stress on the tabs so you
need them to be fairly wide to take the
stress of opening and closing so this is
going to be the parallel fold and you
can actually play around with these you
can have it really wide on the page or
you can have it pretty close I tend to
actually cut off the corners of gluing
tabs I just think the when they're under
a bit less sharp they tend to snag less
it doesn't matter whether whether
they're inside like this or whether
they're outside like this you can you
know that the position of the tab
doesn't matter the only thing that
matters is the position of the crease so
here is by put by folding it in half and
then folding the tabs on we've got
balance on the pop-up piece the lengths
both sides are the same so again we just
put glue on glue on one side
snoo on well right up to the crease I'm
gonna have these these tabs on the
inside so we'll stick it down there the
crease is parallel to the central gully
then fold the whole piece shut put glue
on the other tab smear it up to the edge
and close the base so it finds its
natural sticking position so this is a
this is a parallel fold this is a
symmetric parallel fold there are three
kinds of parallel fold this is the this
is a symmetric equal parallel fold both
both sides are the same both lengths on
the on the pop-up at the same and the
distance from where it glues down to the
spine is the same so on the left you've
got a short bit on the base and a long
bit on the pop-up on the right you've
got a short bit on the base and along
with it on the pop-up this is the second
type of parallel fold this is the
parallelogram you look at it this way on
and you can see on one side on the left
you've got a short length on the pop-up
and they're long lengths on the base on
the right you've got a short length on
the base and a long length on the pop-up
so again you've got balance the length
balance and the last one this is the
this is the asymmetric parallel fold so
all four lengths are different so on the
Left you've got quite a long bit on the
base and the short bit on the pop-up on
the right you've got a short bit on the
base and a long bit on the pop-up
so as the whole thing closes you can see
from the spine fold to the leading
leading fold the two sides are the same
the the pop-up is balanced on v-folds is
the angles at balanced on parallel folds
it's the lengths at balance and the
third
the third principle is that every pop-up
creates gullies so the first principle
every pop-up my spanner gully and the
first gully is the spine fold the second
principle every pop-up must balance on
each site v-folds it's the angles
balanced parallel folds it's the length
of balance and then the third principle
is that every pop-up creates gullies and
you can stick pop-ups into those gullies
so here's a gully on a parallel fold you
could stick this in like this or you
could stick this this one in like this
and on on the V folds again you've got
you've got these gullies you can stick
it into on the back as the page closes
the the pop-up will close or you've also
got a gully here you can stick there you
can stick the pop-up into the gully you
can stick it any height you like in some
way I've got a an example here is this
is a this is a v-fold the blue piece is
a v-fold
and there's pop-up stacking this is a
parallel fold stuck into this gully and
this is converging creases or stuck into
this gully all these are different forms
of of pop-up stuck into the different
gullies here you've got an example of a
counter fold like that like this piece
this is this is a big counter fold is
the same principle applied to this piece
of pop-up there's three ways you can use
the base either the base can either be a
base that the pop-up rises from it can
be a background that the pop-up comes
forward from or it can be a base and a
background and with the pop-up stuck
into the gummy so the first one I'd like
to show you is this is Christopher
Columbus bye subasta it's a pop-up from
the 50s
this is using this is using the base as
a as a base with the pop-up rising from
it
there is and this is if you actually
look at it from the top you can see it's
based on v-folds although where it's
glued to the page all the creases will
converge at the same point so this is
this is a pop-up using using the base as
a base with the pop-up rising from it
the second way you can you can use the
base is with the base as a background
with the pop-up coming forward from it
this is the little fish who cried shark
so if we open this one up this is using
the the base as a background so you've
got the pop-up coming forward from it
and in this case again both both halves
of the design they're based on V folds
and they look to me like a symmetric
v-folds so the angles on the two pop up
each side of the popups are different so
this is using the pop-up as a as a
background and the third kind is a it's
another capacitor again it's from the
50s it's the base and the background so
so that that's the last thing I want to
talk about really techniques and then
the last thing I'd like to say is almost
all all popups use a combination of
mechanisms so I've got a few examples
here this is when I made this is this is
V folds all three folds and then this V
fold at the front is raising raising
this the dog and the dog is made of a
whole series of parallelograms so this
is a combination this design is a
combination of V folds and
parallelograms and then this is a this
is a really early pop-up this pop-up is
from the 30s this is from a series
called the Baccano series and this is
number 15 I think they're about 30 and
the designer was a guy called Louisa
roan and so here is this is a this is a
pop-up again you can see the the basic
part
is a v-fold and the v-fold is raising
parallelograms raising these other
images so if you look at it this way
around you'll see that these other
images of parallelograms raised by the
v-fold
and then this is a more modern one this
is David Pellom Appleby's shapes and
this is this is the same thing here we
have it Appleby's shapes it's a it's a
v-fold it's a cute angle v-fold again
it's raising parallelograms so you look
at it this way around and you can see
it's parallelograms raised by the v-fold
and there's another one here this is one
of my favorites this is Chuck Murphy
black cat white cat and in this case
you've got this it's quite extraordinary
construction this is the v-fold the the
box is the v-fold it's actually a this
is a parallelogram the back of the box
but it's this front half of the box is
the v-fold which is raising the whole
structure you look at it this way around
and you can see the ladder and
everything else is parallel folds and
it's it's all raised by the by the
v-fold the v-fold box raises the whole
structure and then the last one and this
is fantastic fantastic fairytales
I think this barrier Ron van der Meer
and here we have it in this case this is
a this is a right angle V fold raising
parallelograms you look at it this way
as the as the page closes the
parallelograms lifts up you look at it
straight on you can see this is the
gully that this parallelogram is built
into this is the galley that the next
one is built into this is the gulley
that the next one is built into so
that's it for this tutorial
if you want to follow it that this is my
book pop-up design and paper mechanics
everything we've looked at
they is in this book
[Music]
[Applause]
you