this tutorial is about the box mechanism
this is one of the most important
mechanisms for building sculptural
pop-ups so here's an example this is the
box and the way it works is quite basic
if you look at it this way you can see
it's actually 2 parallelograms centered
on the central spine fold this central
pillar pushes up the lid the lid pushes
out the top of the sides this is crucial
and then you have this piece that joins
the two outer edges
that's what locks the whole piece into
shape this is used in endless sculptural
pop-ups oh I just got a couple of simple
ones here and this is a just a basic
quote be free Owl and the Pussycat it's
based on the box this is the box you can
see here's the pillow that pushes up the
lid this is the lid and then these
curved shapes these are what lock the
whole piece into position this is a
slightly more fancy one this is again
this is the basic box if you look at it
end on you can see there is a pillar
glue to the spine that pushes up the lid
the bonnet and the roof and pushes those
up that it's the lids that push out the
sides of the top of the structure and
then you know here's the and the two
ends that lock the whole thing into
shape
you will need a ruler as well as a biro
or something like that to score with and
glue and scissors so start with a scored
line this is going to go right across
the paper this is going to be your
glueing tabs just go right across do it
three times so you got one two three you
want strips so we're just making a
really simple small box so these are
going to be cut lines rather than score
lines
so we'll just draw it in there there's
one there one here and two more in here
that don't go all the way up so early so
when you cut it out I'm just going to
use a craft knife rather than scissors
and it's just for speed but you can use
you can use either so just cut along
these these lines so you're making four
strips you might want to cut against the
metal ruler but I usually just do it by
eye and then trim these up
so two like that and two like this here
we are got two short ones which are just
two squares with a tab on each end and
you have two long ones that are three
squares of the tab on each end and we'll
just fold all those those fold lines
so here's your base sheet a single piece
of card thoroughly creased and then you
have your your four step of strips that
are going to make the box so you've got
two long ones two short ones so take one
of these long ones put glue on one end
you glue you glue this one end flush
with the spine so it's like that then
you can just fold out just make sure
it's really comfortable there so that
that's one you now fold it into its
closed position
put glue glue right up to the up to the
crease is quite important
shut the vase open that up now you've
got a parallelogram this is covered in
tutorial 5 now you build the same thing
on the other side of the spine so you
take your other three panel strip put
glue on one end glue again flash with
the spine slows it down and then glue on
the other end of that strip put it in
its closed position shut the base okay
now you've got two parallelograms back
to back this is still an unstable
structure at this point if you're going
to want something coming up out of the
middle if you want something like the
masked on this aisle and Pussycat boat
sticking up from the middle of the box
now's your chance to put it in so if you
want that stick it in now otherwise now
put glue on on the surface in the middle
here and glue these two back to back
this central pillar takes quite a lot of
stress so it's good to have it double
thickness card so is it it can push up
the top quite easily without buckling
this is still an unstable structure this
is just to parallelograms and as you can
see it just wobbles around this is
actually the basis of really early
pop-ups the Victorian pop-ups were just
made with parallelograms like this which
gave you a floating plane above the page
but there wasn't stable they could just
wobble around it was still 3d but not a
rigid structure then you take one of
these two panel pieces and these stick
across they attach to the outer Plains
and where the tabs go really doesn't
matter it's a question of your design
they can go inside or outside and these
yeah I'm just going to do it on the
outside just for simplicity
you can put glue on both tabs at the
same time glue them in glue them on shut
the base just to make it fun now this is
a this is a rigid structure you don't
need the panel on the other end only if
you're really wanting to make a solid
box also it doesn't need to be the full
height of the of the box yeah as long as
it's joining the two outer planes then
it will work the difference between
these and the floating plane type
mechanism that we looked at in tutorial
12 is as you close the base the lid
sinks down and the outer end comes up so
it will stop you having anything that
juts out forward you can have pieces
that are jetting out this way and this
way but in this case they can't just out
directly from the top
so now I'm going to show you a whole
range of amazing pop ups and pop-up
sculptures that are all up all based on
the box like this so this is this book
is The Nutcracker by Nick Dench field
and it has a really amazing flamboyant
display the important thing in this
tutorial is this piece at the back this
is the box so as the rest folds down the
rest is all based on defaults the box at
the back stays stays vertical we look at
the back of it you can see here's the
central pillar that pushes up the lid on
the top and then the lid pushes out
there the top of the walls at the side
so as it closes you can see how that
works so that that's the box is part of
a part of a big display the next one I'd
like to show you is roaring lion tales
by Ron van der Meer
this is an interesting variation this is
a a circular variation is still stacked
down parallel to the spine on each side
but the ends are rounded more like the
boat that I showed you at the beginning
and as you close the base you can see
that the top of the box sinks down and
this has a chunk cut away from the side
so you can see inside you can see the
central pillar and that actually has
some movement on it so quite quite an
interesting sculpture this one knee next
we have this is another variation the
way this one's been used this is great
pop-up buildings of the world by David F
Smith and this this model of the Golden
Gate Bridge
this is based on the box if you look
there is a central pillar pushing up the
lid which is the deck of the bridge and
then the V some these side bits those
are the pieces that lock the whole thing
into shape so as it closes you can see
all the components of the box are there
but it's just in a really unusual
configuration next we have Dinah topia
by James gurney
and here it is this dinosaur with a
curved shape the curved shape is
tutorials 13 it's built onto a strap
which is tutorial 9 and as we close it
you can see is a central pillar pushing
up the box the lid is inside the
dinosaur and then these are these are
the sides that hold it all together so
this is a curved shape built on top of a
box and built onto a strap so the whole
thing is not centered on the center
center of the book but off off to the
side next we have Hormats pop-up book of
famous ships this is a really beautiful
little popper this is very unusual
notice of these box designs they go up
and down the central spine of the book
this one is really clever it's been
going across it if you look at it end on
you'll see there's the pillar coming up
from the spine that pushes up the deck
the sides of the ship at the ends that
lock it into place and in actual fact ik
it does go there is a slight a slight
straight bit at each end yeah beautiful
bit of bit of design that one
this book is pop-up board games with
paper engineering by Matt Johnston and
here's the one I want to show you this
is another boat if you look at it as it
closes you'll see there's a there's a
pillar in the middle that is pushing up
the deck and then the deck is pushing
out the sides of the boat interestingly
this mast is because it's got rigging
the rigging is stuck to the sides of the
boat as the book closes its the the deck
is going down but the sides of the boat
are going up so you can't have the masts
stuck to the top of the rigging and
stuck to the base this mast it's looses
slides up and down inside the deck the
next one is some fabulous flying
machines paper engineering but if penny
and this is a really amazing sculpture
it's based on the box with a whole
series of parallelograms if you look at
it end on you'll see there's the central
pillar pushes pushes it up and then the
bottom wing is the the equivalent of the
lid of the box and then it's just a
whole series of parallelograms and this
piece at the front that's part of what
locks it into shape but also in this
case these propellers these are at
diagonals and so as the page closes
those are stuck into the two corners of
the parallelogram that go further apart
as the page closes those are coming
together til you reach the right
position and then they lock the hook the
whole thing into shape next we have
Willie bollocks
maxi's machines this is the most
extraordinary set of sculptures really
and this is the one I want to show you
that the massive truck it goes beyond
this tutorial this is really
extraordinary has a pull strip built
into it when you pull the strip the trap
lifts up and and dumps the the contents
of the back I can show you this sideways
on as you pull the tab the whole back
the truck lift up and dumps the tarmac
or whatever out now really extraordinary
sculpture that one let me go to a quite
an old line issue some
chitty-chitty-bang-bang by hallmark
paper engineering by Paul Taylor this is
the car again this is based on the box
if you look at it end on you'll see
there's a pillar in the middle that
pushes up the lid the lid is inside it's
really it's really hard to see if you
look this way you can probably see
inside there is the lid which the
central pillar pushes up and then the
lid pushes out the sides and then the
bonnet of the car goes over the top so
on these structures you have to have the
lid inside because as the page closes as
the book closes the lid goes down and if
you want the bonnet to stay popping up
that has to be a separate piece
so there's the lid inside the pillar in
the center pushes up the lid that lid
pushes out the walls on the side and
then this is a separate piece stuff on
top next we've got the Wizard of Oz by
Roberts buda and then in this spread
this house is the box so if you look at
it end on you'll see there is a pillar
pushes up this little bit here and then
this is a piece that links the two outer
walls so this is using the box with the
book as a background rather than a base
so there is you can see just the way as
on this here's the original one I showed
you so you can see as it closes the lid
goes down but the the wall that locks it
all into shape that comes forward so in
effect what we've got in this case is
this this is the roof of the house going
up as it closes and here it is as it
closes you can see the roof of the house
going up so this on the side is another
separate interesting mechanism this is
the automatic pull strip that we look at
in tutorial 16 so this is the last one
and Brer Rabbit paper engineering by
Victor / white and here we have this is
the strap again and this is the the
tower
this is a box mechanism and at the end
here again we've got again it's built
onto a strap and this this pony and cart
that's a box mechanism you can see end
on there so you can see the central
pillar pushing up the lid the lid
pushing out the sides so that's the box
it's dealt with in detail in this my
book pop-up design and paper mechanics
you